Hello and welcome to a new set of
tutorials in the famous CAD
software Solid Works. So in this
tutorials we're going to use the Solid
Works 2014
the newest in this year.
So Solid Works is a very famous and most
used since it is strong CAD software
userfriendly with interactive interface.
So here you have your first interface
when you are starting your solid works
and here you have the file view tools
help the file you have the new open the
view the toolbarss
and they are still shortcuts until we
enter the parting or start a new part.
So here you have a quick shortcut new
and open
and here at the end if you open you have
the option
where you have the system options. We
are coming to this options later in this
tutorial and also you have the addins.
So, Solid Works has addins not only its
main job to make 3D modeling also you
can perform some specific studies like
simulation, routing and also you have
some tools that you are they are already
made that you can easily insert them
into your assemblies like bolts, screws.
So also you have another addins.
So for example, if you want an addins to
start an addins, you just pick it from
your menu here. And if you wanted to
start up with that,
you can check it. So I keep it unchecked
because that would save some time in
starting. So now let's start a new part.
To start a new part, you have the new or
from file new.
So you have three main types of parts or
files. The part is a simple 3D you are
creating
and then the assembly to assemble what
you have created in the parts
and assemble your final product drawing
a 2D presentation
at the it is a last stage to represent
your products to client or the
manufacturer.
So let's select part and then okay.
So here's the new part interface.
Here you are able to minimize it. And
here you have your part. And to the left
you see your part three.
And as you notice here, you have the
simul simulation icon is in here because
in the beginning we started it
and
also we going to talk about the units
because it is important to
choose your units. So now let's go to
the options menu.
From here if you take this option this
time you will notice the document
properties. You have the options here.
You can try to have a look quick look on
them. But the most important now we go
to the document properties
and then you go to the units and choose
the system you want.
So we are going to use the millimeter
gra second system. in all our tutorials.
So when you are done, click okay. So
when you are looking here at the bottom,
you'll see the used units and you are
able to change them quickly
to other system.
So I'm going to give you them to mm g
second.
Also if you look into the interface you
have these quick icons. Right now we
don't have any drawing part that we can
use them but they are easy to use and
they are like the zoom to fit zoom to
area the section view and how you are
viewing the orientations of your parts
the gyometry normal tool. So if you
notice this one is the normal tool which
bringing your part to the normal to the
face you select
and here you have on this under the
glasses you have different options
we be familiar with them when we
starting our parts.
So, in the next tutorial, we're going to
start the first sketch
and see the sketch
menus, functions, and tools.
Tutorial number two. In this tutorial,
we will start our first sketch. So, this
is the first tutorial. We going to start
working with Solid Works. We said to the
left you have the part three and the
most important
things to look at right now are the
planes. So you have three different
planes and you have the origin. So if
you remember in the mathematics you have
the origin with the coordinates of 0 0 0
and front plane you can imagine it like
the Z X coordinate top plane the XY and
so on.
So these are the views or the planes
where you are able to start your
sketching. So depending on the
orientation of your parts or how you
want it, you can select the plane you
want. So once you choose your plane
and click on it, you will see this
sketch. So that mean you are able to
insert a sketch on that plane. So let's
click on it. Now we are able to make a
sketching. So the sketch menu here is
activated if you go to it. So you have
the sketch tools. So it is
the starting from line the simplest tool
the corner and so on.
So we're going to have a look on the
sketch tools in the next tutorials.
So now let's start with the line
and let's start from the origin. So
solid works is user friendly. So it give
you marking to you and helping to choose
your points. And if you look at the
bottom you will see the coordinates of
your points. So if you put it on the
origin, you will get a 0 0
or coordinates. So now you can see your
coordinates here. So let's start from
the origin.
And now you can see the length of your
line.
So that is a helpful tool. So you know
the
the approximate length instead of making
small lines or bigger lines and then
redimensioning them that might miss your
sketch.
So
you can take it to be for example 100 mm
and when you click use selecting your
point you are still able to use the line
tool. So when you are done you can click
escape or right click select to end your
line tool. So another thing to use with
the line, let's select the line, pick
the point where we want
and if you notice this yellow
relation appears to that mean this line
is vertical. So when you are drawing you
have some relation as well.
For example, now if you hover over this
line,
you are able to select the middle point
and you see the relation appear next to
that tell you that is is a middle point.
So we can pick it. So now we know
there's relations.
So if you make it like this, you have
this relation. it is perpendicular to
that line.
So they are very helpful tool to help to
help you sketching and accurate in an
accurate way.
So if you want to show the relations on
your sketch, you said on the glasses
here you have the
view sketch relations.
when you select it. So you'll see the
relations in your
sketch. So you have the midpoints here,
have the perpendicular
relation and intersection here. So if
you want to delete uh so before deleting
a relation, if you want to pick that
point, try to move it. So you are able
to move the whole part. So and this
continue to be in the middle. So let's
click this point
right click delete or
simply click press delete on the
keyboard. So you deleted that relation
and if you pick that line so you are
able to move it freely from that line.
So the relations
playing an important role in your
sketching. So sometimes you need to
see for the relation if you are not able
to correct some or move some lines or so
on. So now let's return that relation
put it.
So we made it again here. So let's hide
the relation again.
So in the next tutorial we going to
continue talking about the sketching how
to use the line in another way and
adding the dimensions.
So see you in the next tutorial.
In the previous we knew how to start a
new part and sketch. So let's do it
again here as a repetition. Let's start
a new part. Click new part.
Okay. And then we're going to start a
new sketch this time on the top plane.
So click on it. Sketch. So now we are
able to start sketching. We have our
sketching tools. So let's pick the line
again and show you some tips how to use
the line. So let's start
from the origin.
And you know you know about relation
from previous tutori. We have vertical
relation here have horizontal
and again vertical.
And if you continue, you will be able to
continue making lines. But if you return
back, so you'll notice the icon is
changed to be double circle. That mean
you are able to start drawing an arc.
So you can find the place where
you want it. So now
when you are done so you can continue
drawing your lines
and again if back you are able to create
an arc and if you back again you will be
able to draw an bigger arc.
So depends
on your
type of sketching. So again
here we are closing our sketch.
So if you notice at the sketch you have
some lines are with the black color and
the rest are in the blue colors or dark
blue colors. So that mean these lines
are defined
and the rest they are not defined. So in
this case these lines having a starting
point and or ending point for this line
on the origin and as you know the origin
is a defined place. So on the rest they
are missing something to be defined. So
to do the definition you need to make a
some dimensions.
So there comes the dimensions smart
dimension tool. So if you click on that
and select the line, you'll be able to
add the dimension you want.
So let's add 60 mm and then press enter.
So let's again choose diameter or
dimension for this line.
And if you hear roll
below, you are able to
change
the dimension. Or if you click on the
arrow, you can also
change the dimension
or simply click the the value you want.
And here you have duty that is the name
of that line. So in the advanced
tutorials you'll be able to make the
dimension parametric or controlled by
some equation or so on. So but for now
let's just select the dimension to be
120. Click on
then okay.
So we are able now to continue adding
more dimension
until we define our part.
So you notice now the lines are
changing.
So here if you look at the bottom you'll
notice that the sketch is underdefined.
So that mean you are still need to
define your sketch. So let's add some
more dimensions. This is the last
dimension.
Okay. And here you look fully defined.
So that is important if you want to make
a good sketching to define your
sketches.
So this is uh user friendly way to tell
you if you are missing some dimensions
or not.
So if you added your dimension, you are
still able to reedit your dimensions by
double click on it
and you are able to change
then click okay.
If you want to delete a dimension
click it on the keyboard
delete or right click delete. So you see
here the line is here not defined. So
let's delete more lines.
Select delete.
So there is another way how to define
your sketch but it's not used very
commonly because mostly you are adding
your dimensions. you know dimension you
want but sometimes it can be used if you
go to the display delete relation
expand that menu you will see the fully
defined sketch. So if you click on that
solid war going to calculate the message
dimensions and add them to your sketch.
So calculate. So you have now there are
no solution because this overdefined. So
let's undo
click
and delete and let's delete all the
dimensions
again. Let's go to fully define sketch
calculate.
So solid wars automatically
make your dimensions.
When you are done, click okay.
We have this sketch from the previous
tutorial. So if you notice to the corner
you have this
X and the exit sketch
icon. So when you are in the sketch mode
so you'll notice that is appearing here.
So when you are done with your sketch
you need to exit from the sketch mode by
clicking on that icon. So when you click
on that, so now you are outside the
sketch mode and you notice the color is
changed. And when you are done with your
sketch, you will notice to the left that
your sketch has a name
on the
left tree. So you are able to rename it
by right click
and then you can
then you go to the feature properties
and write the new name and here you have
descriptions.
Okay. Or a faster way just
one click on that then you are able to
rename that sketch. You can type first
sketch then press enter.
So when you are selecting your sketch
you notice the dimensions are appearing
on that sketch. And also one thing you
are able to edit your dimension outside
the sketch node as well. So you can
so this is a new feature in the so the
new so it works versions that they are
saving times you are able to change
dimension here directly. So,
and here you have the icons. We said
we're going to use them along with the
tutorials. Here you have the zoom in and
zoom out. So if you here select an area,
we're able to zoom
then zoom out.
So now you have the 2D sketch that is
ready to be working with
further for this tutorial. Now I'm going
to show you a fast or quick way to start
to work with your sketch. If you go to
the feature, these are the 3D modeling
tools. And for just quick a start for
your solo, just if you extrude and you
need to select a sketch. So let's select
that sketch
extrude it. So now you are able to
extrude. So this is a very fast start
to give you an idea how you're going to
use your sketches. So either you can
extrude, revolve, sweep, cut and so on.
We are going to talk about this feature
in the future tutorials.
In this tutorial, we're going to
continue talking about the sketching and
also going to talk about how to use the
mouse. So, in the previous tuto, we
created this
fast 3D model or extrude and now I'm
going to show how to use the mouse. So,
the mouse is the most used way to
rotate, move, zoom in, out your part. So
to rotate your part just on the middle
wheel keep clicking on that and then
rotate your mouse. You notice the icon
of the mouse change to rotating move. So
the wheel, keep continue pressing on the
wheel and move your mouse
to zoom in and out. Also with the mouse
wheel,
we can roll up and down to zoom in and
out.
Also, you can use the keyboard arrows to
rotate your parts. So now let's show you
another thing. There is also view
orientation for your part. Here if you
click
you will see the view or plane
where you are able to choose your plane.
So if you don't see this cube so you can
activate it with this view selector.
If you don't want to see it just
deactivate it. So if you hover here, so
you are able to choose how to view your
part from top plane,
side, left, front and so on.
So here you can select how you going to
see your part. So these are important
for the future modeling. So you are able
to use that
view or surface to make more sketching
and
the rotate
and also you have an important icon the
normal too. So that is giving you the
normal view. So for example select this
face go to normal too. So now it's
showing you the normal to view.
So now again let's get back to sketching
because sketching is important as a
first step before start making 3D
models.
So here we have this extruded part
and if you expand it you will see your
first sketch here. So this extrude use
that sketch and again you are able to
get back to your sketch and edit again.
So if you click on it here you see edit
sketch. So it is not inserting a sketch
is edit sketch. If you click on it let's
go to normal tool.
Now you see your original sketch. So you
are able to change the dimension. Click
okay
and then exit as we learned before.
So now you have the extrude already
updated
to your new sketch dimension.
So let's again
you select that face. We said also
before you are able automatically change
the dimensions. If you want to get back
to the sketch
also you can select it or double click
on it. Select
normal tool.
And as you notice that the features menu
deactivated
and the sketch is active that you are in
the sketch mode. So, we're going to
continue talking about the sketching. We
already talked about dimensions
and the line. In the next tutorial,
we're going to talk about the rectangle.
So, we're going now in the next
tutorial, you talking about the
sketching
before start working with some feature.
Tutorial number six in Solid Works.
Let's start a new part.
And as we said, today we're going to
talk about rectangle. Let's select the
plane to start our sketch as we learned
before. And now we are in the sketch
mode. So the next after line is the
corner or the rectangles. And if you
hover or expand that menu, you have the
five different types of rectangles. So
the first corner rectangle is you are
picking the corner points to create your
rectangle. So first point, second point
or second corner point. Then you having
your rectangle
and also you are able to select the type
of rectangle from the menu to the left.
So if you select this one now you are
able to make the center point rectangle.
So the center point rectangle is a very
helpful tool
will be used in many of the example.
So we have a list for hundreds of
examples in solid works. You can find
that play playlist in the links
in this channel. So so now let's use the
center point rectangle.
Now you're making that rectangle.
So let's again select the center point.
Let's first make a two corner point
again here.
And if you want to make a center point
rectangle with the same corner rectangle
kind of
not
easy job to find and then you're going
to dimensions
many times until you get to your center
rectangle. So let's Ctrl C
to undo what we done. Then select the
center point rectangle.
Here if you hover over there you see the
middle point
and if you hover here you will see also
the middle point too. So now we have the
center point of this rectangle. If you
select it
very simply, you are creating a
rectangle in the center of the
rectangle.
So you can see how helpful that
rectangle is.
Also have a third type of rectangle
three points corner rectangle. You
notice that rectangles are horizontals
but you can make your own orientation or
angular view to your rectangle. So you
can select three points and create
rectangular
or with an angle a rectangle with an
angle.
So
can see or understand the idea of this
angled rectangle. And here again we have
the center point rectangle with an
angular.
So we can select any point and create a
center rectangle.
And the last one is the parallel
This is not rectangle but it has a
parallel
edges
as you remember in the math. So these
are the five different types of
rectangles. And one last thing I want to
show you in the line menu if you expand
it you have a center line. So center
line is easy to understand. It is for
making a center line.
But if you remember in the engineering
drawing lessons this type it has
dot hash that indicate is a center line.
So you can make it
here.
So that indicate we have a center line
for that rectangle.
And if you select one of these lines or
let's again the line make a line here in
the option you have
you select it here in the option have
for construction.
If you select that so now you have a
construction line. So this line can be
used as a reference for your sketching
and drawing as a helping tool and also
the center point can show you some
references in your sketching.
So this is
all about this tutorial and see you in
the next tutorial.
Tutorial 7, we're going to continue
talking about the sketch tools.
So, let's go to the sketch menu
and
let's try a new way to start a sketch.
So, now we are not in the sketch mode
and you notice
not all the sketch tools are activated.
Let's select uh a slot
here. And now you'll notice that solid
works give you three planes. You can
rotate with the mouse as we knew how to
rotate.
So you see you have three different
planes shown to you. So maybe can give
you a better viewing to the orientation.
So let's select the top plane here. Now
we are in the top plane menu. So let's
click on the normal two here or from
the
orientation
menu normal true. So we are normal to
the sketch. So this we're going to talk
about the slots and circles. The slots
they are quite easy to use. If you see
the
explaining figures here on SL works
and let's select the straight slot.
Simply select two point then your slot
is done. You have a center point slot.
You can make your slot depending on your
center point. Select that point.
Now
have another slot circle slot where you
are able make your slot in on an arc.
The last one is the center point arc
slot.
So you select that is the center to be
of your slot and you can create it the
way you want. So now
have that slot.
So now when you're done. Okay.
So the one is more used is the next
which is the circle. You have two type
of circles. The one you are able to make
it from the center point or you define
it by three points. So let's start the
first circle. You can select the center
point where you want to draw your circle
and then your circle is done. And
dimensioning. We learn how to add the
dimensions. Just you click on that
circle and add the dimensions. They're
machining the slots also on the same way
but you have two dimensions need to be
added to the slot. Let's add 50 here and
let's add the second dimension
to be 150.
So, so let's add the relation here. If
you click that point that point you'll
notice that relation
icons appearing
select consent. Okay, your slot is
defined. So we take we going to make a
tutorial about the adding constraints.
So for now we have this circle is made.
Now let's start making a circle tangent
in three points. So let's click this
line
this circle
or so now we have two lines selected
they are inside these two lines.
Then the third one you can select that
arc or that point or you can select this
point to be clear to you. So now you
created your circle inside three points
you are selecting. So let's try it
again. Let's make a center point
rectangle.
Select the threepoint circle. Select
this line, this line, this line. Your
circle is inside or tangent with these
three lines.
Tutorial number eight. Let's start a new
sketch on top plane.
Now, let's go to the next sketch tool,
the arc. If you expand the menu, you
have three different types of arcs. And
this time you don't need to draw a whole
circle. You can just draw your arcs. So
let's try to make a center point
rectangle in the origin. And now let's
activate the three points arc. So here
you see the three points arc shaded in
here. And you can see a hint how you can
use that
or where you place your points. the
first point, second point and third
point. So here you can select first
point
and second point. Now you can specify
the radius
few.
So you are done. Click there. So you are
done. So the second time is the two
points arc. And this time you are not
able to change in this case two points
you are not able to change in the radius
of your arc. So you have only one choice
will be defined to be as a tangent. So
let's select this two point. First point
second point
let's try.
So here you see your your arc. So you
can select a different place you are
able to see your arc. So here is your
arc. So it give you an arc with radius
between these two points. So this is the
only way to get that arc.
Let's try to use it with two lines here.
Let's select the two points arc. Select
this point. This point.
So this is your arc.
And you have a third type where you can
choose your center point. your center
point. Then start to draw an arc from
that center point.
And now let's move to polygon is also
quite easy to use polygon.
Then choose the number of
edges three. If you select three simply
you're going to create a rectangle. So
this is a very fast way to use polygon
to create a very fast rectangle. And
there is two options
to make it outside the circle or inside
the circle. Here you can change the
number of your polygons
edges.
And then one thing
you can add the dimension
for your
polygon. And one thing I want to say if
you want to define it can select one of
the edges
activate this small dimension. Select
one edges. Uh the relation make
horizontal
then
make this point to the origin.
center point. So you define your
polygon.
So
this is a way how to define your
polygons.
The next tool in the sketch menu is the
spline. The actually one of the you can
consider it is the most difficult one to
use to be used between the sketch tools
and it is one of my favorite tools and
is flexible and can draw many shapes
especially in creating some complicated
surfaces. So in the splan you have four
different types. So the equationdriven
curve is quite advanced where you are
able to add equation to control the
shape of your splan. So it's quite
interesting and this plan on surface
we'll be using it on the surface tools
when we going in the stage when we are
ending with the sketch tools features
tools then we're going to use the
surface tools. And now we have two
splines. The first one is this. And you
have the second sty spline where you
have points and edge where to control
the spline
shape. So let's first choose the first
type of spline simple.
And now
we select
uh sketch. We did start a sketch spline.
Now
if you create a span with two points
only
now and then when you are done right
click select or escape. So you notice it
is a straight line but still you are
able to control change its shape. So
let's throw on the SPL three points
one point
to point3
or click select. If you click on this
line you'll notice each point has two
important things.
You have the handle and you have the
direction. So if you
select this,
you are able to change the size of the
handle
and the other one you're changing the
direction
of that spline edge. So you have two
things here to think about the size
and the handle.
So let's do it here again.
So now we are able to say
change size direction
also you are able to move
the points.
Sometimes it is healthy practice to use
as less points as possible in the spline
to be more simpler to use.
So if you select your spline right click
you have another options to add for your
spline.
So you have insert a spline point.
You select where to add a point. So you
have inserted a point. Then you are
done. Escape. Click escape. Then you
have your new point added to that spline
plan.
And in the spline plan you can add
dimension as well. You can select two
points
and add dimension between them.
This is one way to control your spline.
Also, we said you have size and
direction.
So, you are able to add dime for that.
So, let's add
size for your handle.
You can add 50.
You can notice the different and also
you have an angle. So let's draw a line
here. Simple line.
Select smart dimension. Select your
spline edge. And this line you have an
angle.
Add
to your spline edge.
So there's many way to control your
splan
and you are also able to add relations
too. So if you select that point just
deactivate the dimension by click no
escape select this
point. So you have some relation can be
added. So let's try
select this
handle.
you have add relation horizontal.
So you have a horizontal relation added
to that spline plan.
So you can try to review what we said
cuz plan is quite
need some practices to be able to use it
in a good way. And now you have a second
type of spline with the guiding line
as a way for more control to your
spline.
So you notice
your spline is
contained inside
these guiding edges or lines. So if you
select that point
from that point you are able to control
your spline.
So as you notice you don't have the
handle and the size as shown in the
previous type of spline.
[Music]
So let's for example add line
smart dimension. Select this point and
that line. So
can add
dimension to your
guiding
midpoint relation here.
So this is an idea how you can work with
your spline two different ways.
So I hope this tutorial was useful and
gave you an idea about
the display plan using control adding
dimension.
Number
10, the mix tool in sketching. Let's
start new part. Start sketch
and choose the ellipse. The mix tool in
sketching. And there is four different
types. Here in this menu, you have the
ellipse, partial ellipse, parabola, and
connect. Let's start an ellipse. The
ellipse can be done with two direction.
the horizontal and the vertical. So once
you are selected your
first direction, horizontal direction
then you start with your
vertical dimension or vertical direction
and in this smart dimensioning you can
add dimensions in these two different
directions. So here's the first
um
second
dimension
and you have also relations. So let's do
some relations.
This deactivate the smart dimension
tool. Select this point, this point,
this point. So when you are selecting
these three points, you can add a
relation horizontal relation. When
you're done, okay, you define your
ellipse.
So, we are talking about the relations
with the sketching. So, the relation is
an important tool for defining and
making your sketches.
So, let's try the second type of
ellipse. Partial ellipse.
We are doing
partial ellipse.
the same idea
as arc in circle.
Now you are done your partial ellipse.
So
this is how it looks. So you are able to
move
your sketch if you click on that. But in
this ellipse you are not able to move it
because you have a midpoint
and the horizontal
or you have this intersection relation
or coincident with the origin. If you
click that and delete it your sketch
ellipse is undefined. You are able to
move it. So let's move it again and add
origin. And you notice the relation is
activated.
So here you can add dimension on the
same way
second direction
and you need one more dimension
the gap in the partial
ellipse. Select these two make a gap of
34.
Let's delete that
and select these two points and adding
dimension the way you are moving your
mouse the way you're showing the
dimensions. So if you make it horizontal
dimensioning you have 31.47.
If you make it par to the gap so you
have it 34.8.
And if you make it vertical, you have
14.97.
So you have to know exactly which
dimension to add.
I make it parallel to the gap. I can add
35 here. Let's add one more relation.
Let's make it
vertical to the origin. Pick
stick pick this point this point and
here you have a vertical relation. This
quick menu. Uh one last dimension
between the origin.
So you have your ellipse to fully define
your ellipse. fully defined. Calculate.
So here is your ellipse is defined.
So now let's move to the next. In this
menu you have the parabola tonic.
Parabola is something you
should be familiar with. You start at
the center point of your parabola and
then
you start drawing it.
So it's quite rare to be used unless you
have some special
sketches.
And the next one is conic.
So you see you need four points to
create your clinic.
Three
four.
So it's quite
interesting way to make a conic in the
end of that rectangle.
Let's make one.
instead for example that I'm making
an arc.
So this is a brief tutorial how to use
this conics and parabola.
Good morning. Let's start a new sketch
on the front plane
and let's go to the next
feature in the sketch menu. We have the
sketch fillet and if you expand it you
have sketch chamfer. So to use the
sketch fillet we can do some
sketches here can make two lines
can make
rectangle.
Now let's activate the sketch fillet.
Here you need the radius for your
fillet. Let's make it 5 mm.
And then either to select the two edges
to create the fillet
and then right click on the mouse or
okay here.
Or you can directly select the corner.
Let's make it thin here.
then run down. Okay.
And let's show you one thing else. Let's
activate the clip.
And here we have this corner selected.
And we choose dimension each flip and
keep the constraint corner.
And now
instead of selecting each corner you can
right click or selecting you can see
that
pencil.
Now you selected all the corner included
in that then okay. So this is quite
faster and now we use or check the
dimension each fillet. So we see the
dimensions in each fillet. So for
example, let's make another
example.
We have many corners here.
Let's
fill it. Use this. Then select
all chips.
So in one click you made all the fillets
to all these parts. So while selection
so when you go to the right click you
can see the type of selection box
selection or lasso selection. If you
select
box you'll be able to make box
selection. So now let's go to next menu.
We have the sketch chamfer. So it is
almost the same idea but it's creating
uh chamfer.
So let's make two
tankers.
Activate chamfer. So in the chamfer you
have two types added to select the
distance two equal distance.
And here you have to check it or the
angle distance. Let's first use the
equal distance.
Select this
edge is not working in the case of the
chamfer.
So let's let's just select the corners.
Uh apply the chamers.
And here you see the cher equal
distances.
And when you are done click okay. And
you notice these red icons that means
they are
driven or associated with other
dimensions. In this case they are equal.
Let's again cher
select and check the equal distance and
here let's make two different distances.
Choose this
and let's reverse.
Let's click okay. Then sharper
make it 10
or five
by 10.
So you have to
different distances.
Again let's create the last rectangle
and
select
chamfer this case let's choose the angle
we can make 30° angle
to mm
okay
this time 60
5 mm m.
Okay. So here you see distance is five
and 60 mm
and here too.
So here are the different cases of the
chamber.
Tutorial 13. Let's move to the next
feature. In the sketch menu, we have
plane, text, and point. So, we're going
to see the plane, insert the PL into 3D
sketch. In this case, we don't have a 3D
sketch. What we have is a 2D sketch. So,
let's exit this sketch and show you what
is the 3D sketch. When you go to the
sketch here and expand the sketch, you
have sketch which we are already using
the simple 2D sketching and you have 3D
sketch. So we'll try to make a lesson on
that. It will be almost using the same
tools like in the sketch but on three
directional way.
And also you can find the 3D sketch icon
in the web
tools. So this is the 3D sketch. It is
very nice to solid works that you can
create in a 3D directions.
So let's go to the sketch here.
Edit sketch.
We are back to our sketch here. and
let's use the text. So in the text there
is nothing special. Here is the curves
where you can use the text. Let's select
this line. So you have the line selected
and you can type
[Music]
thing you want.
And here
can make it
bold color it
little rotation.
So this quite word
work you can in the middle or
to the left
under or up or to reverse. You need this
reverse
case of moles or getting the negative
and let's click okay. Let's try the
text on a curve. Let's select this
curve. This line
right
arrow
to
box. So you see the arc and line they
were selected and you have your text on
them. So let's try to reverse direction
and then you are done. Okay. So you are
also able to make a text on curse.
So the next option we have the point.
The point also is a useful tool can be
used to insert points, helping points in
sketching or references
or so on. For example, we can make a
reference here.
So we have this point is a reference. We
can use it to draw a line for example
from here
to this corner.
And also you can insert points on lines.
So you can see that relation the
intersection relation ch and as well you
can add dimension for your points.
[Music]
Let's make a dimension from this point
this point.
Also you can make dimension
for points in space.
So this is tutorial about the text point
in solute works.
Let's start a new sketch on top plane
and let's go to the next feature. We
have trim. If you expand it, you have
trim entities or extend entities. So,
let's first work with the trim entities.
Let's create some intersecting lines.
So now we have these
three lines and now we have the excess
line in here and here. So let's try to
trim that line to look better. We can
use the trim.
So in the trim you have
five different types of trim. The
easiest one to use is power trim. It is
automatically detect your trimming
object and do your trim. So to use the
power trim, just
keep clicking on the left mouse
and make a line.
So you are trimming and again
holding the left mouse button move then
you are trimming.
Ctrl C. This trim we have power trim.
You can also trim both of them at once
by clicking by drawing the trimming
line.
And the next one is the corner.
Let's make Ctrl C the corner. This is
from its name. You have to select two
lines. Then you're going to trim the
corner to that corner. So let's again
select this one. This one. So we have
that corner. Let's trim it. Let's make
hello line.
Trim corner. This line and this line. So
you are trimming to that corner which
you used
and you have different types of
trimming. They are
quite need some selection or some kind
of
uh special sketches but the most used
are the the power trim can do most of
the job. So let's have an idea how to
use trim away inside. We have these two
edges. Let's make
lines.
Let's activate the trim and trim away
inside. So you can understand from the
or from the figure the type of trim. So
let's select this line and this line. So
we have
this.
So you're trimming the inside.
So control C.
Let's trim trim away inside. Select that
line. This line. Now you are able to
trim everything in between these two
lines. If you select that, so you are
trimming. Ctrl C. Let's try the next
type. Trim away this line.
Select. So now you are doing the
opposite. Trim away outside.
And now you have the trim to closest.
Make Ctrl C
trim to closest. So if you select that
edge, so it will be trimming to the next
closest edge. So this is about trim. And
now let's try to use the extend. The
extend is trying to extend your lines
more.
So let's have
this shape.
And now you have this edge is
short and we need to extend it to
to meet the second edge. You can use
that with the extend entities.
And now you notice you extended that
line be one long line. So you have your
triangle. Now you can
trim
with power trim. Trim that edge.
So you have your triangle
also. Let's try to extend this lines.
Extend. Select that line.
You extend it to the next edge
as well.
This line.
So I guess now it is clear the trim and
the extend
entities feature in sketching
tutorial 15. Let's start a new sketch on
the top plane.
And in this tutorial we're going to talk
about the convert entities an important
and timesaving tool in sketching.
So to let you understand the convert
entities working we can try make some
different examples.
Let's try first make a sketch here.
Can be any kind of sketching.
So we have this sketch done. So let's
exit from that sketch.
So we have sketch one and let's try to
make a sketch two on the top plane two.
So we have top plane insert insert a
sketch the same plane as sketch one. And
now if we have
to make the same sketch as in sketch one
either to try it from start from scratch
draw lines and follow the path. If you
have complicated sketch, it can be not
easy work to do. But you can do that in
just
few clicks. So you can select these
lines
and then convert entities.
So now we have two sketching that they
are lying on each other. So maybe it's
quite unlogical they're having two
sketching in the same
plane but it is an example to show you
how to convert entities because it
should have in logical cases you can be
two planes par to each other and you
want to make the same sketch on two
different planes par together but we
still didn't take the lesson about
inserting planes and drawing on
reference planes But this is the idea
how you can use the convert entities to
convert and existed
the sketch instead of drawing it from
scratches.
So let's exit this sketch. So we have
two sketching laying on each other. So
if you press
that and click hide. So you have the
second sketch still there.
So also you can convert entities if the
second sketch on
a different plane par to the sketch. For
example, we have that sketch on the top
plane. Let's make the sketch on front
plane. So we are assembling a sketch.
Let's make it normal too. Now you are
able to select
these lines
and convert them convert them to
to sketch convert entities.
Now let's rotate a little bit here. So
now you have that projected line which
represent the converted entities from
sketch one.
So this is another example.
And now also let's show a different
example. Let's extrude one of the
sketches here.
Okay.
Now
let's just insert a sketch here. We
didn't take that lesson but let's
quickly do it. If you select that face
you have the in the sketch or insert
sketch in that plane.
Now you are able to
select these lines or even you can
select
chain
convert entities.
So you have these selected lines
converted. So let's control C select
them
again
convert entities. So you have that
sketch on that face on that 3D face.
Exit. Let's try to hide
the extruded or solid face.
Now you can see
you have two prior sketches
each other.
Tutorial 16. Let's start a new sketch on
top plane. And let's take the next
feature in the sketch menu, the offset
entities. To use offset entities, we
have to create a sketch.
So let's create
rectangle center point rectangle.
And let's make fillet.
Okay.
So, let's activate offset.
And the offset is making uh is
duplicating the existing sketch making
some sketch parallel
or offset to it.
And here you have the option add
dimension or reverse
the the offset plates or by directional
can create sketch on both sides. So
let's change the offset to be 2 mm
and okay.
So you have created your offset.
So it is time saving. You don't need all
the time to create an offset. If you
wanted, you can just use offset
entities.
Now you can make an offset
from
one of these sketches or offset
sketches. Let's uncheck re directional
and
make base construction.
Okay.
So when you use when you check it the
base construction it make the original
sketch to be for construction
and that one that you made the one you
will be used.
So in the offset you can create an
offset and delete or make the original
one as construction and start working
with the new offset sketch.
Tuto
mirror entities. The next after the
offset entities we have the mirror
entities is also a timesaving tool which
is eliminating the time for creating a
new sketching by using some type of
mirror as well as the convert and
offset. All these are sketch
manipulation tools. They are time saving
and so on. For example, if we want to
make the same sketch like this one
to be on the opposite side.
So that need some time to be created.
But you can do it by mirroring the same
this sketch on a mirroring line. So
let's try to make a line here to be
parallel to
this edge.
Escape. So this line can be a mirror
line. So we can convert it into
construction as well.
Now we have a mirror axis.
And let's activate the mirror. And here
entities to mirror. You can select which
part you want to mirror. So I want to
mirror.
So let's make sure that we are in
here you are selecting
you want to mirror and here you have the
mirror about which should be the mirror
line.
So you notice that we made the same
sketch mirrored on that line.
Okay.
The same way we can mirror the whole
sketch. Just activate mirror entities
and select the whole sketch by selecting
box
mirror about.
So we are done. Okay. So we made a
mirror copy from the
sketch. So let's try to make another
line to make it
inclined that like this. Let's convert
it into construction.
Also we are able to mirror this
sketching on that line. Let's make
mirror.
Select this
and uncheck. Copy
that line. Okay.
So you see when we didn't
check the copy
we are having only one side
to be used.
So let's do it again where entities
click.
Make sure that you are not selecting the
green line
about and let's check copy here. So
we'll have two copies
original and the mirror.
Tuto 18. We're going to talk about the
next feature in the sketch menu. The
linear sketch pattern is also a sketch
manipulation tool which save times and
creating copies and instant instances
from existed sketch. Let's start sketch
on top plane. Let's make a rectangle
and let's make here
circle.
Okay. So one note we have we have here
the mirror and the linear pattern. But
if you go to the feature you have also
the mirror and the pattern but they are
different because this one in the
feature mode you are working on the
solid or 3D parts but in the sketch it's
working on the 2D or sketch level. So
let's activate the linear sketch feather
and here is the x-axis is selected. The
distance between the instances and the
number of distances. So we select the
two here and 10. Let's make the distance
to be 20 mm.
Increase the number of instances.
So you see you are creating copies or
duplicating that existed circuit instead
of drawing them all the time. This is
distance between to be 30. So when you
are done can okay.
So again let's try to
make instance on that direction.
Let's activate the linear pattern edges.
For example, let's delete this. select.
So not is not able to select that
direction.
So now let's just here deactivate the
direction one because we don't want to
make it one. So now it is deactivated.
Now let's make the direction two is the
y-axis.
And here the line to pattern
clear selection and select this circle
the number of instances.
So we can make
six instances
and the the spacing
20.
Here we can just delete this line. need
only the circle and to change the
direction
can click on that arrow or here you can
make the change the the degrees but on
the arrow is easier to make the
direction.
So when you are done
click okay.
Also you have one option down instances
to skip. So for example you don't need
all these six you need some of them. So
you can activate the instance to skip
and you not there is point
shown in that circle. So if you select
that circle it will be skipped.
So now let's make another example. Let's
make the pattern to be not on the XY or
in the X direction or Y direction to be
something in between. So in this case
there's a angular manipulation. Let's
clean your
sketch pattern.
Let's select entities to pattern this
circle.
And here you have the angle. You can set
it into 30° angle. Let's make the
instances to be five spacing 30.
So you can flip direction there. So if
the angle of 30 is not the one we need,
we can make it 2
90.
Here
you can
change
to the
angle you want
instances.
You are done. Okay.
So we showed you three different cases
how to use the linear pattern.
The previous tutoal about the linear
pattern
and there is a different type also
called the circular pattern where you
are able to make the pattern on a
circular shape.
So here we have the origin. It will be
the center of the circular pattern.
Let's try to make a circle
here. And let's make some instances in a
circle from that origin. Let's activate
the circular pattern. Now you have
that
circular pattern around
here. We have the point one which is
origin
and
the number of instances
can change it here either to use equal
spacing
or not.
And you can also make pattern around
270°
angle or less.
And okay,
if you want to make a circle pattern not
on that center point,
just
make another circle pattern.
And let's change the direction the place
of that center circle. Here you have the
coordinates
of
the new
circular pattern circuit.
Now let's make stances
10.
They are done.
Okay,
tutorial 20. This tutorial we're going
to talk about the next feature in the
sketch menu. We have this sketch from
the previous tutorial. Let's enter that
sketch mode. Hit sketch. Now we are in
that sketch. So here you have the move
entities. Let's activate and move the
entities we want. So let's select
all these
and
all these as well.
So we have all these entities selected.
Now let's move them.
So here from two
let's
activate
the parameter of movement.
So let's select
start point
end point. So you are move that
selected entities to that point new
point.
So again let's
select the entities.
We can make Ctrl A that we can select
everything. Let's
move entities.
Start point
is this one.
Uh let's make the
end point
for example the origin.
So here we move our entities.
But as you notice we moved the entities.
We didn't keep the original ones. So we
have the copy entities in this case it
keeps the original one. So entities to
copy either to select some parts from
there or all the sketch I'm going to
select everything like Ctrl A and now
let's activate start point end point.
This is start point and let's make
another point.
We can make a point from before to be a
reference
and select it. Even we can stick that
point.
Now we have two copies from that.
So it is also can do the work of
linear pattern in case the linear
pattern didn't work. it was or it was
complicated to move some instances in
some different places or direction.
So, this might be easier
to make the copy and move as you want.
Today, in this tutorial, we're going to
talk about the rotate entities. We have
this sketch from previous tutorial
and
let's see how to rotate this
sketch
to go to the rotate in the move entities
expanded. You have rotate entities
and entities to rotate. Here you are
selecting the entities which you want to
rotate and you can keep the relations.
We talked about the relation before and
you have an idea how the relation are
and we are going to make
a tutorial for relation as well. So
let's select the outside edge.
So we have the outside profile is
selected and the center of rotation. You
have to select the center of rotation
the origin where your profile will be
rotating. I'm going to select this
point. So let's activate this field.
Select that. And now we are able to
rotate.
So you can notice how you rotate it. So
now you we already made that outside
profile is an offset from inside. So
that mean there are some connection
between so let's try if I'm checking
this can't fix anything. So now we
remove the relation
now we have no relations connecting that
outside profile with the inside.
So now we can continue increasing the
angle
until we get
to the angle we want. Let's try 180.
And here we have this rotation
270.
And this is the rotation. We are done.
Okay. So now let's try to rotate the
whole sketch. We can do that by clicking
Ctrl A.
Ctrl A or selecting all
the
sketch and then rotate entities.
And here the entities to rotate they are
all selected.
Now let's check the key relation because
in this case we will rotate the whole
sketch. So
and now let's try to find
center for of rotation be this point.
And now let's rotate it
120°
when you're done. Okay. So now you see
you are able to rotate the whole sketch.
The next tool is the scale entities. We
have this sketch from from previous
tutorial. So imagine if you want to
scale this sketch drawing by drawing it
with a smaller scale or bigger scale. It
will not be easy to make all the
sketches. will take some time to draw
that manually all the time. So you have
for this reason the scale entities
expand the move entities menu. Here you
have scale entities where you are able
to rescale your entities. So let's first
ctrl A select the entire sketch.
Okay. Or Ctrl A again.
Scale entities.
We have the entities we want to scale.
They all selected here. Scale about. We
need to pick a center point. For
scaling, let's make this point a center
point.
And the scaling, let's make
scaling to be two times bigger and if
you check copy it will keep the original
sketch. So let's check copy here
and you notice here you have
the copy and also you are able to make
instances on that. So we have now you
see the bigger scale showing
and click okay.
So we have the original small sketch and
then we have the bigger size sketch.
Let's ctrl C to undo.
And let's try
the other way to make a a smaller Scale
scale entities. Let's make
five half the size without checking the
copy. Let's select the center point. You
can select it somewhere in the space.
And here you have your smaller sketch.
So this is
uh rescaling for the half size of your
sketch.
Also you are able to rescale some part
of the sketch with the same idea.
Hello to another important tutorial in
solid works. We talked before that we
going to make a tutorial on relations.
So in this tutorial we're going to talk
in about relation in details. We talked
before briefly but now we're going to
talk about relation is the next feature
in the
sketch menu. So let's start a sketch on
top plane
and here we have the relations menu. you
have display, delete, relation, and if
you expand it, you have another options
as well. So now we don't have anything
here. Let's draw some random lines.
So we have two random lines here with no
without having any relation or any
definition
or relation. So for that case we can add
the relation. So the relation they are
kind of defining
some type of constraints in the sketch.
So here if you expand the display and
delete relation you have the add
relation. Right now if you go to the
display or delete relation we don't have
any relation to show. So let's add
relation first. Expand addation.
So now it's asking you to select
entities. So let's select this line. And
when you select that line here showing
you if there is existing relation in
this case we don't have any relation um
the relation available to us to make. So
we have the horizontal, vertical and
fix. So if you select the horizontal you
will make your line horizontal or
vertical. So you cannot add them
together because they will be
overdefined. So delete first the
horizontal.
Now your vertical relation is working.
So when you are done click okay.
So let's activate the add relation one
more time
and select
this line.
So we have these two lines are selected
and here you have the available
relations
whether to make them horizontal vertical
or so if you select vertical you'll make
the second line to be vertical as well.
I'm going to go to Ctrl C
and I want to join these two lines
together. So I'm going to clear
selections here. Try to find another
selections.
You can select this point instead
instead of the whole line and this
point. So we have these available
relations. So we want the merge
relation
and then you are done.
So without closing with before click on
okay you are able still to add more
relation. So let's add more relation
between the origin and this point. So
select this point
and the origin. So we have these two
points selected.
We have the
three type of relation we can add. We're
going to select the consent.
So now we have the center point
and this line are intersecting. So when
you are done click okay. Now you can go
and show the relation display and delete
relation. Here you see the relation
associated with point 4.
So here you have the entities to select
and if you expand it you can select all
the sketch or some options or selected
entities. You can pick all the sketch.
You'll have the vertical
and the conincent relation available
here in this sketch.
So now you're showing your relation.
Also if you go here
with the glasses you have an option to
view sketch relation.
So if you activate it your relation will
be all the time showing here and if you
have many relation it can be kind of not
showing the sketch real sketch clearly
you can deactivate them and let them
work when you want. So one last thing
you are also able to delete relation
here. You can display our delete. This
one is selected
and you see it here on the sketch.
Delete. Also you have other option
suppress. For example, if you select
this relation is selected here.
Suppress.
And now you have this relation is
suppressed. So that mean it has no
effect right now unless you're going
back to activated. So let's go back and
display relation. So we have this
coincident
relation
is suppressed. So uncheck this one.
Okay. So your relation is back to work
and now you are not able to move it from
the origin.
Done. So let's show some other type of
relation. Let's draw a circle
and okay
you can also add the relation without
choosing this add relation I option. You
can simply select that circle control
select this line. you had it selected
and here is the tip duration you can
apply it.
Let's draw another circle. There's also
another
way faster way to do
this circle. Select this line and this
small menu is appear. It's showing you
some relation that you can add. So make
tangent.
Okay.
So let's make underline here.
Select this line. This line and here you
have some of available relation. So if
you make colinear you have the colinear
and okay
and this again show the relation.
Pick one of them.
Click delete. So you are able to delete
from the keyboard
as well.
And again you can move freely your
entities. So I hope this tutorial was
useful and that you understand more
about relations this important topic.
In this tutorial, we're going to start
working with the solid models or 3D
modeling after we finish the talking
about the important tools in the sketch
entities. So before working with feature
is better to have a good knowledge in
the sketch entities and feature. So the
basic to make a good solid modeling
start from making good sketches. So
let's now start working with the
features or solid
features.
So basically are for creating the 3D
models. So we have the extrude, revolve,
sweep, lo and so on. We're going to deal
with all these feature in the tutorials.
So first feature is the extrude boss.
So let's start making a sketch.
As we know, let's make circle
rectangle
and let's make slope.
We have three different profiles.
Let's except
the sketch or without exiting the
sketch, you still able to work with the
extrude. So here is the extrude is
activated. So now let's select extrude
feature. And now you notice you are
extruding your part
all the
drawn sketches. And you see this arrow.
This is a quick extruding option. When
you select that arrow, you are able to
expand it or change its direction
downward. So it's kind of quick way to
create extrusion
and sometimes you need to make some
quick solid models without
having exact dimension.
So that is a quick way to make it.
And now let's move to the left
menu. Here you have the type of the
extrude. Blend is just can move it the
way you want. And here you have
other options. You have up to vertx. For
example, if you have another body in
front or other edges, you can select the
vertex. And if you have a surface in
front, you can also select that surface.
and up body. But in this case, we have
the mid plane. We can start working with
it. So if you pick mid plane, so you
notice you have your extruded is in a
mid plane.
So if you select the mid plane, you
notice the second direction is not
activated because it is extruding in two
directions equally. So let's make blend
extrusion. And here you have the
distance you wanted. So if you type 70,
you have 70 the exact
value you want 80
or 50 as you want.
And if you want to change the direction,
you have these the flip or this icon
reverse direction. So you have on the
other direction.
So let's make it there.
And here you have the draft on or off.
So when you are making extrusion, this
first make okay. Let you see how the
extrusion looks like. Now you have this
extrusion
parts
and you can edit the existing extrusion.
You can
click on it and here edit feature. So
you are able to edit that feature again.
So here you have the draft. You can
apply some draft. So you can let's make
the angle to be
little bit there 10°. So you understand
this angular extruded part. So this is
the idea of draft. And here if you
select the
draft outward. So you are drafting
outward. Now let's continue to direction
two you are able to make a second
direction for extrusion. the same way
with the same options if you want to
have a draft or not. So here you can
make it 20 not necessarily to be equal
and the draft you can make it
zero or or deactivate it again.
So now you have extrusion in two
directions.
Okay. So this is how it looks.
So let's back again continue talking
about extrusion. Let's edit feature. And
now here you have
the selected contours.
That mean you are able to select
some of the sketching to be extruded not
all the sketch. For example, we have
sketch containing many profiles but we
want to extrude some of them. So let's
select what we want to extrude.
So it should be close profile.
Let's extrude both of these. And we have
the options. We already took the one.
When you are done, click okay.
In this tuto, we're going to talk about
appearance
because I wanted to change the color in
this tutorial, but I want to show how to
change the colors
before
asking how this color is changed. So, I
want to show how this is done because I
will be changing colors in the next
tutorials. So, that will not be strange
for you. So to change the color you have
this edit appearance menu here. If you
click on it so you'll be able to
select the colors you want. So now here
you are selecting the color for the
entire bodies and here select geometry.
Here you have select part and you have
select faces. So if you select faces you
are able to change the color of the
face. So let's here delete
that part. Now select the faces you
want. So you'll be able to change that
face.
So if you don't want to
that face, you can delete it. So this is
how you can apply the colors.
And here you have the
the values this colors and so on. And
here if you have surface but in this
case we don't have surfaces and select
bodies and so on. So the body is almost
close to the part but the body is
selecting only one body not the whole
parts. If you select part it going to
select.
So it will consider all these bodies as
one part but in the bodies you are able
to select this
separated body. For example let's not
make green
and make
and select that body. We're selecting
the
change it color.
Also, there is another way to change the
type of the material.
You go to the edit appearance in here
and here you have the appearances
plastic so on
and drag it or just
select body select
double click you will be able to
apply the appearance.
So let's take this body
take that
more body or from solid bodies you can
select from there.
Now you are able to change color. This
is a quick tutorial about change the
colors because in the next tutorial when
we going to continue talk about the
feature
with when you have different colors you
know how we
change that. So we'll just back our main
tutorials. We continue talk about the
feature in here and that will be in the
next tutorial.
In the previous tutorial, we know that
we can insert a sketch by selecting the
plane and inserting a sketch.
And here you're going to show another
way to insert a sketch is not necessary
to be on the main planes. So you can
insert a sketch on any flat surface you
can see. So we have this part from the
previous tutorial and we have flat
surfaces on the top of them. So if you
pick that surface you'll notice this
sketch icon the same when we are
clicking on planes. So if you pick the
icon and notice here you have the
exit sketch that mean you are on the
sketch
mode
and here you have your sketch features
which we talked about them before. So go
to normal too and now you can sketch
normally as we learned before.
in creating a sketch. So let's pick a
center point here. If you hover over
this line, you see the center point and
here is center point. So
um the origin. So
make a center point rectangle
and we are done. Okay,
that's it.
So we have a rectangle in the top of
that plane. But now if you select that
surface,
you don't have that sketch icon. Here
you have edited sketch means the
original sketch engaged in that surface
which we made before for creating the
extruding part. So this is not inserting
a sketch.
But if you select that surface,
you have this sketch icon.
Now you are able to
create a sketch in that surface.
So you can make it normal too by
clicking the icon. If you don't see it,
you can go here and normal two.
So we can
make a circle in the middle.
of that. So if you are not able to see
this center line
and create a center line from here
circle
and you make it on the center of that
line
you want add animation can do it.
This is not it's not the purpose of this
tutorial and we are done except
so we have sketch
on that surface and on the top of that
surface.
So now it is important that you know we
can insert sketches on surfaces
which we are able to work with them
further. So in the next tutorial we're
going to talk about the extrude cut and
we going to use these surfaces or these
sketches we already created on these
surfaces.
Tuto 27 extrude cut. We have these parts
created in the previous tutorials and we
made also a tutorial how to change the
colors
and inserting those sketches
as you see
also have been done in the previous
tutorial. So if you didn't catch these
ideas can review the previous tutorial.
And now in this tutorial we're going to
talk about the extrude cut. We will keep
the revolve
post in the next tutorial. So we use the
extrude cut because it have the same
work like the extrude. And if you are
familiar with the inventor, the inventor
making only one option for extrusion and
cutting.
So they are almost the same
work. But in this extrude cut, it is
removing material. So let's activate the
extrude cut.
because that sketch was selected before.
So now it's created a cut on that part.
So the same we have the mid plane cut
the same extruding feature. So let's try
to make through all. So it's going to
cut through all the body. And if you
make it blend, you are able to make a
distance. If you make it distance
inside,
click okay.
So you have that cut. Let's edit again.
Select it. Edit feature.
And let's select this time up to next.
It will be the same work as through all.
So if you make up the next, the next
will be that edge.
So you have a preview here
and let's make up the vertex.
You can select that vertex.
So you will see and just click okay. So
you'll notice how
that cut looks like.
So let's edit it.
And let's try make up to surface.
So we have this surface. Now we are
extruding to that surface
for cutting up the body. If you have
another body in front of it, you can
select that body to make that cut. So in
this case, I'm going to make it up to
next.
Okay.
And we have this extruded cut.
So now let's select that sketch from
here
and then go to extrude cut
and let's try to make the same we did in
the extrude here. You can make
an angle for drafting.
So you see how is your
cut looks like
and here the one is the direction two if
you want to cut in second direction but
in this case it will not work because we
don't have another side. So let's just
uncheck direction two and the thin
feature you are making a cut like
only
an offset surface.
So here is the distance you can make it
a thickness of 5 mm
and I make two direction of or mid plane
two direction but in this case we will
use one direction because we have only
one direction for cutting.
Now
let's deactivate the draft
to be able to see the cut here.
Let's click okay.
Now notice
how you cut it in the part. Let's edit
the feature.
Just deactivate the clean feature
and
Let's
make it
then put
three of you couldn't be able to edit
the cut because of some closed feature.
can delete. Right click, delete. Yes,
but you still have your sketch there.
Extrude cut.
And let's see
the selected contour. The same idea like
in the extrusion you have this contour.
You can select it
and you have all the bodies or selected
bodies. For example, if you have
different bodies, so you can cut through
one body, not all the bodies. So
we will try to cover this sample.
Now let's just make that cut.
Let's insert a surface on that part as
we learned. Insert.
And now let's use the convert entities.
We had a tutorial in the previous
tutorials
how to use the invert to convert and now
it is a good example to how to convert
that surface that profile. So now we
converted that circle into
uh profile.
Now you are able to extrude. So let's
extrude it. And here have the merge
result. So this is another
thing we didn't cover but now it is
shown because you have different bodies.
So if you select the merge it will
consider all the part as one body. So
let's now keep it merge. Okay. Here
notice you have three bodies. This one,
second one and third third one. But
let's edit the feature here and uncheck
the other one. So you have now solid
dwarves consider that as separated
bodies. And now you see four different
bodies.
So let's insert a sketch on that
surface. Let's make a circle.
Okay. Let's go to extrude cut and we
said we want to show you the selected
bodies either all bodies or selected
bodies. So now let's make it
through all selected bodies
and uncheck that one
here. You can select
so you can select
that body. Okay.
So, you'll notice the cut only in that
body, not all of the bodies.
So, I hope now you understand
more about the extrude cut and extrusion
and the other options in there.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the revolve boss feature in the
features menu. We have these sketches
from previous tutorial. Now, let's show
you how the meaning of revolve. So,
revolving is to revolve uh a sketch
around an axis. So, let's select that
sketch. Revolve.
Now you have the selected contour.
Either we can revolve all these sketches
or
one of them. So let's select the axis of
revolving. Select that axis. So you have
all the sketches are revolving around
that axis. Click okay.
And now we have a rebuild error. So
let's now try to fix it with
making selected contours. So you have to
be a logical
type of
revolving. So now we revolve that part
with selected controls. You'll learn
about it in the extrusion. We learn how
to use the selected control. So okay. So
the
revolving is working. So you have to
think about the type of sketch you are
going to revolve.
So let's make control see and activate
revolve.
Select the sketch
and this this time use this axis.
So
now let's try click okay. So this time
the revolving all the sketching is
working
because it has no
zero thickness inside the material. So
you have to think about which type of
sketching are working and which type
will not work. So now you have this
sketch. They are solid parts
and you can make like pipes. Let's edit
this container about the wall.
Here you have the selected contours or
we don't have the thin feature
activated.
So let's make Ctrl C.
To undo
select the sketch revolve
revolve around that axis
you have thin feature. We already talked
about the meaning of feature. Thin
feature let's make 20 or
3 mm.
So we have these kind of pipes.
So now let's try to make an angle here.
270.
Okay.
So we have an error. Let's try
to build it again. V
and
select thin feature. As you notice, it
didn't work with the center
rectangle
because that will generate as the a zero
thickness feature. So we can fix it with
selecting contours. Select that control
and that control and that it let's make
an angle of 220.
Okay.
So this is an important issue in solid
works to be able to understand the logic
behind your shape and what parts are not
logical to be done and creating errors.
So So now select okay.
So we have
these pipes created by revolve post.
The next feature the sweep post. The
sweep post is need to sketches the
profile and the path to sweep your
sketch. So let's first make a sketch on
the front plane
and let's make
circle
and exit that circle.
So we have the circle drawn on the
origin and let's make a path for
sweeping that circle. So think about the
path should intersecting with that
circle and be
perpendicular
to that circle. So let's select the top
plane.
So we have that plane is perpendicular
to that circle and insert
sketch in that plane number two.
And here
you can start the path for sweeping the
circle.
So we make it
lines.
So let's now activate the
sweep. We also could use the spline. So
the path here is selected as sketch
ribbon and the profile
we can select that circle.
So we sweep the part and the option you
have different option for example keep
normal to the path. So in this
so you have this normal to
path. So, let's edit that feature again.
And you can twist along the path.
Um,
so for the twisting, you need some kind
of angular path to twist around. So,
let's go to the guide curves.
So in this case you have only one curve
so it will be enough. If you have
different curves you can select from
here.
It's quite advanced
and then okay.
So let's make undo
and start it from
before.
Let's edit that sketch
and make that line to be let's remove
that
horizontal relation as we know how to
deal with that. Make that line to be
kind of
incline. Now activate the sweep
the profile
the path.
So now you change that way of
shipping thin feature you already know
about it. Okay.
And here you have your strip path.
In the previous tutorial we created this
part with the sweep post. But what if
you need a different thicknesses around
the SW path? For example, you need that
radius to be bigger than
the rest of the parts. So you can make
different type of swifting or lifting
with this
feature the lofted pose. So for creating
lifted boss we need to have different
different sketches on different planes
so that we can be able to insert or look
between them. For example you can
imagine this part this
sketch is on that plane and that edge on
a different plane and that is on a
different plane. So that mean we need to
insert planes.
So in this tutorial we're going to talk
about inserting planes. Let's start a
new part.
And here you have the reference geometry
icon. If you expand you have plane. So
let's try to make four planes
parallel to the top or front plane.
Select the front plane
plane.
So now you have this
menu. So these are the reference to
create your planes.
You will be able to use them in the
future when you are start creating parts
and so on. So you'll be able to have
different type of planes either to make
perpendicular to that plane or parallel
or consider. So I want to make parallel
and make the distance
of
50 mm. And if you click flip you
changing reversing the direction and
number of planes we want you can insert
four. So you have four
with the front plane
and if you want if you have other parts
or references you can select them to
insert the
the orientation
you wanted to your part. So when you are
done click okay. So now we created these
planes and ready to insert the sketching
on them exactly as inserting on front
plane and so on. So here you notice
these planes the created planes they
having the same icon like these planes.
So in the previous tuto we learn we
start learning sketching on the original
planes and then we learned how to sketch
on the parts or surfaces
flat surfaces on the parts. Now the
third case of start sketch is on
inserted planes.
So that we will show you in the next
tutorial and have example of the lofted
boss.
We inserted those planes in the previous
tutorial. So now we will use these
planes to insert sketching on them. So
to use the lifted boards feature. So
select the plane from here
sketch. So now you are able to insert a
sketch. Let's sketch a circle. Except
sketch.
Also you can select the plane from here
and insert a sketch exactly as the
original sketching
normal tool or you can keep that view
and create rectangle.
Okay, select that plane.
Let's first exit that sketch. Select
that sketch.
And let's again insert another profile
for circuit
origin
and
okay exit sketch
another one sketch
let's make rectangle
exit. So now we are able to work with
the lofted post. Let's activate lofted
post. Here are the profiles
we need to loft. So we can select them
from here. You notice
now you are creating a loft. But here
there's something when you are dealing
with the loft you have the orientation
points. So sometimes you need to
manipulate these points because these
points are changing the twisting of your
roof. So let's make this look this point
here. So now in this case it worked.
And let's change this point
to another place. So it didn't work.
Let's try
here.
And let's try put it in that corner.
So you notice the difference lifting
according to these twisting points or
the guiding points
by changing to that part
and you are done.
You click okay and here you have
advanced option to use a guiding curve
as well. So we have points also you can
use the guiding curves but we can make
it in the next tutorial.
And now click okay. So you created this
shape
or with the lofted post.
In this tutorial we're going to show you
a trick in changing the order of your
work or feature.
So everything you create in solid works
is arranged in orders. For example, we
inserted these planes.
So we have these planes here and then we
work with the loft. So the loft is after
the planes and you cannot for example
start the loft without the planes. So
the loft is coming after the planes. But
now let's try to make another example
for the loft. and showing you as well
the order of working. So we want to make
uh a profile to be lifted not
on a par plane to these planes. So let's
make
find plane and insert a plane
reference to that plane.
So you can make this as 170
to let the loaf be able to be created.
Now let's insert a sketch on that plane
normal too.
And let's make a circle here.
So have to be in your not making a
circle here. So that can be difficult
for the loft to create that. So let's
make it here
circle
except
sketch. So we have a profile here. So
notice we insert the plain sex then
insert a sketch. So there is an order
for your work. So let's now edit the
loft here. Edit feature
in the profiles. this uh
uh the created profile but if you look
here you can't find that profile.
So it is if you even expand this tree
you are not able to select this
this sketch because the order is not
in the right way because we created that
sketch after that loft. So logically
that loft will not see that plane. So in
this case we can show you this
trick to
pull
to drag this
features to be before the low. So you to
do that, select the feature you want
and notice you are able to place it
before the L or in any place. So when
you are working with this type of
changing order, sometimes it will not
work due to some relations and
complicated figures and so on. But this
case is this logical will be working
because there is nothing can prevent
change that order. So now we have the
plain six and sketch order it before the
loft.
So let's edit that loft
edit feature. So now you are seeing that
profile. So let's select it also with
the rest of the profiles changing the
point that it will work. You are done.
Okay.
So here we have this lifted part. So in
this tutorial we learn how to change the
order in order to
make some more feature to work. And in
lofting you can also loft a profile is
not necessary to be prior to
rest of the profiles.
Tutorial 33. In this tutorial we're
going to talk about the guided lofted
bus or the advanced lofted bos. We have
this profile created in the previous
tutorial.
When we inserted planes and the
sketches, we turned the planes off that
they are
hidden. So here is show. And then when
you click on the glass hide, we hided
the plane. So we'll be able to work
on the sketches.
So now we want to make a guided
line so that the loft will going to
follow. So let's insert a sketch or a
guiding line on
a plane that is passing through them. So
we choose top plane insert sketch
number two. So now we can start making a
spline intersecting with these
profiles.
And if you found it kind of tricky to
intersect with the profiles, we can try
to project or convert the sketches.
So convert entities and then you convert
them into
construction.
So now we have reference for
the
for the sketches here. So now let's
insert a spline
in the shape we want is intersecting
with the profile as we see here.
So it done right click select. So we
have our profiles and we have our
guiding curve here. So let's exit sketch
activate boss and here let's select the
profiles.
Let's be sure that we selecting it.
Okay. So this is the original lifted
boss without any guided curve. And here
in this menu the guided curve. Let's
activate it and select this curve.
So when you are done you will see the
results.
So you have the post followed that
guided line.
So let's try to
insert another guided line. So let's
edit this sketch.
And here we have
another spline.
So now we have two as lines.
You can decide the shape how you want
and make them. But here we show you the
idea of the G line. So exit
activate the lofted post.
Select the profiles
for the Gate
this one.
Okay. And then select the second one.
Okay.
So you have two guided lines
and it works as well.
So this is the idea how to use the
guided lofted
post.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the whole wizard feature. We have
this part from the previous tutorial.
And let's try to activate the whole
wizard. And when you activate the whole
wizard,
so it will guide you to create your hole
with its size, type and standard.
So here when you activate the hole with
you, you see the different type of holes
here
and the standard which you're going to
pick. I'm going to give it the ISO
and here also the types of foils
the size diameter
and so on. So let's select the this type
and
when you select the type
select the standard
and then here you have the size. So it's
like to make it m
six it means diameter of 6 mm. the fit
normal and here either to use through or
blend. If you choose blend then you have
a distance to add. So now after choosing
the type dimensions of your hole
next you go to positions
where you can select the place or
position of your hole. So here we can
pick
hole
and then can try to make two holes here
or four holes
and then
when you are on position you can start
the smart dimensioning. This is an
important step to add a dimension to
your to position your hole. So I will
add 25 here
and
25 on the
other side.
So also the rest of
the holes.
So now we
added the dimensions to the all of the
holes. So we have our holes in the
accurate places. So you are done with
dimensioning and the hole positioning
and click okay. So here we created our
holes. Also
there is another idea that you can use
with the hole. You can create one hole
and if you have many holes like 10 of
them you can use the linear pattern to
make different copies or instances. So
in the next tutorials in the future
we're going to use the linear pattern
for the feature
level
tutorial 35. In this tutorial we going
to show you some
functions for displaying your product or
viewing your parts. So that might help
you in modeling and seeing some type of
feature which are hidden inside. So here
if you hover here you have display style
and when you expand it you have
different tab. So you have shaded. So
now you have your product with that
shading line and here you can have it
without any color. And this one is it
will show you the hidden line inside.
So it show you here the holes and the
hollow inside this base.
And last one is
showing you the inside with
normal lines.
So
this is the display style and also there
are the cross fiction
the cross-section view
which can make a cross
through this part. So activate the
cross-section
because we have the right plane is
selected. So you'll have cross-section
through the right plane and in the arrow
you can move that cutting plane.
So now done. Okay. So you have a
cross-section you can see inside the
part. So let's deactivate and now let's
try to select a different plane. So we
have these planes created before
also you can select one of them and on
the arrow here
you can move and see
for example the thickness
of the hole through the face or any
else.
This is a simple way to use the section
view.
So when you are done, uncheck it. So you
are back to your normal view.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next feature revolved cut. So
it works the same way like the revolve,
but this feature removing material. So
let's create a sketch on the right plane
normal two and let's make
center line
to be the revolving axis. And let's make
or draw
So we have this
profile we draw and we're going to move
the material from inside this vase.
by revolve cut this profile. So let's go
to revolve cut.
So need to close the
add another line.
sketch line.
It's got the revolve cut.
And here you can see the cut. So let's
change the
shading.
Okay.
So you can see the cut inside this
material.
Also you can create a
cross-section cut
or cross-section view. So here you see
the cut inside this base.
section view undo.
So here we have
the base
the swift cut.
The sweep cut is working on the same
base like the normal sweep, but this one
is removing material. So, let's try to
make two profiles as we know from the
sweep. One for the profile and one for
the path. So, let's insert a sketch on
that plane on that surface.
Let's make a circle.
exit and let's make another
plane or another
another sketch
to represent the path. So here
we have this top plane can intersecting
with this profile. So let's insert
sketch on that.
normal to we can have the cross fiction
view.
Let's try to
find
a path.
So let's start from that point.
So we have our path here. But uh we can
do one thing else. Ctrl C. We have this
line is from the
the face
edges. So let's try to select this and
convert entity.
So we have this
curve already done.
So
after rejecting this
edge. So let's exit this.
And now let's try to sweep cut this.
So we have the sketch is selected and
the profile will be this one. So we
created that cut inside the face.
We are done. We can expand.
So we can have a look.
I change the view style.
Do you like having a water path inside
this
base? So this idea can be
developed further for
more creative idea.
Let's change the view style.
The topic of this tutorial will be the
lifted cut. So let's show a
cross-section of this
vase. And now we have that revolve cut
inside this vase.
And maybe someone is saying he want to
have a better cut, more smoother cut
than this one. So let's try working with
this. So working with this will give
chance to try some techniques for
learning as well. So not just showing
the doed cut and that it. So we have
here some inserted planes. We can try
also to
use them as well. So let's show them.
And here we have plane here,
a plane here
and so on. So what we can do is
select that plane, insert a sketch,
select that circuit, convert entities.
So
and let's say click the plane, insert a
sketch on that.
Let's show inside
circles. We can
convert into this circle.
So we have a problem here is um open.
So Ctrl C
we can still select that circle.
Now let's move to the next plane.
Insert sketch.
This one you can select that circuit.
Convert entities.
Set.
Select that bin on that circuit.
First insert sketch.
Select circuit. Convert entities.
So we have three or four different
profiles
on
four different planes. Let's show change
the space style make cross-section.
Okay. So let's now try working with the
lofted cut.
Let's select that one.
that one.
So we have more smoother cut in here.
So we fixed this
area here.
But still
we need to make more smoother cut in
here. But now it is clear how to use the
lofted cut. And in the next tutorial we
showing you how to use the guided lifted
cut to try to include this areas as
well.
In the previous tutorial, we used the
lofted cut to make the smooth cut inside
this face.
But still we couldn't cut through this
rough edges here
because the profiles didn't pass
through this. So we'll try to fix this
issue by using the
guided loft cut. So now let's insert
a sketch on
a plane that intersecting with these
profiles which we created in the
previous tutorial. We have the top
plane. So, let's insert
a sketch on there.
And let's try to
first delete that cut or this loaf
and start from scratch.
So top plane sketch
spline.
So in this case
we are not sure if that spline is
padding through. So we can try do is to
convert entities. Let's delete this one.
Select these profiles
and here
convert entities
construction.
So here we have some reference
segments which we can use to insert our
spline. Let's try now move
spline.
So we are done. Exit this. Now
activate the lofted cut. Select the
profile.
[Music]
anticed curve be this.
So we also can add on the other side
but for now let's okay.
So
we tried.
So this cut might be look smoother.
Let's
So this is the idea how to use the
guided lofted cut.
Tutorial 40. In this tutorial, we
talking about the fillet.
In the earlier tutorial, we used the
sketch fillet.
And here we have the other front fillet
which is dealing with the 3D models or
three parts. So let's first hide these
planes. Select them. Hide.
So the flate, let's activate the fillet.
So we have different types of fillet. We
have a constant size, variable size,
face fl.
So in this tutorial we going to talk
about the constant size
and the item to fill it and then you
will have the radius of the fillet. So
let's make radius of 4 mm.
And there if you have you can connect or
connect radius. So it's kind
manipulating the circular making more
curve curvature
while using these. So I'm going to keep
it with the circular
and let's fill it this edge. So by
selecting it
you'll be able to fill it all that edge.
You are done.
Okay.
So, let's try also make a fillet for
that edge.
You're done.
Okay. So, you have a curvature curve.
You are able also to add a fl to it. So
now
let's try case affiliate. So let's
select that edge.
Now you added affiliate
to that continuous edge
and you're done. Okay. But if you have
many edges and keep selecting all the
time might be
taking some time. Ctrl C. Let's undo
with that fillet
again. And here you have the face fil.
So in this case you are able to select
two faces. This is a face and second
face.
Third face.
So
you see the different colors.
This is also a useful tool for creating
face grid.
In the previous tutorial, we used the
constant edge fillet to create the to
fillet this edge. But as you see the
fillet, it doesn't look that
smooth.
So let's try to find that fillet and
delete it and try with
the variable fillet. So we can try to
make that fillet to look better by using
the variable fillet. Let's activate the
fillet. And here you have the variable
size. So item to fill it. Let's select
that edge. And when you are selecting
that edge, you will notice there is
point shown in that edge. So these
points you are able to select and add a
plate radius on that. So let's select
that point.
And here when you click you are able to
add the radius. Let's add 1 mm here.
And let's select that one and add a
radius of
5 mm
and
we have here 5 mm. Let's add 10 mm.
Double click here. Let's add five.
Select that point.
Let's add
five
mm and this one add
one.
So we have now created our variable
radius.
You can also manipulate bit here.
So let's increase 30.
And here we can add
20.
Soon you see that no preview that mean
that fl is not
working.
We might add here figure
75.
So,
so now we created that
we are done. Can click okay. Also, you
are able to
add more
points by selecting this number for
instance. And here the selection smooth
transition.
If you change it to straight transition,
it might not work because it's going to
be a straight on that curve edge. So
let's keep it smooth and add some
more point.
So we have five points.
So when you're done. Okay.
So now you have your rubber fillet.
The next type of fillet the full
round fillet. So if you expand the
fillet you see here the full round
fillet. So when you click on that it
will require you to select three sides.
So now let's fight with this cylinder.
You have to select three
faces that can have chance to be
rounded. So this is second face. Third
face will be in the bottom.
When you're done, click okay. So now we
created that ball by making this face
round for round. Now let's try here.
Select that face.
The second face,
third face here. So you are making whole
round edge by that
option. So now let's try with the hixa
polygon. Let's try to select that edge
here. Let's try make two edges,
three edges.
Third side here. So if you notice we
didn't get any preview that mean these
edges are not allowed to get rounded. So
to un select some of them you see that
dot can click on that menu then you
unselected
and here
you have that edge
either try to click delete or click on
that point. Now we have the foreground
preview.
So when you're done click okay.
So we can try to
make it on the other side.
This is first edge. This
edge third.
This edge third.
Here we have no preview as well. Let's
try to unselect some of the edges.
Here we have
preview.
So we make it another rounded fillet but
it changes the
the shape geometry. So let's try to
delete
that edge and select that edge instead.
So here we have that's full rounded.
Hello to new tutorial in Solid Works
2014. Let's start a new part. Okay.
And let's create any sketch.
Let's make a block.
Extrude it.
Okay.
So, we have this block. In this
tutorial, we're going to talk about the
chamfer. If you expand the fillet menu,
you have the chamfer. So when we are
talking about the chamfer you have to
remember three types of chamfer. You
have angle distance
distance and vertex. So angle distance
you have to specify the distance and the
angle. So let's put here 30°
and choose that edge.
So here you will notice
the distance
here is 10. And this angle is 30°.
Change it to 60.
So you will change that degree that
angle to 60. And that distance is 10. So
here is the first type of shame.
We are able to make an angle distance.
Let's go to the next type. We have
distance. distance. So it is almost the
same results give you but here you are
using the distance instead of
using the angle. So if you select this
one
you made here a five to 10 distance and
that means you have an angle of 30° if
you remember in math. So this is if you
want to make it distance
make it 15 here.
So you see here you have that distance
horizontal distance is 15 and the
vertical is five.
Okay
let's try to make
the next type of chamfer. We have the
vertex. So in the vertex you have to
specify three distances. Let's make the
first distance five 10
and select that
vertex.
You see you created that
jumper in that corner with these three
different
values.
And now let's try to fill it or to
chamer the whole face. Let's make a
distance
five
and select that face.
So you notice you are able to select one
edge
not the whole
face. So
now let's try
that face.
Click okay. you're not able to cher a
face as the case of fillet
that mean you need to select
edge by edge
the next feature the linear pattern so
let's create a hole here to work with it
hole
so let's select that simple type and
let's make it
five
in diameter
and make it
through all. Okay. So let's select
position here.
Okay. So we have that whole scripted.
Okay.
So now let's try to make this hole along
that edge and that edge. So if you want
to make all the time this hole repeating
it all the time. So it might take some
time but in line pattern you can
make many instances. So here feature to
pattern is already selected the whole
and the number of instances
let's say four
and
here you can select the edge or the
direction
okay so let's make this five or as you
want and here you are you have the
distance
now you created five holes
can change distance and so on. And when
you're done, click okay. So if you want
to repeat this pattern as well on the
other side or okay, you can do it as
well. So let's take
on linear pattern. You have this feature
is already selected.
Let's select that edge and make the
distance of 30 or let's make it 10.
Okay.
So now let's try select this hole and
make it on two direction. Pattern it on
two direction. So select new pattern.
Select that.
And we have five
here. You can see it.
And then you can select the direction
too. You have the second direction.
And then you are able to select that
edge. So let's make the number of
instances to be 10.
So you'll be able to see
these two 10 on that direction. And we
are done. And now here if you go to
instances to skip for example we are in
d one direction two you are able to skip
some
instances for example we have these
are already repeated so you can just
click on that dot
So you are able to skip these instances.
So when you are clicking on that dot you
are skipping
from repeating that instance.
So that's it. When you are done click
okay. So you have this but in two
direction. So we made this the previous
process in one process in one step two
direction at the same time.
Now the next feature the circle pattern.
We created this desk for showing you the
circle pattern. Expand the linear
pattern menu. Here you see the circular
pattern. The circle pattern is doing the
same work like the linear pattern but on
a circular reference. So let's try to
find the reverse reverse direction. But
here you can select the the edge any
circular edge or cylinder. So for
example you have selected the edge. If
you select that face you are also able
to select it. And if you select that you
are also able to select. Now we have the
angle for
revolving or the circle pattern. The
number of instances let's try to add 10.
And here you have equal spacing feature
to pattern. We select the cut that slot
cut. So now we created 10 instances as
you see in the preview and here
if you go to the skip instance to skip
the same idea you are able to skip what
you don't want
you are done click okay.
So now let's try to make a linear
pattern for that
and make it on the other
side. So let's try to make an edge.
So sketch in there. Let's try with the
line. The line
might not work. But this you have a
line. Let's make a linear pattern.
Select that edge. So we have that line
is selected. The feature
make two.
The feature to
linear pattern is circular pattern. So
here you see you created that pattern.
increase.
So you see that pattern is created
there.
For example, we can make the reverse
direction
and the
the feature to pattern can clear that
and select only that cut. So let's
increase
distance.
So here
right 225.
Okay.
So we made that line and we made from
that line a c uh linear pattern. So now
we can create a circle pattern to make
that
slot here around the second half of this
disc. Let's click that line. edit it and
convert it into
constructional.
Okay.
So now let's now
circle pattern
feature to pattern will be that linear
pattern number of instances then the
reference will be that edge.
We can increase
the number of button.
So to 10.
So now we are able to create a desk.
The next feature now we will take the
mirror. So let's activate the mirror.
And now I will show you one idea when
using the mirror. The bodies should be
connected to each other in order the
mirror to be to work. So let's find
spread plane. Tomorrow about it. Let's
insert plane reference to that plane.
Okay.
Let's make the distance.
Okay. So now we have that plane.
Activate the mirror
feature to mirror. Let's select the
body.
The plane one is selected. Click okay.
So you look you'll see there is an error
in that or warning in that mirror and
you don't see your mirrored part. So
let's try
to
make
a sketch here or in that plane.
Let's make a
circle
extruded
mid plane.
Okay.
So now we have this cylinder. It should
connect the mirrored part. So let's
delete that one
or you can do something. You can move
that here.
Now you can see here you are able to
mirror that disk.
Now you can see that
you can edit the mirror. You can mirror
the other stuff as well. camera circular
pattern
and so on.
So here you can see your mirror part.
In this tutorial we're going to talk
about the next feature in this menu the
curved driven pattern. So from its name
that you are able to create pattern
according to some drawn curve. So we
have this plane inserted here. Let's
draw a disk on it. Normal to
select uh
here feature extrude
pin feature.
Okay.
So we have a desk here. Let's
make it thinner.
Okay. So now let's insert
uh
a cut on that chip in the desk. Insert.
Let's make a
rectangle
this time
feature
shortcut.
Okay, now
let's make a curve
with the spline.
Can make
a shape you want.
Okay. So we have this curve. We can edit
further more.
Okay.
So let's activate the curve
circuit. The curve pattern
we have sketch seven is already selected
which is that spline. We have the number
of instances let's make it 10.
The distances will be 10 as well.
Feature to pattern we can select it from
here. If you're not able to select you
can go and find it. So here we have this
pattern along that curve. Make it clear.
Let's increase the distance
to
and let's make the number of instance to
be 30.
So it's quite
memory consuming but now we are able to
create that pattern
along that curve. So here we have can
also
edit and make it
for construction.
Okay.
Then exit.
So now we you see when you convert to
construction it didn't work. Just again
edit the sketch.
Stick that line
more
back again.
Can do is to hide that sketch
plane.
Here
you have your circular or curve pattern.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next type of pattern, the
sketchdriven pattern. So let's remind
you with this part what we have done so
far. We created the circular pattern and
then made a linear pattern and again
circular pattern mirror this part and
created a curved driven pattern. So this
time we're going to make a sketch driven
pattern. Let's click on that surface,
insert a sketch. Nowhere to so in order
to make a sketchdriven pattern mostly it
should be points. So the pattern will be
following that point. In this sketch we
have a point. Let's create some
points here where we want to see more
cuted rectangles.
So we couldn't cover
this part with the curve. Now we can
select the sketch driven pattern. Now
the places of the point will be
the new pattern parts. So when you are
done so we have that sketch here. Let's
exit that sketch. So we have sketch nine
containing these points. Now let's go to
sketchdriven pattern.
You have sketch 9 is already selected.
Feature to pattern. We need only that
rectangular cut now. So let's find it.
There you have it here.
So
let's activate this part.
Select that.
Now don't like this you created
rectangular cut on this point you made
you are done. Okay.
So here you see your
sketch driven
pattern.
In this tutorial we're going to insert a
new coordinate system. You know that the
origin here is the original coordinate
axis of the solid works where it start
from 0 0. But sometimes you need to
insert coordinate system to be a
reference for some sketches that we
going to use the coordinate system in
the next tutorial as an example how to
use it as a reference. So let's try to
make a
a block here.
You if you look here this is 0 0
and give it some dimension
to be 100
by
by 100.
Now it's extruded.
Okay.
So in principle the origin is in that
point. But now let's insert a new
coordinate system. To do that go to
reference geometry
coordinate system. Now here it'll ask
you to choose the new origin. So let's
pick that origin.
Now you see the new coordinate system.
This is the X Y Z by default. But here
you are able to select another. So let's
select this to be the X Y be that one
but on the reverse direction.
So here we have X and Y and Z is fine
here. Okay. So here you have a new
coordinate system.
We're starting from zero. So you will
wonder how you going to use that. In the
next tutorial, we're going to use the
tabled driven pattern and the coordinate
system will be helpful in that case. So
see you in the next tutorial.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next feature, the tabled
driven pattern. In the previous
tutorial, we showed you how to insert
this coordinate system. So if you didn't
attend that tutorial, this is good to
see how we inserted that coordinate
system. And now
let's
activate the tabled driven pattern. And
here you will notice it will ask you for
a file to read from. So now if you
browse the types you will need is a
solid work table or text file. So in
this case we're going to use the text
file. I'm going to open a text file to
show you how it would look like. So here
we have three different points.
So these having coordinates one to two x
one and y 2 20 10 30 50 and let's add
and if you remember the dimension of
this block is 100 by 100. So let's try
to be inside this range and this one
let's make it 40 by 80.
The next one, let's make it 0 by
60. And another point, let's make it
by 0.
And the last point can make it
by 80.
So, let's save it.
Close. Here this back to tabled driven
pattern. Browse
this. Find our file. Here we have it.
And now
solid work inserted these points
exactly the same we
now here the coordinate system you can
select. This is our coordinate system.
And here notice the new points point Z
it will turn into 50/50 which is the
original
coordinate system
values without the
without this inserted system
now and the rest will be the same the
feature to copy feature feature. So now
just cancel this for now and create a
feature to be
pattern this
cut here.
Okay. Now back to table
pattern. Browse for the table
coordinate system will be pick from here
or from tree.
If you look here you will see
the points which we pick.
So here is for example the
60 by zero and here 0 by 60 and so on.
So here are our points which we
made them here. So just click okay.
And now
you made
that point or that
interesting
pattern according to point you made.
So I think this type of pattern is an
interesting and can open door for more
advanced
sketching and modeling.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about another interesting type of
pattern. The fill pattern. So from its
name, it is filling an area and make it
a pattern according to that selected
area. So either it can be a sketch or a
face or whatever. So let's try to
activate the fill pattern here. The fill
boundary. Let's select that face. So now
this face will be the filling boundary
and as you notice we have these holes
from the previous tutorials.
So let's see how it will be. Now we have
the type of arrangement of the pattern
the feature to pattern. We can select
that cut from here. So here you notice
that it filled that empty area but it
didn't interact with the already found
cut. So this is the type of arrangement
you can change it to be circular or more
arrange
so on. And here you can make the
distance between
the
instances.
So just keep it to zero.
So this is the fill pattern. So when you
are done like okay
[Music]
type Ctrl C
or delete that one
and let's try another fill. Let's create
a sketch here and make
a slot here.
Okay.
Let's go to the fill pattern.
The fill boundary. Select that sketch.
You're able to select it. Now the
feature to pattern.
Let's select that cut.
So you fill it that
slot
with this
cut. So we can make distance between
this
and here can make
two
that can increase or make 20 to decrease
the number. So,
so it is up to you how to
make it and how you want it. So, you can
play with these
values until you get your
required pattern. So the idea is that
you are able to select the sketch creat.
Okay.
The next feature coming here is the rib,
but we will keep the rib for the next
tutorial because we will show you how to
use the draft then the shell and then
there will be a need for the rib to
support the draft and the shell we
created. So let's try to make a box
here.
Very quick box
extruded.
Okay.
So we have that box. So now you are able
to make a draft. If you remember from
the extrusion you have the draft angle
that you are able to create an equal
drafting sides from all the sides.
But with the draft, you are able to
create a draft in some parts, not in all
of
the faces or edges. So let's click on
draft here. The neutral plane and faces
drop. The neutral plane is the neutral
plane method which you are selecting the
the plane which are not going to move
for any change
and faces to draw. Let's select that
face.
So the draft angle let's type 10 to be
more clear. See? And here you have the
direction of the draft. So in this case
with draft outside. So let's click okay.
You see we made a 10° draft on that ed.
Let's edit that
feature. Click on that arrow reverse
direction. So it will be a draft inside.
So here you have
this. So also you are able to
select
many faces. You have the neutral face.
You have only one face to select. But in
the faces draft you can select two faces
for example or many faces.
And let's click okay. So you drafted
these two edges 10°.
So this is the neutral
face draft.
In this tutorial we talk about the next
type of draft the parting line. So we
have this draft from previous tutorial.
Let's delete it. Yes. And now let's
activate draft. The second type is the
parting line. So if you understand the
idea of the neutral plane which we have
that neutral plane and this truck plane
and that would be the parking line which
is between the plane. So either to
select neutral plane or parking line and
then you'll be able to select that
direction of the pole. Here you can
select that parting line.
You can select that line.
So here you are going to create a draft
of 10°. If you click inside,
if you click okay, you'll get that
inside.
So let's edit it.
and this reverse this drafting.
Click okay.
So we created that outside outward
draft. Let's try it again. Draft.
So the pulling direction that is the
line which is going to change in the
angle and the parting line which is
going to be the
If you imagine the hinge, so that will
be the axial of the hinge where this
face going to rotate or that line going
to rotate. So parting line let's select
let's move that space outward. So this
is the the line of the hinge or of the
door axial. So imagine that as a door.
So select this as parting line. The
direction of
the pole imagine that will be moved
outward. So this line going to move that
direction in 10°. So polling line
you will see and here is the direction.
Let's make it 30°.
Okay.
You make uh three 30° inside track to
change direction. Click on that. You
make it outward
outside.
So here you have the parting line idea
for creating drafts.
The next feature the shell. We have this
box
with different drafted edges. We have
created that with the draft from the
previous tutorial.
So now we made this type of box.
So let's make a shell. The shell is to
make a hollow inside that box. So if you
click on the shell,
make a thickness of your box. Let's make
it 4 mm.
The face shell can speak that you have
the shell preview. You can see a preview
for your shell. So and you can make it
outward.
So you will keep the same volume you
have and just creating a shell outside.
So here you have your box ready. So this
is the shell
uh function to create this
hollow shape
and
boxes.
In the previous tutorial, we created
this plastic box.
And as you know, the plastic box have
all covers have rib inside to support
them because this box with this design
might be not very strong. And here come
the function of rib to create a
supporting
parts for your boxes or other products.
So you need first to create a sketch for
your
rib and from there you are able to
create your rib. So let's try to make a
rib in the middle of that box to support
these walls. We can pick this
surface. Insert a sketch
and let's pick a line normal to find the
center point.
Center point here.
If you go to the feature, you'll find
the rib is activated without exiting the
sketch. That mean you able to work with
rib. So now that line is
riveted. Here you see the direction of
the rib and the thickness of supporting
rib. If you want to change the
direction,
you can click here or you can click on
that
arrow. So
let's see if we will get the right
direction. So it's not. So you select it
should be normal to the sketch. So we
have that sketch. So now we should flip
downward.
Okay.
Now you have that rib is created. So you
know the idea of the meaning of the rib
now. So if you want to make another type
of rib to make it on the side here, you
can do it either to insert reference
plane in the middle. Let's see if we
have plane
pathing from the middle. We have the
right plane. Let's insert a sketch in
there
and make a cross-section view. Okay,
normal to here we have this
cross-section and let's draw a line.
Try to find
place for that rib.
Okay,
now let's go to rib.
You can see the shape and the direction
of rib. So I think now is on the right
direction.
And here you have different
type. You have from one side or both
sides or second side we make it in the
middle. Click okay. Now you have that
rib. This back to the normal view.
And here you have your rib.
Now we will deal with the next feature.
The wrap. The wrap is for adding some
extra detail or decoration for your
part. We have this box. Let's start to
make a sketch to you see the the work of
the wrap. So let's draw a slot in that.
Okay. When you are done exit your So we
have a sketch parallel or in that
surface. Please activate the grab. You
have three different types. You have the
impulse. It will be drafted or extruded
outside impulse inside or just a sketch.
So let's select the face where we going
to show the should be parallel to the
sketch. And now we have a thickness make
it three.
Okay you will see here grab if you edit
that wrap reverse direction.
So you it will not reverse because the
type is impulse. So the impulse is
always outside. So if you make a thick
imposs
okay you make it inside. Um you will
itch it inside.
Now
let's try to make scribe to be only a
strip on that
surface.
Now we're going to deal with the next
feature. It will be the dome. Here you
will see the next feature is the
intersect. This icon is newly inserted
in Solid Work 2014. Before it was the
dome in the place of the intersect and
you in the previous versions you need to
go to the insert feature to get to the
intersect. But now you see it here. So
it's quite advanced. We will keep it for
the
uh next tutorials. Now is the another
decorational feature called the dome. So
here I have the features menu where you
will have all the features. So we
already talked about deflate, transfer,
craft, trim. Then we have to scale the
dome. So now we're going to use the dome
and the dome is to create like
elliptical
surface on a surface. So it's kind of of
bolts if you can see this feature on
bolts and many other products. So it's
kind of saving time instead of creating
it manually. So let's select that face.
Here you have the thickness of the
dome. Let's make it 2 mm.
And then you will see the dome. We
reverse the direction. So it will be the
dome inside. So if you look here,
the field surface is
sinking inside. Let's edit that and make
it 5 mm.
and reverse the direction
then okay
so it's not seeing a lot but here you
can see some kind of
down let's edit make it a little bit
now you can see we are changing
this
so Now we're done. Okay. So here you
have dome. You created a dome for your
part.
For extra decoration, you can add the
dome for that crab. Let's change it to
be in post
in
insert
features
to
select that
surface.
Um here you can see the dot is decrease.
Okay.
And here you have the chance to make it
continuous or not.
Here you have that chip for your plastic
box.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the scale feature. The scale
feature you are finding it in the insert
features
and here you will find the scale and the
scale. For example, let's say you have
this box and you want to create another
box, plastic box for another customer to
be two times bigger or two times
smaller. So creating this box from
scratch will require some time. So you
have two choices to do either to be with
equation and it is quite complicated for
this or easier with using the scale. So
the scale you'll be able to scale your
part directly. So let's choose centroid.
The centroid is going to rescale it on
its
keeping it as a center
and you have you know for scaling let's
say you want it two times. So here you
have your part is two times bigger.
Let's make it
rescale it again. Feature
scale and second option. You going to
scale it around the origin. So it will
not see a lot of difference because this
part is quite
placed near the origin. Let's make it
quarter the
size.
So here you have rescaleed part.
So if you want to redo that shape.
So it's better to use the scale that
will save you a lot of time. And now
let's insert a coordinate system as we
learned in tutorial number 50.
and let's insert it on that part
the x-axis let's make it that
click okay we have our coordinate system
insert feature scale now we going to
scale about the coordinate system so
let's make it
two times we are
so you have your coordinate system as a
reference for your scaling.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next feature, the free form.
The free form is your first step toward
the complicated
surface modeling.
So now
we created the dome here on that surface
and we created a rub and they are quite
uniform shaping. But what if you want to
create your own shaping to the surface
with some kind of curves,
bubbles or whatever. So let's try do
this on that face by using the free form
tool. Go to the insert feature free
form. So select first the face where you
want to make your free form and then you
will need reference lines and points
where you're going to make your
deformation.
So first let's add line.
You can add that line or curves by add
curves. They are control curves. So if
you move on your surface,
you will see that you are able to create
this line. If you flip the direction,
you'll make the lines on the other
side. This flip direction. Let's make
two lines.
And after creating your curves or lines,
you need points
in order that to be manipulating them.
So go to add points, move over your
lines. But if you move in other lines,
you are not able to add any point just
inerted curves. So let's add a point
here,
one point here,
and let's add one point here.
So when you are done
you can go to the
deactivate the point add points and now
select your line.
If you click on that point you see three
arrows. These three arrows you will be
able to free move your points. So here
you make a deformation that side or on
that side or make it upward.
So here we have your free deformation.
Now let's move to the next point
and
by the same way
you can make
that deformation.
Now go to this line.
So be sure that we are deactivating
here and we are able to show the
coordinating or controlling.
So we got a mess here. So you need
some practicing to get
your
this shape.
So this tool is tool showing you
how you are
able to deal with. So when you are done
click okay.
So you have
just kind of experiment
how you can deform your part. So it's
quite not logical but can delete it.
So this is the idea how to use free form
and hope this tutorial is useful.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about another detailing tool for faces
and surfaces which is deform. So the
deform is creating a deform in your
surface and it's quite easier
than to control
than the free form because the deform is
kind of uniform. Deformation is closer
to the work of the dome.
So let's select this face. You have
three set or three types of deformation.
You have the point curves and so on. So
if you click on that surface, you're
going to pick a point where solid walls
going to create a deformation. So here
you see your deformation and you are
able to to change its radius.
So if you have a look here, you see
how
is the deformation
is going here. You can increase
the
the peak of your deformation.
And here you have the three types
of your deformation
provider or something in between.
So when you are done click okay.
So you'll see
that you created this deformation
in your face.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next feature, the split tool.
You can find it in insert
features and here you see split.
So to split the body you have now we
have only one body. If you look at the
tree here so bodies we have only one
body. So to split the body we need some
kind of splitting tools.
So we can try to insert uh a surface in
the middle or in the place how we want
to split this part. So let's try to
split into two half cutting in this
direction.
So let's try to find a plane
cutting in the middle and insert a
sketch there.
So normal tool let's try to make a
center point rectangle.
Be sure that it is cutting through all
this part so it can be able to split. So
now you have choice either to make a
surface. Since we didn't cover the
surface
topic, we can just simply extrude it to
a very small thickness. Let this make it
1 mm.
So here we have one whole body.
If you look here, we have only this
whole body.
Now we can try to split that body
through that
surface. Go to the insert
features split
the trim tool. We will use that face
and then click cut part. Now you have
these two part generated to you. So here
you can select what to keep and what to
remove. If you select both, so you'll
keep both parts.
So if you look here, we have two
splitted bodies. So you are able to
delete one of them. So let's go to the
edit body. Remove
that body. So you have splitted
the body to two part. So let's try to
edit and make and spread that surface
down from these parts.
If you go to the edit feature and merge
result, you can uncheck that. And when
you look here, you have three separated
bodies.
In the previous tutorial, we splitted
that body into two main parts and third
part is this splitting extruded
surface here. So now after we could
split this part, we are able to delete
what we don't want. So to do that you
can go to the insert
features
there you have the body so you can
select that body for example or
first let's try to delete this part
after we splited it in the previous
tutorial. So if you don't know how we
split that part you can see the previous
tutorial. So when you are done click
okay. So we deleted that part. So we
have now these two part splited parts
as you see here. If you want to delete f
more parts
you can also repeat that
option features
delete body. Select the body. delete. So
you have that part. So now you are able
to save them in separated files. Save
this part in one file and the other in a
second file.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next feature, the move and
copy. But before going to that feature,
I just want to add one note to the
previous tutorial. We could delete the
splitted part but you still able to get
them back. If you look here we have
deleted body to delete by three. So if
you right click delete so you will undo
with that process you
if you make here delete.
Yes. So you are undo that process. So
you have that part again. So let's just
delete this part.
The feature
the body
was extruded.
So now let's try to activate the next
feature the move and copy. So here we
have feature
move and copy. You have to set for
moving. You have to enter the values
manually to be more accurate or just
free movement. And in the copy, if you
check the copy will create copy of that
body. So you'll make two bodies. So now
let's select the body we want to move or
rotate.
So as you know we split that body. So
this is nice
feature the split. So you are able to
rotate that part. So let's rotate that
part
and here
and move it.
When you are done click okay.
So here you could move it but you could
interpret it because it has some kind of
relational
with that body but now you are able to
spirited move it there. So let's try
to move it farther.
Insert
feature move.
Select the body. So let's try that side.
Okay.
And here you have it in a different
place.
So now let's try to rotate them. Insert
feature.
Move and copy. Select this part. Let's
try to rotate it in that direction.
And then you're done. Click okay.
So
from one part to two different
directions parts.
In this tutorial, we're going to show
you how to save each part separatedly.
So we now splitted this body. We created
it from the previous tutorial and we
worked on it until we reach to this
part. Now we going to save it in
different files. So there is an option
to do that. To go to the insert
here, save bodies. When you click into
bodies, it show you two different
bodies. Select the one you want save and
then click okay.
So now it will save it as body one. If
you
decrease the window you see it here open
in separated file.
Now let's go to the part. Let's save the
other part as well. If you go to the
insert feature, save bodies. This time
let's save this body. Okay.
Either save it here or can select it and
try to find it
here.
Okay. Can save.
You're done. Okay.
So here we have it.
So
now you are
able to make it in different
part files.
This is
original
and here we have
the two
spreaded files.
Hello to the first tutorial in
surfacing. This tutorial we're going to
be having
introduction about surfaces.
So let's start a sketch in one of these
planes
and to reach to the surface
place. You have to right click on this
bar here and then you have surfaces. So
surfaces is a toolbox by itself in solid
works which have some tools working
with. So with surfaces they are quite
familiar with
the features we were talking about in
the previous tutorials. So but in these
toolbox they are in the surface level.
If you are familiar with the inventor,
inventor making only one tool set for
example like the feature works and there
are options always for creating the
surface. So in inventory there are one
set but here they are two different
toolboxes. So here we have the surfaces
and also you can reach the surfaces from
insert
surface and you have your surface tools.
Okay, now let's start making a sketch.
Let's make
very simple spline.
exit
then exit that
sketch. So now we have this line. If you
go to the feature, try to extrude it. So
you will extrude it like
a solid body with a thickness. You see
here the thin feature is activated. So
you can make it 1 mm or smaller then.
Okay. So here you have a body or a solid
part. So if you look here to the left
solid bodies. So this is considered that
extrude
as a solid body. But the surface is
something different. So let's delete
this extrude
and go to the surface instead. So let's
activate the surface tool. And if you
look here, you have the extruded surface
disactivated.
Select that. Now you have
a surface.
Just try to find this arrow here. So now
we extruded that surface and you are
done. Okay. So the difference now if you
look here the left tree you have a
surface value.
The surface has no mass, no volume, just
it is
uh
a a view to a surface because in the
future you are able to add thickness and
so on after working that surface.
So this is the first introduction about
surfaces. the next tutorial we're going
to continue talking about the extrude uh
contours.
So see you in the next continue talk
about the extruded surface in details.
So here we have this
spline extruded from previous tutorial.
If you want to edit the surface simply
like before you can click on that
feature edit feature and then you are
able to add a dimension.
So let's add 20. So exactly the same
option like the 3D all the features
extrude.
Now you have 20 here
you can increase to 30 and so on. If you
want to reverse the direction here you
can reverse direction and you have some
option up the vertex up the plane or
so we knew from previous examples that
if we have a second body in front that
we can extrude that surface as
that reference either a vertex surface
whatever but here you can choose the mid
plane we are able to extrude in both
sides. So let's make a blend. Now here
you have direction two. So you can
extrude in two direction with two
different distances. So we have 30. We
can add 50. But if you choose the mid
plane, you will get 50 in both sides or
30 in the in both sides.
And now let's go to the draft. You are
also able to make draft in the surface.
So let's add 30° draft.
So here is clear
what the meaning of draft. So you are
drafting the surface as well.
So, let's add a draft here for 90°
and then
activate the drop
20°.
So here you have your drafted
two directions
with two different
drafting
angles.
The extruded surface
icon we used it in the previous
tutorial. Now let's try some advanced
extruding.
Let's try to edit the sketch here
and make another
space or another
profile.
Okay. So now we are in that sketch. Now
you go to the edit extrude
and in the contour
you can select some contours. So clear
selection here and now you have both
profiles they are extruded but now we
are able to select some contours. So if
you hover over that closed area, you're
able to extrude that area. If you hover
over here, you can extrude this area or
that profile. So let's select that.
Click okay.
So you are able to extrude that contour
for that profile.
So this way is able to make some
complicated shapes which are
not easy to make with the normal
sketching. So you can try to intersect
with different
profiles to create some special shapes.
So let's try to extrude the
other profile. Go the contour clear and
select that contour.
Okay.
So we extrude that
contour.
So in the next tutorial we're going to
talk about the revolve surface. So see
you in the next tutorial.
Welcome to a new tutorial. Let's start a
new part
and
change the
story. We're going to talk about the
next feature the revolved surface. You
remember we talked about the revolve
walls and now we have revolved surface.
Let's start making two or a sketch with
an center line. Let's first choose that
front plane
and make
shape of bottle.
So,
okay.
So here we have a very
quick half of a bottle.
Now let's insert
center line
and the
add relation to be vertical.
And there can add some dimension.
[Music]
Okay.
So now after we have this
dimensions, we can now activate the
revol revolve. You have the line
selected line seven which is the center
line and it revolve that profile around
that line. So here you can make it mid
plane or up to vertx or so on or blend
and the angle of so how much you want it
can make half revolution
and you can make it a full
revolve direction tool the same way like
we talked before and extrusion we made
three tutorials about extrusion talk
about the direction and select contours.
So this works
on the same way. So when you are done
click okay.
So here you have the water
very quick
and fast to create with surfaces
and the revolve.
In this tuto we're going to talk about
the contours and revolving.
So we make this tutorial to show the
contours in revolving because it might
be kind of tricky to use. So now we have
this profile made.
Let's make an offset from that.
Call it sketch.
Edit sketch.
And now we have the offset.
Let's try to make an offset of one
or 2 mm from the
click. Okay.
Close your
profile. Close
here.
Fine.
Here we have a closed contour. And let's
try to make another
contours. So
I make some
circle here
and mirror
it on this.
This activate this as we learn make it
just one. switch activated in that
direction and here we can make five
reverse.
So we have this.
Okay.
Now we have this close contours. Now
let's try to
trim
uh surface revolve
here. So you got able to select some
contours. Select the line of revolution
and the contours. You need to select
some closed contours.
Try to find a closed contour here. So
here we have closed contour.
So now we are able to
select the control from the front
profiles.
Tutorial number 71.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next surface tool, the extrude
or sweep surface.
It is not activated here. So let's start
some sketches to
to make a script. So let's start this
profile
exit and try to find another profile to
be perpendicular to that profile in
order to swip. So we have to plane
make an asline.
So here you can decide the shape of
sweep.
Let's
exit.
So now you notice the sweep surface is
activated. You have two surfaces, the
profile and the path. So let's activate
the sweep. The profile is here. Select
to be the path. So it's not the right
selection. So we select sketch one as
profile. The path will be this.
So when you're done, click okay. So this
is the very simple SW
choice
and
you can try to edit and see the
different options. So here you have poly
path. So it give you a very simple
sweeping and you have keep no more
constant. So it will the profile will
continue being constant the whole
sweeping way.
So if you click okay so you see the
different between exit or edit here you
can also twist along path.
So here you can see
the twisting when you are increasing.
So we can make it 90°
or
let's make another angle.
Here you can revolve the twisting
direction.
Let's edit again. Here you have twist
along with the normal constant
try
and let's try to make another option or
another trick with this twisting. If you
go to edit
full path, you have twist along the path
and you have either to select with
degrees or with turns. For example, if
you can select turns, five turns. Click
okay. So you are twisting and making
this special road.
So there are many options to do to
create your
almost any shape you want on solid
works.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the lifted
surface. It works pretty similar to the
feature
low.
Let's insert some reference planes as we
learned the previous tutorial. Let's
make two more
with the front plane. Let's start with
the front plane. Making a sketch. Select
the center point slot.
Um,
except
let's go to the second plane.
Insert a sketch.
What we can do? We can make a trick.
invert
the entities
then rotate it.
So we can select
and then center of rotation can select
the origin
90°.
So uncheck the keep relation.
So you are done except go to the third
plane sketch.
Select the first sketch and convert
entities.
So we have these three sketches in three
different planes. Go to the locked. We
have sketch three selected. Select
sketch
two.
and then sketch one. So when you are
selecting you are also need to care
about the points you are selecting. So
it's not just to select because
selecting a point can decide the shape
of your L. So now we have the uniform
l.
If you change the point place that can
create some twisting to your part.
So
that why you need to
understand or know where is the loop.
So sometimes it became not
working.
So
you have to choose. And now we are on
the uniform lofting just the
same path points.
Okay.
So now you created your
floor.
In the previous tutorial, we created
this simple loft without having any
guiding lines. just selecting the
sketches in solid works. You are also
able to select some guiding lines if you
want your glove to follow some specific
path. So let's try to delete this loft.
And now we have these three sketches.
We will try to insert some
guide.
So we can find a plane where we are able
to
have a path intersecting with all these
sketches.
So let's start the sketch on the right
plane
and then
can make no to be sure that we are
intersecting with the
sketches. We can make
can projecting
Okay. Then convert this
convert them to construction
and make a spline.
So here we created a path
exit
go to the loft
surface
clear selection and the profiles we have
to be sure we are selecting
our sketches.
So this is the simple loft for regarding
curve. You can select that curve
then click okay. So you notice it was
not able to create that love. So you can
move to the other option
to be sure that we are selecting. So we
have another advanced option. you'll use
it for the first time in this set of
tutorials.
We can go to the 3D sketch. If you go to
the sketch, you have 3D sketch. So SC 3D
sketch is not
associated with any planes. So it is
moving free in the space in three
directions. Let's select a spline.
Select this point. So now we are sure it
is
intersecting with that
profile and then select
another point.
Then third point
and you are done. Select.
So we have since it is a 3D sketch so it
needs some extra
control
to see where is path is going. So let's
try to see this
path.
This is intersecting
this point here. Try to delete
that relation.
Make sure that this point is
intersecting with that sketch.
Soon you are
So when you are done with your 3D
sketch,
okay, go exit. Select the lofted
clear selection here. Select the
profiles.
Third, for the guiding line, select the
3D sketch.
So here you notice that your noted guide
is working.
So now you have your special
or unique lifted
surface.
Tutorial 74, we going to talk about the
fill surface tool here. And before it we
have the boundary. We will make it in
the next tutorial.
The filled surface is quite it is doing
the same job like boundary but the fill
surface is quite easier. It fill the
gaps and the surfaces. For example,
let's activate the boundary. Just select
that
and click okay. So you find it is
it needs more inputs to create the
boundary surface. But let's now activate
the fill surface. So it's going to fill
the profile. So if you select that
you'll see a preview
which going to
fill that surface. Also you will be able
to s to select some guided curves
and the type you have the tangent but in
this in this way it not work when you
going to select the tangent because you
can't see
this surface is perpendicular to that
surface. So we can try do it in the next
tutorial. Now let's select the contact.
We have that surface. Okay, you fill it
that surface.
So, this is a way to complete your
product very quickly.
Fill the surface with one click.
Tutorial 75. In this tutorial, we're
going to talk about the clay surface.
Let's show the surface tools box. And if
you don't know here you can see right
click
and you have the surfaces toolbox
the filate is come here later. So we use
deflate in this tutorial. It is quite
easy and it will be also useful for
creating affiliate to the next tutorial
when we going to use the boundary
surface. Let's start a sketch on the
front plane.
Let's make circle and center point
rectangle.
Let's trim
very quickly
with power trim.
Okay. Now exit
or even before exiting you can extrude
that surface.
Extrude. Okay. Now we have this extruded
surface.
We can make these edges smoother with
make a fillet. Let's make fillet. Here
we can have the 10° or 10 mm distance.
Select that.
you are able to create that plate. So
increase
let's make it 50
and make 50 here
and then can make another 50 here. So
you are done click okay.
So you have this
shape.
This tuto we're going to talk about the
boundary surface tool. We have this
profile created in the previous
tutorial. It contain many spreaded
sections as you see. So let's activate
the boundary surface. Now you are able
to select the boundary surface
and create that surface. You can see
this is this edge and this edge. So here
you have your boundary surface is
selected. Can also select that edge. In
this case be different. This cancel make
a boundary surface. Click this edge.
This edge. So you are able to create the
boundary surface between these two
edges. So when you are done click okay.
Tutorial
77. In this tutorial, we going to talk
about the two direction boundary
surface. So it is a first step to
advanced surfacing. Let's start make a
sketch to let you understand the idea
between two directions
boundary surface. So let's select the
front plane.
Insert a sketch there.
normal to
let's make two lines or simply convert
these two lines.
Then we have these two lines on that
surface.
So let's exit that sketch.
Activate the boundary.
Select this line
when you are done. Okay. and
the second line.
Okay. So, we have two
lines
done. Click okay. This case you not able
to see that. Okay. Let's go to boundary
surface again. Select the line
and this line
here. You see that boundary surface
it's created. But as you notice it
created a straight boundary line and
didn't it trim around that fillet. Let's
edit that
boundary. And this case you can select
the direction two. So this is second
direction here.
And here second direction
you created
exactly the same
closing boundary surface
to fill this gap. If you want a very
simple surface without any complicated
edges or so on, you can simply select
the easy way the filled
surface. So you are able to select the
boundary
edges.
Select the edges.
Last one you have your fill surface.
Okay.
So this example show you the boundary
and the fillet and the use
of them. Tutorial 78. Let's start new
part.
In this tutorial we're going to talk
about the next feature the planner
surface. Let's bring the toolbox, the
surface toolbox here. And let's make the
uh sketch on the top plane.
Some
make a circle.
So we have these three surfaces or three
files. Six and extrude them.
with extrude surface.
Okay.
So now if you want to fill some
surfaces, you can use the planner
surface. The difference between planner
surf and filled surface. The planner
give you uh a planer a plan or flat
surface to close. But with the fillet
you have chance to select directions and
so on. So let's activate the planner
surface. Here you are going to select
the boundary of your surfaces of where
you're going to create your planner
surface. Let's speak be sure that we are
selecting the right
edges.
And as you notice here, you don't have
any other choices. Just select the
boundary edges.
You have no chance to make directions or
whatever. So now we have our
uh planer surface created and we fit
that surface.
Again we can activate
the same way you can create planner
surface. So it is not necessary to
select a closed loop
can create a planer surface
on some part of your surface. So let's
again activate planner surface. Select
this circle
and here you have your
planer surface.
Let's rotate the these parts.
Um here we have another choice to fill
all these
gaps at once with the planner surface.
You have two choices. Let's try the
first one. We can choose a plane is par
and intersecting with these profiles and
create a sketch on that.
So and draw
[Music]
rectangle that is covering
these
surfaces.
Okay. and then make a planer surface.
Then you closed all the profiles and you
having this extended sheet and you in
this case you are able also to trim
after that the excessive if you don't
want this excessive surface.
Let's
undo or delete this planner surface and
make the second way to fill all these
gaps with at once. We have that sketch
we made at the beginning. If you select
it and select planner surface solid
works going to fill all these profiles
in that sketch
and then you are done.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the offset
surface. We have this part created in
the previous tutorial. Let's try to make
some offset surface. from it name you
are able to duplicate a surface you are
choosing and make an offset from it. So
let's try to select that surface
activate the offset.
So simply you created an offset surface
that and here you have the distance you
choose
and then you have also to reverse the
direction
as see here.
When you are done you can click okay.
offset surface. It can make some kind of
uh designing for your surface. For
example, you can offset some parts to
make it like
uh appearance changing the appearance
and then deleting the original surfaces.
So, let's try to make another offset on
these
connected surfaces here.
Just select offset surface.
Clear selection and select
this surface. Surface
and then
one.
You're done. Click. Okay. So you created
your offset surface.
Let's try it on again on that cylinder
offset
layer selection and cut that cylinder.
Select the top plane. Top
select
this surface.
And then we are able to fill the surface
between these two with some kind of
fill surfacing.
So let's try to review the filled
surface. Try to fill that surface. Let's
select filled surface. In this case the
pler surface will not work because
planner we said taking flat surfaces. If
you pick you are not able to
select only close profile.
So let's select the fillet surface
and
this edge that edge. So you see that
surface is created to fill this gap.
Okay. So, you fill in
that surface.
In this tutorial, we're going to cover
the delete face tool here and later on
we're going back to the free form and
road surface tools. So let's activate
the delete face and from its name you
are able to delete some surfaces. So
let's select that surface. You have
three different options. The simplest
one is the delete. Sometimes according
to the geometry you are not able to
select the rest. So selecting delete and
here you are selecting that face it give
you some option what delete with it. So
all surrounding all outer and so on. So
let's select that.
Then you are selecting that face. Okay.
So let's try to make it on this.
Activate the delete. Select that one.
Delete. This select delete and fill.
It's not going to work cuz you need to
select some more
some more faces. So deleted and filled
at the same time. So it has no result.
Let's try on that.
Then okay.
So again has no result because it filled
it with the same
surface. So we can do is
delete and fill select and select the
all tangency.
Okay. You'll notice the change in here.
Now let's try to delete this single
surface.
If you try to delete it with this delete
face,
select that face, delete, it's not going
to work. So you need to to make another
option to delete that single face
because of the insert
feature. Delete body. Select that face.
Okay.
So delete phase is having some options
to delete some loops and so on. But with
case of single face you can choose
delete
or
from features
delete body. So if you select that it's
going to select all the surrounding.
If you select that select
selection and select that space
then you are able to delete that
surface.
Tutorial 81. In this tutorial we're
going to talk about an interesting
surface tool the free form tool. We have
these parts from the previous tutorial.
Let's undo the deleting we did in the
previous tutorial. Simply select them
here.
Delete body. Delete face. Right click.
Delete. Yes.
So now we are back to our
normal
shape. Let's just delete this bits
feature
click body.
Okay.
Now we can try to activate the free
form. The free form it making some free
transformation to your surface according
to the design you want. And in this case
you are able to free by yourself or
having some guiding sketch. So the face
you are going to make some deformation
you are selecting that face and there is
two things you have to think about
before creating your deformation. The
curves and the points. So you need
curves and points. So let's try to add
curves. you are able to make in that
direction or
other
other direction if you flip direction
here. So let's keep it with the first
option. I'm going to add two lines when
you are done. Add points.
So the points are
will
be the places where you're going to
create your deformation. So now uncheck
or deactivate the add points. Now you
are able to select the curve, the point
and move it. You have the arrows.
So go next one.
So you're able to move it in many
direction.
Then go to the second line here.
So here you are creating your
deformation.
So you are done click okay.
We can try do it that first create some
transformation.
Add some lines
or curves.
Add to curves and add points.
Also you are able to change the angular.
If you see that small surface here or
small face you are
able to select that and move that plane
direction.
You're done. Okay.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the ruled surface tool. Here we
see it in the toolbox. So the ruled
surface tool is adding extend the edges
with some surfaces. Let's activate this.
And you have many options. The most use
the first two. So if you select that
edge, you are extended that surface.
So now we are extending it
upward. And if you make it normal to the
surface, you are able to make it normal
to the surface. So this kind of
extending the surface. Here you can flip
the direction.
And as you remember we made an offset of
10 mm. You can increase that but the gap
here is 10 mm. So when you are done you
click okay. So you have some trouble
here to connect with the surface. So we
can decrease
9 mm.
Then click okay.
Let's
flip direction.
Okay.
So we have a
problem because this extended surface
they are intersecting with each other.
So let's flip direction
and you are done. Click okay.
So let's try to make it on this circular
edge. R face normal to the surface. Flip
direction
please.
Okay.
So this is the idea of road surface.
Now for example we can extend that
cylinder here. R
extend make it tangency.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the need surface tool. So the need
surface is combining the surfaces. For
example, we have this product and in
reality it is kind of
uh one part. So you can imagine this uh
drink can. So it is made from one part.
So but in this surface or in this
tutorial it is separated surfaces. So if
you select here have that surface and
here you have a spread surface and this
is a spread surface. So you so it is
important to
show the type of connection between your
surfaces. So these if they are one
surface so you should need them and also
it is good idea to knead your surfaces
to decrease the number of surfaces you
have. In this case, we have 16 surfaces
and we said these surfaces we need to
combine them. So, let's activate the new
surface. Select that surface. This
surface that surface
you can also select that one too.
Then click okay. So if you notice here
you decreased
your surfaces
and here you have only one surface they
are combined together. If you look here
you have the surface need three you have
all these part in one surface.
Let's try to create again here each
surface this one this one the rest.
Okay.
and rather we
increase the number of surfaces.
So also we can
take this plane
meet it with this body.
Okay,
this planner need
body here
needed
inside body here. Okay.
And so you are able to
combine your surfaces and decrease the
number of surfaces or can be easier to
handle and also decide which part are
combined together or one
sheet of surface.
In one of the previous tutorial, we used
the delete body tool to delete some
surfaces. But in the previous tutorial,
we made some combining to the surfaces.
We made some neat and let's try to use
the delete body and see what will
happen. Go to the feature
delete body.
Select that surface.
Okay. So you notice you're going to
delete the whole neat surfaces combined
surfaces. So that is prove that they are
only one part. So the neat surface is
combining your surfaces to make them one
single surface. So Ctrl C to undo. And
if you try to do it with other surfaces
which are combined with the rest, it's
going to delete them as one unit.
In this we're going to talk about the
extent surface.
In the previous tutorials we talked
about the rule space and we saw that we
couldn't make it inside to extend these
edges these edges to the inside surface
because they are overlapping. So you
have other option is to extend surface.
So in this case you can select that
surface
and here you have the direction of the
extending. You can extend it upward
or you can change it to linear. So it
depends on how you you want this
extended to be. So you have a distance
here you can make 10
then you are extended that surface
and you are able to extend the surface
parallel to itself. Can select that
edge.
Make sure that you are selecting the
edge the one you can select this edge
and you see you have
that extending parallel to the surface.
Here you can pull that arrow direction
and add a distance or to be more sure
you have up the point. So you can extend
it and select that point. So you are
extending that edge to that point.
So tutorial 86. In this tutorial, we're
going to talk about some common tools
found in the surfaces toolbox. Here you
have the reference geometry toolbox
which are also found in the features
menu and also you have the curves menu
which are also found there. We're going
to talk also about the curve menu in
this series later on. Now we're going to
try some tools in the reference. You
have the axis the point. We already
talked before about plane and coordinate
system and also in this tutorial we're
going to talk about the helix. So let's
first try to insert the point reference
point. You can select center on a face,
center on arc or
intersection. Let's try to make center
on a face. So if you go to there, you
were able to select that center point
and this center point. If you select
that surface and you will see you have a
point in there. So you have a center
point. So you are done. Okay. So you
have that point reference point and that
center
face. Let's try another type of points.
You can intersection. You will see
intersection between this line this
line. You see you have an intersection
point. Hit okay. Let's try another type
of point. You can arc center. You can
select that arc. Now you have that
center point in the middle of that
arc or cylinder. Now go to the axis to
insert an axis. You can have an axis.
You have three and then you can make it
type
or on line edges or two planes or point
on plane. So in this case you can have a
point
then okay you need another face you can
select that point and that face then
click okay you created that center axis
also you can insert center axis through
the planes in here you can select front
plane
and the top plane
go insert axis you'll have an axis
between these to place. Now what we want
to talk about now is the helix. Helix,
you need to create a helix. You need to
have a circle.
So let's try find circle. That's it.
Create a sketch in here. Let's click
that circle. Invert entities. So okay,
when you have that circle, you will be
able to insert a helix. So here you have
a helix. You can type the pitch
revolution five
and whatever your spring you wanted and
start angle or you can reverse it
direction.
Okay. So the helix is a useful tool. You
are able to create threads,
strings, and many things with the helix.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about an important tool in
the surfaces toolbox, the trim tool. So,
let's activate the trim tool and try to
delete these outside flanges here.
Now here you have the trim tool or the
trimming surface or the main body which
is going to be used as the trimming
tool.
Here we have selected that body you can
see it's shaded in blue and the rest of
the body you can see you can select it
in yellow. So these bodies,
so this body main body shaded in blue
will be used as the trimming tool. And
here you can select the keep selection
or remove selection. I'm going to select
remove selection. And here you are able
to select this surface and this surface.
So when you are done, okay, you have
problem
selection and select that body. Okay.
So we have now trimmed that outside
flange.
Now to make it more clear, let's try to
make another
surface.
Let's make
on the
front plane sketch
normal to let's make a spline.
So let's say we going to
change the type of the bottom edges of
these boxes to be kind of
curved.
So we have this
surface. Let's extrude it
on mid plane.
Okay.
So, we have this surface and we have
these
boxes or cans. So, now we have many
options to do. You can trim the ex the
excessive parts here, trim the down
parts and so on.
So, let's try this example and have and
see what we can do. So the trim tools
you can select this surface. So remove
selection. Now we are able to remove
these parts
and you're done. Can select. Okay.
So now you
could trim
the bottom edges of these scans and make
it circular. So now let's try to trim
this surface. So you can you have option
to delete
this surface. Let's try to insert and
go to features delete body. Select that
surface. Okay.
So now you deleted that that surface.
But when you deleted that, you deleted
the
covers of this. So you can now make
planner circle surface or filled
surface. In this tutorial, we're going
to make the opposite of trimming
surface, the untrim surface. So it is
making the filling the trimming
surfaces. So let's try to untrim this
edge here. We have this part from the
previous tutorial. Let's click on trim
there. The selection of the edges.
Select that edge and that edge.
So now it's going to fill that gap or
untrim.
So if that was trim surface, now you are
doing the opposite and fill that gap.
Okay.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next feature, the fillet. We
already used the constant fillet in the
previous tutorial. And in this tutorial,
we're going to use the the variable
fillet. So, let's activate the fillet.
Select variable fillet, variable size,
and then select where you want to apply
your variable fillet. So, let's select
this edge. And now you see you have
points. These points, you are able to
add a fillet radius to one of these
points. And also you are able to add
more points.
So now let's try to add some affiliate
values here.
So let's add one mm here.
Click on the second point
and add 5 mm.
Third point
at
7 mm.
And then this one can add 5 mm.
last one
and the last one this add
1 mm. So when you're done okay so you
have your customized fillet apply to
this edge. So in if you are not able to
apply a flate on one of the surfaces
you might need to need the surfaces for
example we already may combine the
surfaces together. So if you are not
able to make affiliate so try to need
the surfaces then apply your fillet. So
here you have your vable fillet.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next type of fillet, the face
fillet. Activate the face fillet. And
now let's apply it on these two faces.
Select this face and second face. This
one. Add the radius of fillet to be with
20. Then you apply your face fillet.
As you notice here, this surface didn't
fill it with that
surface.
Click undo. And let's try to fix this.
We need to combine this surface with the
rest of these surfaces. You do that with
knee.
Select that surface and these already
combined surfaces
as we did in the earlier tutorial. Click
okay.
Now apply the face fillet.
Select this first set of faces and this
is the second one. Okay. You notice now
you are able to fill it that surface as
well.
So you have to think about this extended
surface is 10 mm. So if you made the
fillet bigger than that might not work.
So let's try to edit that fillet. Let's
make it
12.
So you notice it didn't work. So let's
make 10 again or smaller will work as
well.
Let's try to make the another example
for the face fillet. Select the face
fillet. Select that face. That face.
This is first set. That's This is
second.
This is third.
Select
one. Press at once.
Change.
Okay.
The next tool set in the surfaces
toolbox is the references. We already
talked about the plane and coordinate
system and so on. They are the same work
as the ones we used before here in the
features
menu, the reference geometry. So now
let's move to the next menu, the curves
or this menu. This allow you to further
advance work with your surfaces. In this
we're going to talk about the split
line. So split line you are able to
create a sketch spline or line and from
that sketch you can split your surface.
Let's try to make a sketch on a plane
that is
where we are going to cut that surface.
So this case in the front plane
insert the sketch
normal to just create a line cutting
line or the knife.
Then we are done.
So we are done with this line. You can
add dimensions and so on
and go to split line. So it is activated
here selected
and here you are having become sketch
this line the surfaces where you are
going to split this surface when you are
done click okay. So this line is moved
like knife through that surface and
split it into two parts.
So now you are able to work with one of
these part alone. You can delete that
surface or trim it. The next tool is the
project curve. An interesting tool in
solid works. If you are following us in
creating this part from beginning, you
will remember that we have a deleted
surface have been created before. So if
we go
to the tree, we can pick that deleted
body here and undo by deleting that.
So now you would remember that extruded
spline. So if you don't have it, you can
simply create a spline and extrude it.
So we have this
extruded surface. Now we'll
make another sketch to project it on
that
surface because it has quite some sharp
edges. We want to make it looks a little
bit better. So let's try to find a
parallel plane to that
extruded surface where we are able to
project a curve on it. So we can find
the top plane.
Insert a sketch on top plane
to So now we can select the shape
of our
So we can
make that chip.
So you are done with the shape you
wanted
and it is matching that extruded surface
in the top of it. Click okay. Now we are
able to project that sketch on that
surface. Go to
or exit sketch first. Then go to project
curve. Sketch six is already selected
which we have clicked already. The
surface where you're going to
project is this surface on the face.
So you notice here you have your
projected
curve on that. Click. Okay. Now,
now when you are done with the surfaces
toolboxes, it's time to see your
surfaces work. Now it's time for the
surface quality. So you have the zebra
stripes tool to get there. Go to
evaluate. You have zebra stripe. So
zebra stripe is showing you the flow and
continuous of the surfaces.
So here you have this stripes. So this
extrude surface looks okay.
And here you can see the glow of the
stripes. And from there you can imagine
what can be
not
smooth or have lower quality. For
example, here we made a fillet. You can
see the smooth between the stripes. And
when it come to the top surface, it
might need some working to make that
zebra stripe flow more smoother. So
zebra stripe is a good tool to show your
surface work that might not be seen with
the normal eye, but with the zebra
stripe, you can see the
flow of your surface. So here you can
see it might need some kind of fork to
make this free form surface
smooth with the rest of the body.
So can now
deactivate. And here you can see this
edge
need some work to make it smoother. You
can apply glade or whatever. So now we
can talk about another tool for your
surface quality or the thing they are
not clear to see by the eye. So we
talked about the zero stripes in the
previous tutorial. Now you have the
curvature tool which measure the
curvature in your
parts. So here if you look at this black
curvature that mean you have and hover
over it you have a curvature of zero
that mean this surface is
flat. Now here you can look this green
this give you the value of the
curvature. So this is
blue here you can see the flow of the
curvature between
the planes. So this part is black and
here you can see the transition is
smooth between the two colors. This is a
way to know the quality or to measure
the curvature of your
surfaces. And here you can see the green
and black you don't have any transition
colors. that mean you have a straight
transition. So in this case it is okay
because it is not a spline or something.
But here can look at the variable
fillet. We have smooth transition
between curvatures.
If you want to see more curvature, you
can apply here some kind of fillet to
make the transition between the black
and these green gray colors to be more
smoother. So this curvature tool is
quite interesting to measure more your
surfaces quality.
Tutorial 95 in surfaces for solid walls.
This tutorial will be the last in the
surface section which will be about
adding thicken for your surfaces. So
when you are done with the creating your
surfaces with your surfaces tools which
we already discussed and checking the
quality by zebra stripe and curvature
and time to add the thicken because
right now you don't have any actual
body. It is only surfaces and they are
not ready to be manufactured or measured
as a mass. So this add some thicken to
your surface.
By going to insert both space you have
thicken. So you can select the surface
you want thicken.
Then
you see the thickness you want to add.
You can add 1 mm.
Here you have the type of thicken you
want it to be outside or in the middle
or inside.
So we have this body is selected.
So okay. So we add some thick to that
body.
So you have look here you have a
thickness of 1 mm to that edge.
Again we can apply to the rest of the
bodies. Insert these balls thicken. Can
select the curvature.
Then add a thickness of 1 mm. Okay.
So we have here thick
one mm.
Then you can continue
the rest of body.
Just select this body.
and add thick of 2 mm.
Make it in between. And here you have
the merge result. So we can keep
checking. So it can merge this surface
with that surface and make it one body
or uncheck to make it separated bodies.
So click okay. If you go up in the tree,
you will have solid bodies here already
appeared. So the thicken they are actual
bodies but not in the surface. So the
surface they are only surfaces and when
you add some thicken you have an actual
body with mass.
So you can see your box here.
So now I am done with this tutorial and
hope this section was useful and the
next section will be the next tools the
weldments tool.
So we have a series for discussing the
welment toolbox.
Hello and welcome to the very first
tutorial in the Solid Works WBS on the
list. It is tutorial number 96. So we're
going to continue talk about the Solid
Works toolboxes. And now let's move to
the weldments. Let's start a new part.
Okay. And the weldments it's word comes
from welding.
So you already know what the weldings
is. So to find the welding weldments
toolbox, right click on the toolbar here
and then you will find the weldments. So
so far away there now maybe you don't
see it but you will write weldments. So
click on that you will find the weldment
toolbox. Also you can find it in insert
weldments and here you have your
weldments tools.
So in this set of tutorials, we're going
to talk about the wellments and each one
of these tools and functions and how to
deal with them. So I hope this
tutorials will be helpful and let you
learn more about the great software
Solid Works.
So see you in the next tutorial.
This is tutorial 97, the second tutorial
in wellman's. The first tool in the
world's toolbox, you will find the 3D
sketching tool. So the 3D sketching tool
is not only withins, you also find it in
other places. For example, in the
sketching here, if you start the sketch,
you have 3D sketching. So 3D sketching
is now it is we worked with that before
but this is the first time I am using it
to with a tutorial to show you how to
use it. So the 3D sketch it is different
than the original sketch. The original
sketch you are creating two-dimensional
sketch in one of these planes. For
example, let's make a center point
rectangle.
So you are able to work in this plane
that front plane it might be the Y X
plane you're not able to move in the
third dimension but if you want to make
another
you want to make a table for example and
you want to make legs so you need to
insert another plane. So for example,
you can go to the feature plane and you
want to insert plane parallel to that
line. So let's find a parallel plane. So
in this case will be the right plane and
this line.
So and we can make it parallel here
and then okay. So we inserted a plane
here. Then you can insert a sketch on
that plane.
normal to and insert two lines
two lines here
and one
line here
and they are equal. So exit the sketch
and then the same process on the other
side to create that table. So you can
imagine how it is kind of many steps to
work with this 3D table. But here came
the 3D sketching work. So it make this
job more easier because you are able to
create 3D sketch 3D dimensions.
But it why it needs some attention when
working with it because it is kind of if
you need to control the direction. So
let's delete this sketch
first. Let's exit this one and delete
those sketches
and start with 3D sketch. So click on 3D
sketch or from a sketch here you have 3D
sketch. So now we are in the 3D sketch
mode. Let's select center rectangular.
We need that to be in the yaxis. You can
look at the compass here
to have
an idea in which plane you are drawing.
So now we are in the xy plane. So as we
remember when you created a 2D sketch it
was on the xy.
A second thing when you want now to draw
a leg so they will be in a different
plane. They will be in the Z Y plane.
So in that case you need to
change that plane by clicking on tab. So
now we are in the S Y plane. So you are
able now to
insert the table legs
and can add or you can add an equal
relation to to them. And now let's move
to the other side.
Select line.
Now we are in that plane. Make sure that
you are
par to the axis
and then one line here.
So you can see it is par to the axis and
again we can add equal
relation to them.
So you see you created that table in
only one sketch which called the 3D
sketching. So if you want to work or
make this sketch on the 3D on the 3D 2D
sketching you will see it is require
many steps in certain planes and so on.
So you created that table in a matter of
few minutes.
In the previous tutorial, we talked
about 3D sketching. We created this
table by 3D sketching. As you see the 3D
sketch here and exactly like the
previous sketching, you are able to
rename it and add a name for it. For
example,
and to edit it also, you can click on
there. Here you can change the name if
you want
3D
[Music]
table.
And
if you click on that you have edit
sketch exactly the same like the 2D
sketching you are able to edit again
your sketch. Let's add some dimension
here.
[Music]
So let's make a table with 1 m
wide
and
give it
L noise.
[Music]
And when you are done, you can click
exit sketch. We have this sketch. Now
let's start working with members. So
wments is actually members structural
members which are going to be welded
together. So the section member they
having different types. Let's start the
first
uh icon. So when you are adding this
icon here that mean you are able to
start working with the wins. So it is um
important icon to show you that you are
in the wellman's tool.
So now our 3D sketch is ready. Our
weldment environment is activated. So we
are ready to work with weldments. In the
next tutorial we're going to show you
the different types of members or
structural members that solve works
offer you to work with. So see you in
the next tutorial. The third tool after
the world bent icon is the structure
member. Here you are able to start
working with the world bins. Let's click
on that structure. Remember you have the
standards. You have the NC
or the ISO. I'm going to use the ISO and
you have many different types. You have
the C channel, L channel and so on. all
these structural members
and in the size. So let's first select
the angle iron and select the first the
group and when you come to group you're
going to select which
group you're going to apply your
wellment set. So you are clicking on
them
then you are done. Okay. So let's zoom
into it.
can have a look
which type you already selected.
Let's uh edit the feature and change the
type. We have the same group selected.
Let's select the C channel.
Okay, so the C channel didn't work.
Let's add the size
first and no
you are there. So here you have your
seasonal type
and again let's have a look on the
second or third type you have the custom
and you have pipe size you have
different size also in you are able to
add your customized
sizes if you want. uh that is depending
on the license you have. You are able to
edit in the solid works
setting. So here you have this type.
Let's edit type
the
rectangular tube. This one which I was
looking for. And here you have the
different tabs. Let's select this type.
Now you have this set. So when you are
done
with selecting
you created these main structures
and you can also add another group.
Let's either to add a new group by again
selecting this
instruction member icon.
Let's make it five here. Size select and
then select the new group we want
which are the legs.
Okay.
So we have two set of groups. We have
the pipes and then we have the structure
member. But as you can look, maybe you
need more working or adjusting to the
corners and the chip how they would
look. So that we going to talk about in
the next tutorial.
In the previous tutorial, we created
this table with these structure members.
So maybe you need to change the type of
the corner not as the default selected
by solid works. We can edit that. You
can go to the group set you want to edit
it. Edit feature. And if you move down
here you have the corner treatment. So
if you select this type you will able to
to rotate or to make this type of
corner. So click okay. can see a look.
You have a look in here. So you might
see a better look
to your structure. If you are not this
type you want again can change it to
different
change the gap opening
and then click okay.
So here this again edit feature and the
next
plan here either to merge the
the members or keep them or keep a gap.
Let's try to merge this.
Now you don't have I mean single gap
between them
that depending on the sign you want.
Let's again edit that feature
here also you are able to add the gap.
In this case, you're not able to add the
gap between. So, you should simply cut
here and you can able
be able to add a gap between these two
members.
They can have a look in there.
This is the 101. We created this
structure table in the previous
tutorial. Let's try to edit again this
first group of members. Let's eliminate
the gap.
make it
uh merged. Okay. So now we have this
shape. Maybe it doesn't look that
perfect.
Members locations. We can try to work
with that. Let's edit the edit feature
and see the next options we have. Here
you have the allow protrusion. If you
click on that, that will eliminate the
first corner.
So it will not start
from the first corner.
You can have a look here. But this so
you know the meaning of allowation but
we don't have it. We do not have in this
case. So let's move to the next option
is to rotate
the members.
Then can
rotate
the
members.
So you can make it 90°.
So you rotated your
member 90°.
So you can try to make 45
degree.
So this is
the shape might be better than before.
So you rotated your
members
to 45°.
Okay. So we will have this shape.
In the previous tutorial, we could
rotate the members to have this straight
members
as we wanted and as the normal tables
looks like. But here we still have a
problem that this member is intersecting
with this wellman. And in reality you
can imagine this
type of wman should have a hole in there
and weld it. But it is not logical
because normally this member should
laying outside here. So we need in this
case to relocate the first member group
of members.
Let's edit that
member and try to locate the profile. So
you remember we have this group
selected. So this group representing the
members here. So for this case you need
to go to locate profile here and select
where exactly these member should lay
according to the group selected or
according to the sketch. Now we have our
members uh centered in the center of
that sketch. And if you hover over here,
you have the chance to select other
alignment tool or way to locate. For
example, let's select this point.
Your members
are laying inside
your sketch
in the middle of the vertical
length. Click okay. So you have look
here how your profile will look like but
still is not the shape we want. We can
again
edit the profile and find where is the
point or we want to locate our profile.
So to get that
table leg center
we can select this point the center to
the middle. So first we should select
locate profile.
Select that point. Click okay.
So now you have your leg is on the right
place.
So this is in the future going to be
welded with these spars.
So now we fixed that intersection by
locating your profile.
In previous tuto we created this table
and we fixed the corners and
intersection legs.
Let's try to add a supporting member in
the middle for that table.
So for that case we need to edit this
structure members.
We have the structure member is in the
top here
where the
center member blend should blend too. So
let's edit that feature.
And if you look here we have these
edges are selected.
We can try to create another edge in the
middle and select it with this group and
see what will happen. Let's edit the 3D
sketch
and add
a center member.
Be sure it is in the middle.
Okay, let's edit this
members and try to activate here. Select
this.
You notice
the structure couldn't update and
selected that edge.
For this reason, we're going to try to
make a new group. So start a new group
and then select the structure member.
Click okay. Then you have that member.
And you notice not intersecting with the
other members is
perfectly located. But now we can
rotate that member and treat it further
more. So edit feature.
When you are editing that feature, it
contains two groups.
We are going to work with the second
group, the center member.
Now let's try to rotate it 45°.
Okay.
Okay. when you find the angle
and again as we learned before you need
to locate your profile. Edit that member
select second group
locate profile
and here want
can have a look here. Okay,
so we have our member center member in
the middle of the table.
Welcome to this tutorial. We have this
table from the previous tutorial made
and we show you how to use the different
options to get your perfect climate
members.
But also there is another icon in the
members
or for the world bins. If you remember
in the beginner tutorials we have in the
tree list we have surface bodies and we
have solid bodies but the case of
Wilmans we have a cut list. It's called
a cut list. It contains all the members
you have. So there is a a third type.
Now you know it is a cut list. So we
have surface bodies, we have solid
bodies and we have members. And if you
look at the cut list, you will notice
this green dot on that. That mean you
need to update your cut list because we
already working with this table and
reedit it and added a new members. So
you need to update that
cut list. So right click on that. You
have update. You click on that you will
see your cut list is updated with
arranged cut groups.
So you have the cut list contains four
items here and we have the second group
then the third group which we added it
to the structure member one.
So here you have an arranged view your
members.
Welcome to this tutorial. You remember
we have this table from the previous
tutorial. In this tutorial we're going
to talk about the next feature. Here we
have trim and extend. In this tutorial
we're going to talk about the extent.
Let's try to make a gap between these
members. Go to the first structure
member. As you remember, we have this
slide. We are able to create a gap. So,
we will create this gap to
to let you understand the type. Okay. We
have this gap of 10.
So we have this gap. Now let's try to
extend this gap.
Click on extend to have body to be
trimmed or extended. In this case this
bar.
Now in the trimming boundary you have
two options either select body or face
plane. Let's select first the face. And
this is the face where we going to
extend to.
Now you have the preview.
Now if we select the second option the
bodies you are able to select the whole
body here. But the difference here you
are able to select this type of pending
and in the wing gap. In this case, if
you choose this SL, you don't have a
holding gap because this will be
intersecting with the body. But you have
this straight end
gap.
You are able to get or make a gap for
certain
material.
I'm going to use this.
Okay. So, this is the extend feature.
Tutorial 106. In this tutorial, we're
going to talk about the trim in members.
We remember that we fixed this leg
members by locating the upper profile of
the members and locating them above the
that member or the leg. So, let's get
back to that situation,
the original situation.
locate profile and select the original
point where it was before. Okay.
So now we are back to the original
structure combination when you have this
leg is intersecting.
So if we don't want to change the
members
location or locate profile for the case
that you you have some sensitive
structure and you don't need to locate
any profile then you can do the second
option to trim that part. So we go to
the trim body but is to be trimmed of
course this leg and this leg
and those four legs
and now the bodies you have a lot
extension
of course and the bodies and you know
the the difference between the face and
planes. Let's try to select the face
to be that face
that face that face
and that face. So when you are done this
uncheck the web gap here.
Okay. Now you trim it these legs to this
face or this plane level. The next
feature in the Wilmas toolbox is the
extrude feature. And if you look at that
icon, extrude both and original extrude
in the feature menu, it is the same icon
and they are doing the same function. So
actually it is the same tool. For
example, you can insert a sketch on the
top of that member. Click on that,
insert a sketch.
Then you are able to create a sketch.
there. Activate extrude
and extrude it.
Also you can insert a sketch in that
face convert entities extrude.
So you are able to extrude and create a
gap for that.
So the extrude tool it is the same
job like the extrude we learn before. So
let's just leave that gap
because there was a special function or
tool in the elements that creating gaps
to close your members.
In this tuto we're going to talk about
the feature we said about it in the
previous tutorial the inc cab. So Wilmet
has a special tool for creating inc cab
for your members. Let's activate the inc
cab. Select where you want to apply your
incab. So this is the first preview for
the selected inc cab. Here you have the
thickness of your incab.
make it two or you can simply keep it
five and you can make it inside.
Okay.
So as you notice it changed the
alignment of the member. So it is cuted
some of your member.
Now let's try it on the other side. See
the other options we have in the in cap.
Let's select the incap. Select this side
and make it outside. This time
here you have thickness ratio. If you
want to keep it 3 mm or just keep it 1
mm.
So you have now if you have the
thickness ratio is one that means it's
going to cover that
or it's going to make a 1 mm to 5 mm
ratio outside. And if you want to
chamer this excess, you have this option
to chamer. So you can make it 13 five
and until you get to the gap
or the cab you want.
The next function in the WM toolbox is
the gaset. The gaset is also called gr
if you are familiar with the feature
toolbar. So it is almost the same but
with different names. So in the world
means if you need extra support your
table here you can add ribs or gaset.
Let's activate the gaset. Select where
you want to add it. So select these two
edges or faces. So you have your gaset
inserted in that place. So you have
different types of gaset
and you are able to change
dimension of it and where you want to
locate it.
You can see
how this is located. So you can sit on
the edges.
And if you want to move it
or change that location to be in the
middle, can select it here. Select that
middle thickness.
And then you have your in the middle
and in the thickness here you can add
the thickness you want. So I keep it 5
mm. Okay. So when you are done click
okay. So you have this shape or this
inserted. You can do the same thing
here. Select this face that face and we
have already these option select from
before.
So
again,
In this tutorial, I'm going to discuss
about the rest of the tools in the
willbents toolbox before going to the
last stage which called the will bed. So
the next feature you can look extrude,
cut, hole, wizard, chamfer and reference
geometry. We already talked about all
these features in the previous
tutorials. They are exactly the same
like the ones in the features menu. You
have the extrude cut. If you look at the
icon is the same with the same
description exactly with the whole
wizard chamber and the references.
So let's try to activate the whole
wizard. Try to make some holes to your
members.
And here we have the different type of
holes which we already talked about. So
you can select this normal type iso
and make it the through all. Go to
positioning.
Find the position where you want to add
the hole.
Add
some dimensions
to it.
[Music]
Can
can increase the
the whole diameter to 10
then. Okay. So we have this hole in that
member. You can
also use some of the features menu tools
canate the linear. You can combine them
with wmanments tool to reach to your
required
[Music]
So this is the idea of how to use some
of the rest tools.
They are exactly that you can combine
with these both tools
to create your
required shape.
[Music]
This is the last tutorial in the wel
band section. Now we are ready to send
this
structure to the welding process after
we are done with the completing the
structure as we want.
So we have this table now is ready to be
welded.
So for that reason we need to specify
the type of welding
and how much you want to weld and so on.
You go to the well w bed build that tell
the technician
the way to build your structure. Now we
have the strips inserted to this
structure. So the strips can be the
places for welding. Now we can select
the faces where
to insert your W.
So select this face and this face.
You have that W inserted there. So you
can try to weld in this way for all your
ribs.
And in the selection you have also the
amount of the radius of
welding. Let's make it five mm.
So that mean will give you a radius of 5
mm. If you are familiar with the
theoretical part. So if you select
both sides, it's going to select on both
sides. So I'm going to keep it on both
sides. You have all around can w all
around the edges. I'm going to make it
both sides. And I guess it is that too
much weld weldments to be added.
We can try to make spot welding
and in the define weld sample. If you
are familiar with the types here, you
can select but I'm keeping it to the
default.
The length for example
will length we have as you remember we
have this strip with the length of 35
mm. I'm going to decrease it to be 30
mm.
So you have it
here. You can change it to
the exact place. So if we make it this
30 from 30 or 25 and here we make it 5
mm.
So you have that will is in the middle.
So you're going to add um 10 mm or 5 mm
offset from that member with the length
25.
And there in the intermittent w you can
select to be spot welding. So we can
make it a gap and with length. So we can
get make a gap of 1.75.
So we can make
the the spot
length be 2 mm
with 5 mm gap between. So I guess this
type of W is enough
and that will be repeated on the rest of
the ribs we have.
So by this way you going to build that
structure and be ready for using in the
workshop.
So now we are done. So here you can have
a look there
and if you hover over there you should
see the sign of the wind.
So this icon here is going to show the
technician
how to read that.
Hello and welcome back to new series of
war tutorials. We finished it recently
with the series of weldment and in this
tutorial we're going to start a new
series talking about the assemblies.
So we remember when we started the solid
works when we start making new parts you
click into new you have three options
you had the part assembly and drawing.
And now we're going to talk about
assembly and see how it works.
and and later on we will going to talk
about the drawings. So here you have the
assembly icon and click okay and you are
done and here you started a new
interface talking about the assemblies.
And as you notice the interface is quite
different a little bit from the part
interface. You have the it component,
insert component and so on. So now let's
start to insert our first component.
So here you have the browse
then you select your part
then click okay.
So as you notice here you are moving
your part everywhere and click where you
want to add your part.
So when you are doing this
the part should be
stick on the origin. This is what we
going to talk about in the next
tutorial. But in this we're going to
have an introduction about the assembly
interface. So as we said it's quite
different from the part and it has its
own
menu the assembly menu with its
functions.
And here another important thing you
have the ms where you will be able to
create ms between different parts.
And if you have a look in here, you will
notice the if at the beginning of this
part which indicate that part is fixed.
So in the next tutorial we going to try
to insert more parts and see the
difference between the fixed and the
minus sign.
And also we going to try to figure out
the positions where this part is
inserted.
Also one thing else I want to mention
about in the mids they are indicating
the type of the ms between the parts and
there are many levels starting with the
first
or the basic ms then to the advanced
industries I'm going to try to cover
most of the ms
in the previous tutorial We inserted
this first part to our first assembly.
In talking about inserting parts, there
are many different ways you can follow
to insert your parts. So as we remember
we saw the browse menu where we could
browse for our part. But before that we
talked in this tuto about assembly and
assembly parts have a different
extension than the parts. So for example
let's have a look here we have three
different parts and you can see the type
of the file is different for the
standard part document it has the name
solid works part and for the assemblies
you have a different types called solid
works assembly liquids so they have
different extensions
so this is one point and then now Let's
try to delete this assembly.
Don't save. And before creating a new
assembly, let's just open that part
before. So now we have our part is
opened here.
And when we start to create assembly,
you have an options
called the make
assembly from part. So this is another
way to start your assembly. In the
previous tutorial we did that by
creating new then assembly. So there's
another way that you can try to make
assembly from part. Now let's just try
the first method. Click new because I'm
going to show you something as simply
click okay. So as you remember we opened
the part two before starting this
assembly. So you will see that part two
is here in the list of brows. So this
way can be
timesaving if you have your parts
already open or you have been working
with them and you will be able to see
them here. So you can click here and
then you insert your part.
Also we said about something about
positioning.
Let's go and try to show where this part
is inserted.
You can go to show origin.
So now you will notice that this part
origin is inserted
far from the assembly origin. So you
have two different origins. So this an
important you have to think about it
because if you will have an assembly you
should know your origin that might be
important for your parts to know their
origin.
So in the next tutorial when we start
talking about MS we will try to fix it
with the MS method. Also in this
tutorial, we're going to try to find
another way to
try to position that part into that
origin. So in this tuto, we're going to
continue talk about inserting part.
Also, you have another way to insert
your component. You have insert
component and again the browse
menu will be open and again you will be
able to start or add another part. This
we going to talk about in the next
tutorial. So here let's close this menu
and close this assembly. Don't save and
we have this part is open. We said
there's another way there you can start
your assembly. You can go to file make
assembly from part. So you have the same
menu
exactly as if you click on new assembly.
So you have this part is selected then
you can put it somewhere on that
assembly.
So let's close that assembly and show
you another way for creating another
assembly. So let's just minimize this
window
and let's create a new assembly. Okay.
And see you have two
window. You can also try to make them
tighter horizontally. So you have this
part and you have your assembly.
So you'll be able to
So there's another way to insert your
parts just by
dragging them directly to the assembly
interface. But before doing that we s
there is an
issue that you have to know where you
are positioning your part. Let's show
the origin here and also show the origin
here. So now you are able to see both
origins
and then you are able to
pick this part and match it with the
origin of that.
So try to drag it on that origin
[Music]
in order to click okay. In the next
tutorial when we start talking about MS
this might be quite tricky to place your
part on the origin. So when we start
talking about M we will find a easier
way to position your origin. So see you
in the next tutorial.
In the previous tutorial we talked about
the different ways to insert your
components. And we remember from the
previous tutorial that we could drag and
drop that part into the assembly
interface here.
And we said we want to position our
origins to the place that we want. In
this part our or in this assembly this
part is inserted the origin of that part
is inserted to be
parallel to the middle of that edge.
Maybe this is not the way I want. Maybe
I want the origin of that part to be
somewhere else to be consident with the
origin. And we found that inserting or
dragging and dropping that might be a
little bit tricky to find your exact
position.
And we remember that from the previous
tutorial that we said you can see when
you are inserting your first part you
will see the if sign at the beginning
that indicate that your part is fixed.
So this is the meaning of the if. So
that mean you will not be able to move
it around unless you float that option.
So in this we going to start our first
myth. We said you have ms here. So the
ms they are the way to create the
relation between the parts. So in this
tutorial we still have one part. In the
next story we will start and having more
parts and more examples for using a
simply MS. So for example to start your
M you can click on M here simply and
then select the
type of the MS. So when you are clicking
on the M you will see the standard M the
conincidence. So you can understand from
that simple the conant making two points
or two edges constant parallel
perpendicular tangent and so on. And
here you have a distance you can create
a distance and angle and then you will
have the advanced meth. We are also
going to talk about them where you have
the symmetry weight and so on. Then the
mechanical meds
also we going to talk about the the
and there are the three types of the
meds. So let's first start with the
conant m we said we want to make this
origin conant to that origin. So here
you have this window where you can
select the parts or the feature we're
going to consider and let's click on
this origin and on this origin you'll
get an error message because as you
remember this part is fixed and can't be
moved. So here is the quick selection
where you can click on undo
and let's close the M menu and this part
let's make it float. So now you have
part is ready to move. Let's click on
that origin
and when you click on that origin you
will see the M icon here. So this is a
quick selection also you can use it from
here. So let's click on that click made
conant
then click that origin.
[Music]
So let's try to
select this origin this.
So that mean we have an error because
when we inserted that part let's delete
that
then you'll see here you have the
consider is working.
So now you move your part to
origin of the assembly.
In the previous we used the first type
of mating the concent
and we remember that we floated that
part. So now you can get back and fix it
again after we inserted that M. So you
have your part fixed on that
origin of the assembly. So now let's try
to find uh another use for the
coincident made. Let this insert
component
browse
and click part two. So now we have a
second part. This just add it there.
And if you want to insert another part,
you can go to the insert and again
browse for part two. But you have other
another easier way. You can click on
control and drag that part. You'll be
able to create different parts by using
the control.
So now let's
activate the mess. Let's select the
the
edge
and click M
and then click the
fixed part or
surface. So you will have the option to
make them constant.
So as you see here and if you want to
flip the direction you can click on that
arrow. So you will flip the middle then
click okay.
So you notice that you have that surface
bottom surface is
consistent with the bottom surface of
that. So let's try use another case.
Just select that edge
and then select that edge. You will
notice that the M is still open. Click
that edge. So conant also will be
done. Click okay. So you see that
we have different cases. We made the
conant with a point the surface and uh
with an edge. So again to fix
so if let's try to make
these two blocks on each other you can
again select that surface and that
surface then you have the constant then
click okay you will also able to create
that
with the edges.
So now we have two parts are inserted in
each other. When you are done click
okay. So if you have a part is not
required or so you can delete it by find
it here then right click delete.
Yes. So now we have two parts inserted
in each other. If you try to insert
another M logically it will not
be necessary. So you'll get an
overdefined
message.
So that mean you don't need that because
now your assembly is fully defined as
you see here.
We will continue talking about ming. In
the previous tutorial, we created these
ms the consent ms to create or to
arrange this
glass block.
So if we want to make a gap between
these two blocks, you can you have many
options to do that. form the coincident
m here. If you want to find that m you
just hover over it to know where is the
m you want. So you have that m you will
be able to edit feature or to edit that
m and again you will be able to
modify on that m and here you have a
distance. If you click on that, you'll
able to
to modify that M. We are not able to
work with that because we have another
constant M with the edges which make
these parts are sticking together. So
let's close that and let's here
make
or to delete that you have an option to
delete or you have another way to
suppress that. So you can click on
suppress you will not be deleting just
to hide that effect. So now you have
this coincident. Let's edit that part
and let's add a distance.
So here you will be able to create a
distance that you want. When you are
done, click okay.
You have another way to do that. You can
click on that distance. This delete
that. Yes. Click on that surface.
Make sure that you are selecting the
right surface
m
and select the parallel m
and this surface. So you will have these
two base will be parallel to each other
and you will be also able to add a
distance for the parallel relation. So
when you are done click okay.
So here you have your
M is done.
This we're going to talk about the next
type of MS the perpendicular M. Let's
delete that last M.
And to avoid any overdefining or problem
in creating the new perpendicular M,
let's click on that
surface.
Let's pick two surfaces.
Let's pick this the bottom surface. So
be make sure that you are selecting the
right surface.
So here we have this surface mated
with this surface
but we want it to be perpendicular.
So here you have that
perpendicular
relation is done. So when you are done
click okay. To fix it more, you can make
this edge
consider with
the edge.
So you have solid works automatically
selected the conant because it is
logically
will be working. So when you are done
click okay.
So here you have this perpendicular
relation is done.
So with the distance you can also add
distance. For example this is
perpendicular or this conant you can
edit it and add some distance to change
the place you want.
So this is the perpendicular
M or relation.
In this we're going to talk about the
next type of MS the tangent M. This is
an interesting M type. So it can make
the the constant m but in the cases that
the conant can't work. We deleted the
previously made ms the perpendicular.
Now we have this part is free to move.
We remember that this part is has the
minus sign and this is a fixed part. So,
so in this case we want to make this
surface to be tangent with that
circular surface here.
So the conant will not work. So you have
that option to use the tangent. So let's
select that
surface
made select the tangent. As you can see
from the simple it is a circle with the
the flat surface
and the second let's select that
circular
surface. So now you have that
surface is tangent to that. You can flip
the direction. You're done. Click. Okay.
So here you have that flat surface
tangent to this circular
surface. So this part now will be moving
tangent to that surface. So then click
okay.
In this tuto we're going to talk about
the concentric m one of the most used ms
and assemblies. So for using the
concentric ms we should have some
circular surfaces and cylindrical
surface to make this made to work. We
have this pin paper spin made in the
solid works tutorial
channel. So we will use them to create
our concentrate meth. So if you want to
do to make this product you can find it
in the you can find a tutorial how to
made it in the solid works tutorial
channel. So let's start a new simply.
Okay.
And as we said because we have the parts
is already open. You will see their
parts are here. So you don't need to
browse for them. So let's insert this
part. Insert component
the cap.
So in this tutorial we'll be combination
between the concentric m and also the
conent made. So let's select this
cylinder to make it in the center of
that cylinder.
So you can click on that surface
made and the second surface you have
this surface is select. So now you have
the concentrate relation is automat
automatically selected because logically
it is working here. So when you are done
click okay. So this is one way to use
the concentrate. But as you notice this
part is not it is moving but
concentrating to that cylinder. So let's
just
delete that m
and show you another way to create that
m. Al let's select this time the
circular edge this edge only and then
let's activate the M and then select
that
circular circular. So again you will be
able to select the concentric
then click okay.
So you have to choose to select
surface cylindrical surface circular
edge or both together. So now you have
these mates are concentrating together
and this part is moving.
You can add another relations to fix
that part as we learned in the previous
tutorial
the con consent relation. So we select
that surface and the second surface can
be
the bottom surface here.
So we have the constant
M selected. Okay.
So now we have our product is ready. So
this part is not moving anymore.
So in this way
this product is ready.
In the previous tutoing
every time with selecting the mates type
and then create the m. There is another
way to create your mates by the alt key
or it's called the smart mates. You
don't need all the time to start the
mate menu and select type. So let's
start make some parts.
Let's make a cube very quick.
Cube
to use it
as an example for our MS. So now we have
this cube. Let's make an assembly from
save and make an assembly.
insert that
cube. We have this cube and we know that
by the control key you can make other
instances.
So now let's
show you how to use the
smart m. So we have this fixed cube and
we have this smooth cube. So select the
face alt and drag it to the face where
you want to create your mail. So you
notice the icon is changed or the mouse
cursor is changed. So now you see the m
icon which is now ready to select or
make a m. So you selected that face
or that face
you'll be able to create that
made automatically. So you have the
chance to choose which type here. If you
want just simply make it a conant and
you are able to flip the size if you
want.
So you are done. Click okay.
Let's try to make another make. We have
this face is con to that. So now let's
select that face. Click alt and select
that face.
So you'll notice that we are able to
make a constant relation with that face
as well.
So now we define two
mates
very easily and very quickly. So let's
select that face. Alt that face
consent. Okay.
So this is a quick way if you have big
assemblies and you have enough
experience with solid works to know how
to deal with the smart mates. So let's
again select that face. Alt select that
face and make it this time a distance.
So you can increase as you want. So now
you have this distance relation.
We can
delete that distance
made. And let's try another thing.
Select that face. Alt.
Keep holding alt and then
select that face.
When you are done, release your
make sure that you made that m before
releasing. So let's make an angle
relation. Let's flip the direction and
make the angle for example 31 or 45.
Enter when you are done. Okay.
Select that edge.
Alt select the other edge.
So
coincident relation. Okay.
So this is another way to create to
create your smart net very quickly.
From this tutorial, we're going to start
talking about the advanced mats. We have
this products made in the solid works
tutorial channel. So you can find it
there. And in this tutorial, we're going
to start working with the width m. So
the width m is kind of advanced
assembly. It is kind of combining the
conant and parallel. It bring you the
part exactly in the middle between two
flat surfaces. So you need four flat
surface. In this case we have this is
first surface second and two on the
other part. This one this one. So you
will guarantee that this part will be
exactly in the middle. So to start with
the width we click on M and here in
advanced M you find the
width M. So let's activate the width M.
And here you have two fields. You have
to fill them. The first two
surfaces
and then the second
two surfaces.
So now you have this with simply is
applied. So this part is exactly in the
middle between
these two surfaces
as you notice here. For example, if we
just apply the constant m
there will be a gap on the other side
but with the width you'll get your part
exactly in the middle. So and when and
then we can apply another m one stand
the concentric as we know.
So now we have this part is
simple but if you notice here
this part is rotating all around
and this is not real. So we to deal with
this thing we can
talk about that in the next tutorial
when we start talking about the angular
ms.
In this tuto we're going to talk about
the angular m. We said in the previous
tutorial that this part is not rotating
like this in the real world. So we will
try to apply some angular m to limit
this angle.
So we can give a specific angle to
rotate. And here also as you notice this
one also needs some angular ms. So let's
start apply the angular m on the button
and the connector here. So we can find
two
planes
that can be par each other and can apply
the angular m. So let's find the first
part here. The bottom part is this one.
So you can try to find
the right plane
and then go to the mir
advance made you will find the angular
limits here.
So we'll try to find the second part
connector
white plane as well or the plane which
is
parall to this
in this case right plane as well. So we
have these two planes and you can
imagine these two planes can rotating in
a limited angle. So let's make a default
angle 30. Make here 50 and minus 50.
Okay. So let's
try now to rotate this part. Now you
notice you we limited the movement of
this part. So it is more realistic right
now. Now let's apply it to the connector
and the top part
with the same idea. Fine.
the planes or rotating planes.
So in this case here we have one plane
for the connector.
Then
we have it selected here and then we go
to the third part
find the angular plane.
So these two planes had to be limited
with an angle and again activate the
angular
make it 30. So as you notice you have to
reverse direction
and minus 50.
Okay,
we are done. Okay, so now you notice
that we limited
the movement or the angular movement of
these parts.
It's more realistic and
nice to work with.
We have this pipe branch built in the
solid works tutorial channel. So if you
want to build it, you can find that
tutorials there. Let's just
show this part complete part of this pi
branch. And let's talk a little bit
about it. Here you have this knot when
you are moving this part. So you have
this knot is rotating also. If you
rotate that knot, you will rotate the up
part as well. Just we applied some limit
m so that stop this part from moving
away from this part. So this story we're
going to talk about the screw
m this part from the advanced
assembly we applied that screw mate on
this not on this part. So let's hide
part two here.
So now we can see clearly
and let's have a look at the screw mit.
So you cannot we applied into edge this
edge and the face inside and here you
have the rotation direction
and then here we added the the pitch
revolution or the
when we applied when we made the helix
we added a pitch of 6 mm.
So you have to add it here as well. So
each revolution this part will move 6 mm
up or down.
So this is the idea how to use the screw
on. Okay. Now we are moving this part.
You see this nice rotation
and also we have we when we assemble
that part we make some study that this
knot will not be
interfering with this part as well. So
this is the idea about using the screw
mate
and
can try to
build this part and buy it.
This tuto we're going to talk about the
hinge mate this part and the mechanical
ms. So the hinge mate is kind of
combining two
ms together in one options exactly like
the width made which we talked about it
in the previous tutorial. So let's try
now apply the
w the hinge m you can find it under the
mechanical nails and we have this hinge
build in the solid rocks. If you want to
build it, you can find the tutorial
there.
So let's now choose the hinge. Here we
have it. And when you click on the
hinge, it will require from you the con
selections and consider selection. So it
is clear. These are the concentrating
parts. And now the consent
faces will be this part
and this part. Now we apply that hinge
made on this.
So when you're done, click okay.
Now you can notice that this part is
rotating exactly like a hinge. And it
need one more m to fix this rotation. We
talked about that type of mids in
tutorial number
122. The angular
mid. So the angular m will
limit the rotation of the spark. So you
can try with this. You can find the
angular m and the advanced m. angular.
We assembled these two gears on this
board.
This gear is made in the solid work
tutorial and we're going to use it to
explain the gear made in assembly.
So first of all
we firstly applied some basic MS. We
have the concentrate here, concentrate
here
and the concent with the surface here.
Now we already know about this type of
mess. But in this we're going to use the
gear m.
We have this uh two gears.
First let's align them that are are not
interfering.
So,
and then we go to the M
mechanical M.
This first gear selection. Now the gear
M is activated. You select the ratio. We
have the diameter.
If you select the
this part and this part, you will get
the same ratio
because we have two equal
gears.
Then when you are done, click okay. So
you have your gear M is ready. So when
you are rotating
the second gear will rotate with the
same speed. But if you change the
diameter you have to
explain that in ratios so
that the mate will understand the
difference in the speed. If you have the
mate also you have to check the
direction of the m if
this gear is rotating on the
right way. But if you have a belt in
that case you need to reverse the
direction.
So this is the idea about using the gear
m.
In the previous tutorial, we talked in
details how to deal with parts and
creating parts and the functions and
tools to create the part and then we
move to the assembly to assemble our
parts. So now it is the next step after
making your part and assemble them to
present them in a 2D way. So it's called
the drawing process. So when you click
on new you will notice here you have
part assembly drawing. We have been
working in the previous flow with the
part then we move to the assembly to
assemble these parts. Now the next step
as we said the drawings. So in this set
of tutorials we going to start talking
about drawings. How to present your
parts simplies
or whatever by drawings.
and and here you can see a brief
production is a 2D engineering drawing.
So in this tutorial we're going to
create our first drawing. To create your
drawing go to new
drawing then click okay.
Here when you click on there you have
the standard which type of papers or
which size you're going to use. So let's
choose A3
and if you have a different type you can
browse for it but this turnout is the
ASO so I'm going to use this and here
you have some width and height and the G
format. So when you are satisfied with
this format, click okay. So now you have
your drawing sheet of paper.
As you notice here, we have the model
view window because we have our assembly
is already open. You can see it here in
the browse window. If you don't see your
assembly, you can browse for it. And
simply you'll notice that you are able
to
drag and drop your
[Music]
so if you couldn't
drag your simply there. So you have the
second method is if you look here to the
right you'll see view pallet. So if you
open it and here you can select your
assembly and here you see all your
views. So as you know from the
engineering book the drawing is
projection presentation for your part.
So you have three main views. the front,
top, and the left. So, it's up to you to
choose which
projection you want. And then let's
start with the front view.
So,
you can just drag it and put it in the
sheet. So, here you have your front view
and when you drag to the right, you will
get your right view. And then you'll
have your top view and then you will get
your isometric view. If you move in that
direction.
So here you have your drawing is done.
When you are done you can click escape.
So this is your first drawing sheet. In
the next tutorial, I'm going to show a
second or a different way to create your
drawing.
In the previous tuto, we created this
first drawing. So now, let's close it
and let's show another way to create
your drawing. So you have your assembly
is open here. You can go to the file
make drawing from assembly. So you can
click on that. Here you can select your
drawing file. Okay. And again you select
your ISO
sheet you want. So let's click this time
A4.
Now you have your drawing and as you
remember we can go to the view layout
model view to browse your model. Also we
said you can go to the view pallet to
drag your projections files directly to
your sheet meter
to your sheet paper.
Also there is another way I'm going to
show is if we just minimize this
window
here we have your assembly
can simply
take it
drag it to this sheet.
So we are done click okay.
So you create your
sheet here or you created your
projection front view projection
directly by dragging your part. So when
you click on it you are able to move or
change the layout of it. So this is your
front view. If you click on there you'll
see projected view. you will be able to
extract the projection
and then you have your isometric view.
So when you are done you click okay and
here you have display style you already
familiar with this you can use it as
that show or this type of showing. When
you are done, click okay.
If you want to change the display style
of your part, for example, click on the
part you want and here you can select
the display.
For example, if you want to display the
hidden line of
your part.
In the previous tutorial, we showed you
how to start creating drawings from an
assembly or a part.
And now we're going to repeat this
process again.
and you will have an idea how to create
a drawing if you didn't watch the
previous tutorial. So go to the this
icon make drawing from simply or part
and select your sheet type then okay
here you see as a first way you see the
projected views. So select front.
If you get back to fillet, drag it
here. Automatically it
project your views. You're done. Okay.
This tuto
in in this sheet is the one to five. We
try to make it a little bit bigger.
So we can do that. If you click on that
part
and then roll down you will see the
scale. So you can select use custom
scale can try change it to be one two.
So now we have this scale is changed.
Then click okay. But in this method you
will notice that here on the sheet down
you will see that the scale didn't
change on the sheet. So that mean this
undo control
or
let's bring back
the projected view.
So now let's change the scale again to
be 1 to five.
Use cheat sheet scale.
Okay. So this is the sheet scale. So
what we can do right now is to find
another way to change this scale. On the
sheet, right click, you'll find
properties.
And here you can change the scale of the
sheet and also you can change the name
of the sheet. So let's try to make one
to two. Okay. Now you have your
sheet.
There you can see the scale is one to
two. In the previous tuto we showed you
how to adjust the scale of your drawing.
But you notice here that the cheat is
smaller to the size of the scale. So we
can try now to change the cheat size.
You go to properties, right click on the
cheat properties. And here you have
sheet size. You select the type you
want. We already have A4. Now we can
select A3.
Uh little bigger. So click okay.
So now we have that bigger sheet. That
is look better. Now we can adjust the
place of
the
the views.
And
here we can keep the
isometric view.
In the previous tutorial, we tried to
change the cheat size to get a better
view because it was the A4 smaller for
our view. But now we got another issue
that the isometric view looks bigger or
actually has no place to fit. So you can
change the scale only for the
asomemetric not the whole views. You can
click on that view here.
Use custom
scale then select one to five. When you
are done click okay. And you will notice
so
the scale of that single view Android.
So now we have that scale. So now can be
easily fitted.
And here we can adjust more
the views.
So now it looks a little bit better.
You're done. Click okay.
From this tutorial, we're going to start
talking about dimensions. We created
this drawings as we remember from the
previous tutorials. So now it is time to
add the dimensions because it is
important to have the dimensions any
drawing. And as you learn in the
engineering book that the dimensions
having some rules that you need to
follow and you can easily know the
difference between the type of
dimensions
and errors and so on. So to start
working with dimensions you have smart
dimensions icon here. You click on it
you will find two types of dimensions.
You have the smart dimensioning and the
dimension expert. In this story, we're
going to talk about the dimension expert
and then we're going to use the smart
dimensioning because the dimension
expert is kind of faster. So let's click
on dimensions and select your view.
You will notice you will get an error.
So when you are selecting this view,
you need to select a vertex or the
reference point to your dimensioning. So
let's start find any point here. You
will get a message that the dimension
expert is used in part level not on this
assembly. So let's go here. I created a
part
a single part here and I'm going to make
a drawing from this part.
So let's place our
parts here.
So now we have
these
parts. this just
so now back to smart dimensioning
dimension expert
and here you know the different between
the baseline and the chain type of
dimensioning that depends on the
baseline is clearer but sometime it
depends on the area and the
available places your dimensions
So here you have the vertex or whole
center. I'm going to select this center
or this point. So now we have a
reference point to for your
dimensioning. Now you can simply click
on the
bars here
and you will get your dimensions
automatically done.
So that is very fast way to create your
dimensions.
The previous tutorial we used the
dimension expert to create very fast
dimension into all parts. But the
dimension expert, it doesn't work with
the assembly level parts. So let's go to
smart dimensioning. In this case, we're
going to use the smart dimensioning.
So also we can create our dimensions.
Just click where you want to add your
dimensions. Then you have the chance to
move to add your dimension or simply
click on this half circle to position
your dimensioning on the right way. As
we said, dimensioning has some
type of place to be added. For example,
this distance should be around 1 cm or 8
mm. So again, let's start adding more
dimensions. Click that edge.
So,
same idea.
We can create
our dimensions. So, as you notice here,
this dimension is higher than that
dimension. This is what you learn in the
engineering book.
So again we can add or continue adding
more dimensions to
our assembly.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about another way for creating your
dimensions. In the previous tutorial, we
used this smart dimensioning tool to
create the dimensions in this part.
So, let's just delete this one. Click on
that and delete. Activate smart
dimensions. And if you go to the view,
right click, you will find here more
dimensions. You have the horizontal,
vertical and so on. The vertical and
horizontal they can be done almost with
the small dimensioning.
And here we're going to use the vertical
coordinate. It might be
done also. So when you are selecting
your first corner here you have the
zero. So this zero is the starting point
for your vertical dimensioning. Then
you're going to select these points
here. You created your vertical
dimensioning. So it might look better
than the previous
used dimensions.
So let's select this one
also. So we have this dimension is
great. So when you are done click okay.
So we can also try doing it with the
horizontal level. So we can try do it
here. Go to small dimension.
I click more dimensions
horizontal or coordinates.
Let's select the
the zero line.
So we have our zero. Then
can continue selecting
these lines
and creating
dimensions. It's very fast and
nice to use. You can adjust the player.
So
[Music]
in the previous tutorial, we created
this dimensions.
And in this tutorial, we're going to
show how to adjust these dimensions.
We mean with adjusting is adding more
text to it or changing the font and
size. First of all, if you want to add
something to the
existed dimensions, you click on it and
here you'll find this quick menu. Here
you can write for example if you want to
add any
marks for example external dimensions
and here you can write for example
millimeter. So you are done it's okay
and you have also chance to change the
the font and the size of your the of the
dimensions. For example if you go to the
dimensions
and here go to the others you'll see
that box is checked. So uncheck that box
and click on font. And here you have the
different font types.
And here you can choose the size of your
font. In this case, I'm going to use the
points and write
10. Click okay. So we adjusted that font
to be more smaller and maybe it has
better look.
Now we can select more
than one by holding the control key. Go
to other font.
Let's click then
activate the points then. Okay. So we
have all these dimensions
selected with
the 10. Or maybe we can make it even
smaller.
to eight.
So we have these dimensions now shown in
this way with smaller font.
When you're done, click okay.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about another method for saving some
times when you are making your
dimensions
with it's called the model item method.
So if you go to the annotations here
and you will see the model items. When
you click on it here you will have your
choices. So simply you can choose the
entire model. When you are done just
click okay.
Solid works will create the dimensions
the all dimensions for you all parts.
And here you have the chance to modify
them.
If you are not
if you want to change it further. So
here you can modify some items.
And here you have all your dimensions
created for you. So this is an advantage
for creating your
dimensions if you don't have a lot of
time for making them. Maybe in this
model it is quite simple to make the
dimensions but in the case you have a
bigger assembly with a lot of dimensions
it comes handy. For example, we already
created some dimensions here and used
some kind of techniques to create these
dimensions and adjusting them. And you
can add the rest of the dimensions with
the models model items method here.
Select the entire model and also check
the import item into all views
and then solid works will import all the
dimensions which we used in solid works
to create the parts. So here you have
all the dimensions.
So
if you find it
you can start modifying them.
So the advantage with using this method
that it give you all the dimensions
which will define your drawings. So
you'll be sure that there's no dimension
is missed.
Just maybe you need some time to
adjust place of your dimensions.
In the previous tutorial, we used the
model items to import all the dimension
used to create these models. And as you
see, this piston contains a lot of
dimensions. And if you want to create
them manually, it might take a lot of
time and you may miss some dimensions.
So we created them with the import items
or the imported items model and we have
all the dimensions here and as you
notice it's fully defined. So this is a
very good tool to use especially with
some complicated
assemblies like this one.
So when you are done with that you click
okay. So now we're going to take go to
the next step
where we going to modify the block
title. So if you hover over it you will
notice the cursor
icon is changed. So that mean you are
able to
to work with the
block title.
So right click and go to edit sheet
format. So your sheet will turn into
blue. So double click on the title here
and then
add the the name you want. For example,
this
drawing
then you have just change size and so
on.
So here the material for example you can
edit it
and write
the
steel
for example
and as well you can modify the date and
so on.
And also you have chance to add some
text. For example, you can click on
notes and select the area. For example,
we have the title
uh our engine
piston
here.
So you have that text and then you can
continue the same way adding
the
rest of the notes that you want.
[Music]
So when you are done editing your block,
you exit your shape for map.
In this tutorial, we going to use the
accelerary view. The Excel view is
creating a views that you are defining
the edge you want, not that default
isometric or views which are already
found in when importing your parts. For
example, we want to make an projection
view from that edge or from any other
edge. But if you for example let's now
activate the accelerary and for example
here you can choose the quality you want
select that edge so you have that
accelerary view from that edge also you
can
do it from that
edge as well. So here you have
that view according to that edge which
you selected.
So this is the idea of using the
auxiliary views.
This we're going to use another type of
views the crop view. But before we start
using the crop view for example you
created the accelerary view in the
previous tutorial and you have the
letter C and D. If you want to change
that, you just click here and simply
write what you want. For example, side
then you'll see view side. And here for
example, you can write angle or simply
a. Okay. So we have the A view is
showing.
So now if you think that this view is a
little bit bigger than should be then we
can try to crop it. This is the idea for
using the crop view. But first we need u
an area to be cropped. For example this
view is intersecting with this
dimension. So we can try to make it
smaller. You can use this rectangle
and create center rectangle B
make a
so
can make that angle can try to make it
smaller
to the area you wanted
then. Okay. So you have this closed
profile, this rectangle. Go to view out
crop view. So now your view is croed
according to the area you selected. So
when you are done
rebuild, you have this icon here. You
build
your part. Then you have your drawing or
croet view as seen here. In this
tutorial, we're going to talk about the
section view. It is often used in
drawing. To create a section view, you
have in the view layout menu section
view. Click on it. So you have now to
select just one view. If you if you saw
that message. Now select this
view section view. Now you need to draw
a line. So you have different type of
lines how to create your lines either to
make it vertical or horizontal or you
choose the points you want. For example,
let's try to make it a vertical one. For
example, we want to see the section of
you between this circle and this slot.
So now let's add this line. When you are
done, click okay. So now you have your
section view. So you can add it in the
place you want.
So now you can
you're done. Okay. So you can defy the
place here a little bit
and
let's move this one as well here. So you
have your section view. You have the
letter E and here is the section E. So
if you want to modify that just click on
that you can simply type B enter. So you
have section B. For examp if you want to
change the direction to make a cross
section from other side just flip the
arrow here. Just click on there.
So you click the section clip direction.
Click okay. So when you have that
section can update your
drawing. So now you can we can try
another way to make uh inclined line. So
go to section view. This time let's use
the accelerary view. So now we can
create this acceler
select place.
Okay. So you have that extra view. So
here in the option you have the
selection view or either to have it
surface or or to hatch it and so on. So
this is things you can choose as you
want. So now we have this accelerary
view with the hatching line.
So when you're done click okay.
In this tutorial we're going to talk
about the detailed view. Dead view is
like magnification for one part you
choosing it. For example, if you are not
seeing clearly for example let's try to
make a detailed view to this area
somewhere here. So to do this first we
go to the sketch
create a circle and let's make a circle
here
so that we would like to see detailed
view for this. So now because we already
selected detailed view before so now we
have that detailed view. So now let's
do it from before again. Let's select
detailed view. Select draw. Then go to
sketch. Select circle. And again, let's
select an area. We want to have a
detailed view for it. So now you have
that detailed view to that section. If
you want to change the scale, click on
that detail view.
Then go the scale. Make it for example
one two
or make it poly number two to one.
So when you are done click okay. So you
have that detailed view to this part you
selected and you edited also the scale.
You are also able to say to change the
view name as we said before.
In this tutorial, we going to use the
next step of use the broken art section.
The broken out section is create or is
breaking or making um a hole inside your
part to see inside of it. So let's
activate the broken out section or
before activating the broking out
section to escape. We just want to
change the view of
the view style of
this. Let's select this one
and change
the view style to be
this
material. So now let's activate the
broken view. Let's draw a spline where
we want to make
the view or to exclude
the view. So now we're going to select
the part which is going to be exploded.
So let's select this part.
Okay. Now let's make the depth. We want
to make the cut until this edge. Click
okay. So now we are able to see inside
this part after creating this broken
view. So now we can see the piston road
inside that part.
In this tuto we're going to talk about
the next
type of views, the alternate position
view. This is kind of nice type of
viewing. It shows the movement inside
the assembly while it is a 2D drawing.
So let's start activating alternate
position view. We created only this
view. We already know how to create the
views. So we just pick it this front
view. So now let's go to alternate
position view. We can also work with the
previous assembly just here to be more
clear. Use it. Now we select this view.
Now here you
change the name for example alternate
position one. Click okay. So your
assembly will be open. So now you're
going to move this piston rod to the to
its maximum angle
and when you are done click okay. So
here you having composition view showing
the movement of your P of your piston
rod. So it is good view to show the
movement
inside your drawing.
We have this drawing sheet. We have been
working with it since we start about
drawing. So as you see we have here kind
of complicated drawing. So it is how it
looks in the real
companies and
the real life.
So today we're going to use the
brick view. So the brick view is useful
when you have such long parts and you
want to save some space in your chip.
So when you have a long part and nothing
happen and that is like continuous shape
we can break that. So let's select break
and select this view.
Now we have two tabs. Select you have
the vertical or the horizontal. So can
try horizontal one and here you have the
types of the cutting line zigzag curve
and so on. Here you have the gap you're
going to break. So you can going to give
the gap 10 mm. And here going to select
curve.
Then here's your first cut. Then this is
the second cut. So as you see we cuted
the part and
normally person can know that this area
that be will be continue. So it is
clear. So when you are done click okay.
This is the idea how to use your brake
view.
Now we are in the last stage before
finishing our drawing and sending it to
printing.
So as we see we add all dimensions and
we had a look at the views on different
views if you want to use some special
views to make some parts clearer to see
or whatever. And also if you go to
annotation you will have the surface
finish with simple and so on. They are
easy to use. Just select what you want
to add and select the surface. For
example, this piston surface. You can
add the simple and uh the amount of
surface finish or whatever. So this
types of sample you already studied in
the engineering book and if you need to
add them so you can just select and add.
There is nothing special in this. Just
now we going to show an important step.
Before
finishing your drawings, you need to
show the names of the parts, the number
of the parts in your drawing. So this
can be done by the bill of material. You
can reach bit of material in annotation
menu tables. Here you'll see bill of
materials. So, so select drawing
and
so we just do it again. Select a view
then go to tables build of materials.
So you will get this menu the bit of
material menu. You have the standard one
and parts only top level only and so on.
At this moment I'm going to use top
level only. And then you will click
okay. So now you will see the bill of
materials shown in your drawing.
So here you can place it in a good
place. So you can see the names of the
parts
engaged in this drawing. And here if you
click here you will have the ability to
change the
number positioning and so on.
Let's change the size of
the
text.
So here you have your bit of material.
So also you can show it on the parts
level. Click okay. But in this case we
don't have sub assemblies. So you'll get
the same table of material. But now we
have an issue that we see our bill of
material but we don't know where are the
parts. For example who are not familiar
with pistons will not know where is the
piston head piston pin. So here comes
the use of balloons. So you have
balloons. You are able to add balloons
one by one. So for example, this is
number one. This is the piston head.
Automatically it is marked. So here you
have here number one. And if you select
this one, you will get number three
which is piston rod. And
here you can see
number four
which is the piston rod cab then you
have here number two the
piston pin. So we can also if you have a
lot of parts and you don't want to do it
one by one you just cancel these
balloons. Click on that and delete it.
You have auto balloons. So solid war is
going to generate the balloons
automatically to your parts. So you
select
then go to put balloons.
So now click okay. You will see the
balloons
here inserted automatically.
area of number three
but still you are missing number two
then you need to add it by yourself
it's not shown in this part you're going
to have it here so when you are done
click okay so now our drawing is almost
ready to be printed because it's include
all the dimensions balloons parts bill
of materials the title block and so on.
So I hope this set of tutorial was
useful and you are ready to create your
own drawings.
Hello and welcome to the very first
tutorial in level two in this course of
solid works. The level one was the first
and this is the first tutorial in level
two and it is tutorial number 146
in the solid work course.
In this series we are going to talk
about the sheet metal menu. Solid Works
has special menu designed for the sheet
metal products. Sheet metal parts or
sheet metal part designs are exactly the
products which are produced by the
manufacturing processes related to sheet
metals. As we know there are many
products around us that are made by
sheet metal manufacturing process like
knives, uh the power supply, computer
chassis and many For example, let's take
this sheet metal part which is made in
another channel. This part or this
products is made by the sheet metal uh
menu and in industry it is also made by
sheet metals. For example, let's take
this base here.
And as you notice it is a piece of metal
which is punched to get that shape and
then
bended.
Solid works and the sheet metal menu has
calculated all the values depending on
the metal you are using which you are
able to pick the metal and that is
really a timesaving and will increase
the productivity.
So now let's see how to start the sheet
metal menu or how to access the sheet
metal commands. This is the assembly
mode. Start a new part
and let's see how to access the sheet
metal commands.
The first method as we said go to insert
and then you will see a complete menu
for sheet metals commands.
You have base flange convert and so on
which we are going to talk about in this
series. The second method is to which is
easier is to have the menu
here on this bar. Go to this menu here
and click on right mouse button and then
check the sheet meter menu. Here you
have your sheet meter menu and when you
press on it you see the sheet meter
commands the base flange convert hem and
so on.
As you notice here the many of the
commands are not activated. That is
because you need to have a sheet metal a
part of sheet metal to activate the
commands. So let's start making our
first sheet metal and it will be very
simple.
Go to base flange. So let's create a
base
and click on that and pick your plane.
Let's pick the two plane
and let's
make a center rectangle
and give it some dimension.
For example, let's add 100 mm
um 200.
Press okay. And then exit that sketch.
And here you have your
sheet or this piece of sheet metal.
Here to the left, you can pick the
thickness
of this sheet metal. And then you have
the other
options which we are going to talk in
details in the later tutorials. We
talked about the bendings.
The type of bendings. You will have many
options here. And then you have the auto
relief. Let's put uh 1 mm
thickness for this
sheet meter. And then here you have your
first sheet meter.
And before finishing this tutorial, I
would like to thank
Satish, one of our students for
reminding me to start uploading the
level two tutorials.
So see you in the next tutorials. This
is tutorial number 147 and it is the
second tutorial in the sheet metal
series. In this tutorial we are going to
talk about these points. First we are
going to talk about some approaches when
starting a sheet metal part drawing or
design. There are many approaches
depending on the shape of the part you
are going to make and then we going to
talk about the first command in sheet
metal the base flange and we will see
what will be new on the tree on the
solid works tree when we are starting
the sheet metal command in general and
then we are going to talk about the key
factor and how it is related to the
material properties as we know there are
different sheets for example steel
aluminum cover and so on and then we are
going to talk a little bit about flatten
so let's go to the this part which we
started go to sheet metal and you see
here the base flange and beside the base
flange you will see convert to sheet
metal lofted bend and then you have the
four main tools. As you notice, we have
only two commands which are activated
and the rest are deactivated
and they will be activated once we start
the sheet metal tree. So now let's talk
about the approaches when you start to
draw a sheet metal. There are basically
according to the sheet metal menu four
approaches to start or to make a sheet
metal product. You have the base flange
which is the mostly used and um it is
almost 90% of the sheet metal products
are created by the use
of B flange. Then we have the if you
have a little bit more complicated
shapes then you have the lofted bend or
you can create by other uh commands like
solid feature then convert it to the
sheet metal as you see here convert to
sheet metals or by forming tools which
is kind of die mold. Now let's start
using the base flange. At the beginning
to make it easier, you can imagine the
base flange exactly the same like the
extrude to the sheet metal. We can press
directly on the base flange. Then we
pick the plane we want to draw on it. I
just click X or we start as we used
before picking the plane that we need.
Then draw the shape. Let's pick the
front plane. Start sketch. I'm going to
make a simple L shape. Let's give it
some dimension.
Let's give this 50
and here 25.
Go to sheet meter and select the base
flange. So as you notice it just
extruded the L shape with thickness.
Here you see the base flange menu. I'm
going to talk about the very basics for
now. We are already familiar with. We're
going to talk about the directions,
the sheet metal parameters
and for the rest we are going to talk in
the next tutorials. We are going to talk
a little bit about the bent allowance K
factor. Now let's go back to the
extruded sheet metal. Here you can pick
the thickness. You have 75 mm. I can put
it one mm. You can notice that the
difference. Let's make it make it clear.
5 mm. You have the thickness of the
sheet metal.
Then you have the bend radius. You
notice here we didn't add any radiuses
at the corner but this is the bending
radius. It is um logical when you are
bending any sheet you get this radius
and here you can specify this radius if
you already know the value. So let's put
2 mm for that bending.
And then if you go to the very first
option direction it is very similar to
the extrude. You have blend there you
can increase
the extrusion or the the length of this
beam. And then you have direction too.
We are already familiar with that. We
talked about that in the extrusion. Also
you can make you can extrude on the
direction too. Let's deactivate
direction too for now. Here you have
again the same options similar to what
we used in
extrusion.
I'm going to pick mid plane. Then you
have your extruded part.
Mid plane extruded.
And here you have under the thickness
reverse direction that where is your
metal you need to be placed. If you
reverse direction
you will notice the sheet metal is
extruded inside. If you reverse
direction it will be outside the shape.
And when we are done with this shape
click okay.
And then we have our bended sheet metal.
We talked about the base flash. The very
basic explanation. Then we will have to
look at the sheet metal tree. As you
notice the difference between extrusion
and the sheet metal. Here you have four
element instead of one element. In case
of extrusion you have the cut list.
Then you have the sheet metal. the base
flange feature command and then you have
the flatten. So this is for
starting every time you use the sheet
metal commands and here you notice the
sheet metals commands are activated. the
elements of the sheet metal tree the
these fours the cutless the flatten and
sheet metal we are going to talk about
them in details in the next tutorials
but right now I'm going to just edit as
we learned before when we need to edit
any feature go to the base flange and
edit feature and you will notice you
have only the basic options are appeared
which we discussed it you have the
extrusion distance which you can you are
able to change and you have the
thickness and millimeters. The reason
for that is sheet metal when you start
the sheet metal commands it assumes the
whole part will be the same type of
sheet metal. So there is no need to
specify all the time the thickness and
the bending radius because it is the
same metal or the same sheet metal for
some reason. If you wanted to change the
thickness or the bending radius, you can
override the values over here. And
again, we as we discussed it before,
let's just click okay. And to get to the
sheet metal properties or the material
properties, you have the sheet metal
here. If you click on edit and this part
is related to the material properties.
We said that we're going to talk about
that in the later tutorials. A little
bit about decay factor.
So as we know there are different types
of materials, different um materials for
sheets. You have steel, aluminum, copper
and solids calculated the bending radius
when you are bending a piece of metal.
For example, when you are bending a
sheet of steel, you will not get the
same dimensions when you are bending a
piece of aluminum. And that is defined
by the bent allowance or the reliefs or
the gauge table. So, okay factor as we
said there are different materials.
Harder the materials decay factor will
be bigger. Softer the material decay
factor will be smaller.
This is a very basic explanation about
the expectation of bending a sheet of
metal. So now let's just click okay. And
the last thing we have the flat pattern.
We will going to talk about that in
detail in spirit tutorial. the flatten
the flat pattern when you bended this
sheet of metal. You can again
uh return it to the original shape by
unsuppressing
this feature. This feature is suppressed
on this flat pattern and unsuppress
you will get again that piece of metal
before bending.
If you want to exit from the flat
pattern, you go to the exit
flat pattern here in the corner.
Welcome to tutorial number 148 in this
solid works course and the third
tutorial in sheet metal series. In this
tutorial, we're going to talk about the
next sheet metal feature edge flange
and we'll talk about the first option
flange parameters which include edit
flange use default radius. So let's
start making a piece of sheet metal.
Click new part and first thing I'm going
to specify a material. This is an
optional step just in case if anyone
would be interested. And here I'm going
to pick a stainless steel
sheet.
This is a a common sheet of metal. Then
go to the sheet metal base flange.
Pick the plane
here. We're going to select center
rectangle with some dimensions
sheet meter
base flange the thickness here I'm going
to specify um 1 mm
and here decay factor will be 04 and
this This is why I pick it the stainless
steel
material. So in this case will be 04 and
in future tutorials we going to talk in
details about the bend allowance. Now
click okay and for the reverse you can
notice
from the
drawing here how that will change. Then
click okay.
Also, I'm going to pick a stainless
steel as a piras.
And here is a very simple sheet of
steel.
So, let's see how to use the edge
flange.
Here you will notice the edge flange
option. Click on the edge is this fe
this feature is to creating a flash on
the edge. So pick the edge. Here you
will see the flange parameters. Select
edge.
Go to the sheet and select the edge
where you're going to create your flash.
Going to select this edge.
And then when you
reach the length you need, click okay or
on the right mouse button.
It is a very simple
edge flange. But we have created this
shape in the previous tutorial in one
single step. Here we have two steps base
flash and then edge flange. I'm going to
show you how we create it in one
single step. Go to the right plane
sketch
normal to and make
it shape.
adding some d some
dimensions.
Let's make this consider or horizontal.
And then sheet metal base flange
to extrude
the L shape
m length.
Click okay. As you notice the sheet
metal parameters is grayed out because
we already
specified it is a sheet of steel with a
K factor 4 and we can change it as we
said in the previous tutorial. For now
click okay. Here you have the second
beam we created
in one single step. So let's make
another
shape where we can notice that the edge
flange is a handy tool.
Go to the right plane
and make
a U shape.
Give it some dimension.
And now let's extrude it by the base
flange. Go to the sheet metal
base flange.
And here we have a U-shaped
beam.
And now let's start use the edge flange.
Select edge flange.
And this time we're going to select this
edge. Now in this case you have
the edge flange.
You can make it in a way that you cannot
do it by the base flange. So here you
can select the edge you need. You can
select it from below or the above edge
and give you the same result. And this
arrow if you click will change the
direction
of this edge flange.
The second arrow here is
the length of the flange. We are also
able to change that length in the next
options. But for now I am talking about
the first option the flange parameters.
And when ch when you change the length
both of the
edge flange changing at the same way.
And when you are done click okay.
And here you will notice that we bended
both side of this
sheet metal.
The next option in the edge flange
feature is the edit
flange profile. For example, when you
selected the edge, it selected the whole
edge. But how if you need just for
example to have half of that, you can do
that in the edit lounge profile.
And you'll notice profile sketch.
This sketch you are able now to change
it.
If you go
the profile
and here is the sketch.
You can change it by dragging it
freely.
change the length
of it
and you can even add
dimension to that. You can for example
add
and this side
10.
You can also
change the shape of that sketch. Let's
select
a line here. Select the midpoint here
and the midpoint on the second line
and trim
the corner.
And you will notice how you changed
the sketch. And when you are done, you
simply click finish.
And you notice how is the shape of the
flange. Go back to the edge flange edit
feature. When we edited the edge flange,
we were able to change this side. Let's
try to change.
And we are just able to finish or to
edit this side. There is a second
approach. You can reach to the
sketch and you can change it on a
different way. If you go to the edge
flange that in case you want to
change the second side, you will notice
you have two sketches. That sketch we
already edited
as you remember.
Exit from that sketch. You can select
when you hover over this sketch here.
Edit. And you'll notice it is in this
side.
We can edit this sketch
at the same way. Add some
dimensions.
and then click okay.
And when you are done from that sketch,
exit the sketch
and you will have your edge flange
edited the same way.
So there is two approaches to edit the
sketch of the flange. Now let's see the
next option. In the edge lounge again
edit feature you have the use default
radius as we said before when you create
uh sheet metal solar work assume you are
working with the same sheet of metal in
this case stainless steel sheet with a
thickness of 1 mm and using the same
press which giving you a bending radius
of 1 mm. So there is kind of no need to
change that. If you change for example
the
press and then you need
and the bendings
radius change according to that you can
you override the values and you will
notice
that Yes.
Welcome to tutorial number 149, the
fourth tutorial in the sheet metal
series. In this tutorial, we're going to
continue talking about the edge flange.
The next option, the angle. How to add
an angle to your flange. There are two
options. Selecting the angle directly or
choosing a reference face. Start a new
part.
Here I'm going to select the appearance
steel and create simple
base flange as we learned.
Make a U shape
some relation
midpoint
equal
And let's add some dimension.
Extrude it with the sheet metal. This
flange one
100 m length.
And there you have the
steel sheet meter.
And now add an edge flange as we learned
in the previous tutorial. Go to edge
flange. Select the edge.
Extrude it to approximate height. Select
the second edge and it'll be
automatically the same height.
And here next you will see the angle
option.
So this edge flange right now is 90°
angle and here you can change it
according to requirement.
So I'm going to add 150. And you will
notice the the shape.
Add 120.
Then okay. Here you will notice
how you bended
the edge flange with an angle. It is not
the
perfect shape right now. We can deal
with these edges in the later options.
But now we see the angle.
Also you can make the angle into the
side. Go to the edge flange
edit feature and change the angle
less than 90°. For example, let's add
75.
And as you see here, you bended.
Let's edit the edge plunge again and add
50 because I want to see the
intersection error or warning. Click
okay. Here you get a warning that there
is intersection between the bendings.
This issue we can solve it as we learned
in the previous tutori by editing the
sketch.
make the edge a little bit
thinner
or in the later options we will see how
to deal with this bending. So let's get
back
and make it 90°.
So the next option is selecting a face.
Right now we cannot select any face as
you notice.
We need to create a separated part. Now
I will make a wooden core separated part
inside this sheet box so that I can bend
the next edge flange on it. Select the
plane in this case the right plane
sketch and intersect here to make it
easier to see
normal tool. Here I'm going just make a
very simple
piece of wood
and add it some dimension
equal relation.
here
and mid point.
I make this shorter than the edge flange
like 10.
So this is logical to bend it.
And let's add here 25.
Extrude this
shape with the extrude boss. Make it mid
plane
and 30 be enough. And make sure to
uncheck the merge result. So it is a
separated part.
Back to original and let's add some
appearance to this score. I'm going to
make from wood.
So now we have this
sheet box and we have a piece of wood
inside. And then I want to bend the
second edge. So select
again sheet metal edge flange.
Select the edge and select this face.
You can notice you bended
the second edge flange parallel to that
face. Also, if you select the second
edge,
go to edge.
Select the second edge.
And you see the angle is
calculated according to that shape. It
can be difficult to
put it by yourself. And here if you
make it perpendicular to the face you
will get it in that
shape. You can see this edge flange is
perpendicular to this edge. Let's make
it a little bit shorter so it will not
intersect
the inside.
And when you are done click okay.
So this is one way to select a reference
face. Let's get back again edit edge
flange and make it parallel.
Click okay. And this is another case. In
the later tutorial, we going to create
the same shape
where this wooden core is
tangent with that edge flange. So we'll
have some intersection and the later
options will show how we can fix that.
Now we can again think about other
cases. Delete the second edge on the
face. You can also select
that face over here.
For example,
you make it par parallel to that face.
You can make it perpendicular.
It didn't work. But you can make it
parallel
that face.
But this option is not necessary because
you can make this click okay because you
can make the same by selecting edge
flange
and make
the same.
So again back to that edge flange.
Select the face
over here. Okay.
So we see many cases by how you can
manage the it flange angle.
Welcome to tutorial number 150 in the
solid works course
number five in the sheet metal series.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next option on the edge flange
menu which is the flange link. We are
going to talk about the
types of how you can
make the length blind up to vertex up to
edge and merge. Also, we're going to
talk about the place of
edge length outer inner tangent blend.
In the previous tutorial, we talked
about the
other option. The first option flange
parameters angle. We talked about them
in details. In this tutorial, we're
going again to talk in details about the
flange length.
I started a new part file and I will
make a box from a piece of
stainless steel sheet
as we learned in the previous tutorial.
and it will be a repetition to the
previous. I will
choose the front plane
and
make the box.
Go to the sheet metal.
Now I have the initial
shape of the box. Going to use the edge
flange.
Select edge flange. Select the edge
where you're going to create your edge
flange. As we learned
and select the other edge.
In the previous tutorial, we were
stretching the edges manually by the
arrow here. Now you are able to add
exact dimension to your
edge. For example, let's add 50. When
you are done, click okay for for now.
As you remember when we created the
initial shape on that sketch, let's show
that sketch.
You will notice that we added 50 mm.
And when we created the edge blanch, we
also
added we picked the blind length and we
added 50 mm.
But you can notice here that the edges
they are not the same length. That is
because of the
bendings over here. To get the exact
length of your edge, you will choose the
next option. Go again to the edge flange
edit feature.
Go to the next option up to vertex
and you can zoom in and pick
the vertex where you want your edge
flange to end. And here you can not see
you are able to pick that edge. When you
are done click okay. So you will have
the exact length for your edge.
If you look
down to the box,
you will notice this type of cut and
bendings.
Maybe you need to change the position of
bending.
that will we talk about in the next
tutorial which will be about the flange
position. And here if you notice on up
to vertex you have at the left reverse
direction. If you click on that you will
reverse the direction
of the plunge.
I'm just going to give it like before.
And now you can move again to blind. You
will see the length is 51 mm. Now I am
going to change it to
10 mm
and pick the first option auto virtual
chart
and click okay. edge flange and over
over the edge you will notice the length
is 8.26
mm. So it was not 10 mm. So the 10 mm is
the length between
if you if we measure
the length from this face the bottom
face you will get the y which is 10 mm.
So when you click the 10 mm it is the
distance
between the top face and the bottom
face. So this is the case of outer
virtual chart. Let's edit again and pick
the next option
the inner virtual chart.
Click okay.
And again let's measure the you can get
the measure two from evaluate measure.
If you pick this face and this face
for the distance of Y, you will get 3 by
10 mm. So this is the option
of inner virtual chart. So you are able
now to know the difference between these
two options. And let's again
pick the next option. It will be similar
to the first option
to not be clear for this simple shape
and
so with these options you can get your
exact length from the first time without
guessing.
Now I will make another edge flash.
Select this edge
and select edge. And if you hover
and expand this menu,
you will not still see the third option.
Delete one edge.
delete that edge back. You will see up
to edge and merge. So let's select this
option
and select the
reference edge. Go to that edge and you
not able to select that edge because
this edge is higher than that edge.
Click okay for now.
For this purpose, I'm going to create
another sheet of metal.
Pick this face. Click sketch normal to
small dimension. Make sure to be on
the limit under
then up to
surface.
Okay.
So again, return to the edge flange
tool, edit feature,
go up to the
or
move this feature up,
edit feature.
Edit up edge and merge
and select this edge.
As you notice
it connected to that surface and merged
with it. And when you're done click
okay. So this is a way to choose the
third option.
Welcome to tutorial number 151
number six in the sheet metal series. In
this tutorial we going to continue
talking about the edge flange and it
will be the last part about edge flange.
We will talk about the edge flange
position and then we will see how to
make a miter flange from each flange and
then flange length and merge.
The first thing I would like to say
until this tutorial you should be able
to create sheet metal boxes similar to
this without any problem. In the
previous tutorial, we showed you many
times how to create the same thing. We
have this box created. In the previous
tutorial, we said about this corner down
here that it doesn't look the way I
would like to see it to manage this
bending. Go again to edge flange one.
Edit the feature.
And here in this section the flange
position.
The best way to understand
this feature is have a look at the shape
over here. For example, we have here
material inside. So in this case the
bending is inside. If you select the
second option material outside, you will
notice now it looks better. Just click
okay.
a better look depending on the
requirements.
We go again to edit feature to see the
next options. Here you have the bent
outside.
So
you have the whole bending outside as
you can see over here. Go and see the
next option.
Ed branch and here you will have bin
from virtual sharp and it will be
similar to the first option in this
shape will not be clear and also the the
last will looks like the first option
for this simple shape.
So now let's pick the first option or
the third option.
Okay.
And here you have the building outside.
So what if you need that bending to be a
little bit more?
You can create an offset. In this case,
go to edit feature
and down here you have an offset
and you can extend that
surface more. I can add 3 mm. So this
option give you offset of zero. And here
you can increase that offset. The same
way as we learned before you can up to
vertex up to surface or offset from
surface.
We went through these options before. So
let's make three
mm.
And here you have the reverse direction.
You can have the offset inside. Can
click okay. And
and if you change it,
you will get
offset outside.
So now I'm going to show another thing.
Go to the edge flange and select the
first option without an object. Click
okay.
This is our first shape. And I would
like to have that
surface here to be parallel with this
edge or in the same level. But the cut
down here doesn't look that
perfect. It is sharp in here and and it
might cured while bending. We can fix
this issue
by adding trim.
Edit the feature again.
And down here, trim side bends.
Click okay.
Now it looks better and easier to bend
without
the risk of tearing the sheet.
Before talking about the edge to edge
flange to miter flange, I would like to
talk about the the merge and length
which we talked about in the previous
tutorial. We created this
edge flange by up to edge and merge.
This feature will work in case you have
the second sheet meter with the same
thickness with the first
So it should be the same sheet of metal.
If we edit this base flange over here
and override the the values here and add
to assume we have a different material,
different sheet thickness. Click okay
and you will get an error.
So you should have the same thickness.
to use the default parameter
and click okay. And now I will talk
about the edge flange to miter flange.
Suppress this extended sheet over here.
Suppress and we have this basic box.
We have an option here called miter
flange. But we are still on the edge
flange command and we will see how you
can create a miter flange by using the
edge flange. Go to the edge flange.
Select this edge. Select
this edge.
And now when you select
third edge you will notice
it converted into a miter flange.
Select the fourth edge. And now you have
this miter shape. And they are
overlapping over each other.
This for now. Click okay.
And you will get a warning that this is
intersecting. Close for now. And we will
see how to fix this.
So for fixing the miter
intersection,
there should be a gap between
these two edges. Go again to the edge
flange here.
And you can notice that you have a gap.
So this is the gap distance. You can
change it.
And you can notice here the shape
can make it 2 mm or
3 mm and keep it 2 mm. Then click okay.
And now you will notice the warning is
solved.
You can also the same option which we
talked about in the previous tutorial.
You can add an angle.
For example, you can make it 100 over
here
and you will have the bending inside
or you can make it
outside bend.
add it.
And the next option as well
you can notice over here
the length
and the position
of the flange.
And when you are done click okay.
So now we have this box
which we wanted to make.
And in order to produce this box, you
can go to flatten as we learned and
suppress this option. And you will see
the piece of sheet meter
need to be cuted to create that box.
And here you can exit the flattening.
Welcome to tutorial number 152.
This tutorial will be a practical
example where we putting which we
learned before together. In this
example, we will review the P flange and
the edge flange. We will bend this sheet
steel perfectly on this
wooden core.
Start a new part file and then start a
sketch on the front plane. Let's start
making the wooden cube. Select center
point rectangle. Give it some dimension.
Extrude it
to 50 mm
and then extrude the surface
the top surface another
50 mm. Select
Start sketch. Convert entity.
Extrude 50 with an angle of 30°. Click.
Okay.
Let's add some fillet. Select one edge
and then select the whole edges
over here
with
a radius of
1 mm.
So this is the wooden
core.
I'll just change the appearance.
Now let's make a base flange on the
bottom of this block.
Click sketch normal to
center rectangle.
Make sure to pick the inside edge.
Make it for construction.
Okay. Make another one
vertically
inside edge
for construction.
Add eorization to the edges.
Uh assign some dimension. Give this one
20.
And then you will have
the construction fully defined.
pick line and select the corners
of these rectangles.
This is the shape of the the base sheet
or base flange. Go to the sheet meter
base flange and you'll have the sheet.
Make the thickness to be 1 mm.
reverse direction
and without checking the merge result
because this would be a sheet decay
factor will be 04. And now let's see how
to make edge flange that are perfectly
bended on this wooden core. Go to the
edge flange.
Select the edge. this edge.
Select
second side.
Third side
and fourth
side.
Now let's go have a closer look at the
edge.
Now you will see the bended steel is
overlapping
over the core. This overlap in case
there you are bending this sheet of
steel without any help or without
anything. But we going to override this
value because we have
this wooden core as a helping core for
bending the
bend radius to 1 mm.
And you see you have the bend radius is
on the wooden core.
And you can check as well on other side.
But you will notice all
this side
are perfectly
matching. So now how to extend this edge
to the to this
edge over here as we learn. Go to the
flange length and select up to vertex
and select
this point.
You will notice that
the edge flange is perfectly matching
that edge.
When you are done, click okay.
And one thing before closing.
You might have this selected and this is
overlapping. You can pick the bend
outside. Click. Okay.
Go to edge flange. Select the edge.
Then
you will have an option for the edge
flange angle. Select first. Go to the
face and select
the face. And then to make the exact
length,
go to the bend up to vertex
and select
this point.
Let's check that bending is correct. So
you'll notice here
the bending is wrong. So you go again
here to the flange position. Select bend
outside and you will see
again that the bending is not perfectly
matching the edge.
Can override
the bend radius to be one
mm
and you'll have the bend
is matching the edge.
When you are done, you can select
the rest of the edges.
And you are done.
You might get this not correctly
showing. You can just edit the feature
and check that is up to vertex
and go again and it will be corrected.
And now time for the last bending and
this one will be easier. Go to the edge
flange.
Select the edge.
Extruded
oblength
make it 10 mm
and check it is correctly bended. If not
you adjust the angle over here. Select
face
and select this face.
And for the radius override
100.
When you are done, select the rest
of the edges.
Okay.
So now we have this piece of sheet metal
perfectly bended on that wooden
core.
And these are two separated bodies. You
can notice them over here over the cut
list. So now let's try to flatten that.
And here you have
go to the first extrude
show and you will see the wooden core
inside.
and unflatten or bend it again.
And one last thing I would like to show,
let's edit the last bended edge over
here with the edge flange. Edit
flash length to 20 mm. You will notice
the edges trim it automatically.
And we can edit the gap as we learn. We
can make it 2 mm
or
zero.
I will keep it one.
Okay.
Welcome to tutorial number 153. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
command, the miner flange. We will talk
about the basics of using a miter flange
and we will make a simple example and
show you how to make a miter flange and
then we will make another example to
compare with the edge flange and see the
differences.
In the previous tutorial we talked about
the edge flange and the base flange.
When we start using the m flange and the
next commands you will see many options
are similar. So you should be familiar
with them. Here I start a new part file.
So let's start to make a very basic base
of steel. Select top plan
this flange
and center rectangle
with some dimension.
Checkm base flange. Give it one mm
thickness
4K factor. Click okay.
Now I will make a basic edge flange but
by using the miter flange. Go to the
miter flange.
And once you pick the miter flange you
will see the message here.
And you will notice there are two
options to start maflange.
Simply I can say you can just pick the
edge where you want to create your
mlange. So let's pick this edge. And
once you pick that edge, solid works
automatically opens to you
a sketch
in sketch six and also inserting a
plane. So this sketch you are going to
draw your edge or miter flange. So click
normal tool, select the line and we said
we want to make it a edge flange. So it
will be in this case just a line.
So give it a dimension
50.
Click okay.
The plane or the sketch is perpendicular
to the edge you selected.
So now when we exit you will notice you
got that edge flange.
And here you will see similar options
and start end which we will talk later
about the start and end offset. For now
click okay.
So as we said once you create a matter
flange it will create a plane for you
and the sketch.
For now, there are nothing special. We
already learned how to create a similar
shape by the end flange.
So, let's see what we can do more with
the edge or the miter flange. Go to the
miter flange edit feature
and on the miter parameters select the
rest of the edges.
And as you notice
[Music]
you are simply creating many edge
flanges by selecting the edges in
series.
And when you are done click okay.
hide this plane.
So now you got this box.
So now let's continue about the next
options. Go again to the miter flange
edit.
The radius is already selected. And
let's see other options. We already
talked about the FL position. Let's make
it outside.
And the gap distance.
It is the gap between the edges or the
flanges.
You can make it 0.25 or 0.5.
I will wait 0.1.
So you know it means this gap.
So now to the next option start at an
offset.
You remember the best sketch which
started the matters. this sketch six
and you will notice it is on the corner
over here.
So the start and end gap you will notice
it means the start gap of the sketch.
Let's see the start zero and the end
five mm.
You will notice the gap with the
starting sketch and you can make
the start also five. You will get the
start and end gap and make it 2 mm
and 2 mm
and when you are done click okay.
So at this point we worked with the
miter flange and we saw the options but
for now there is nothing special. We
already could make this shape with the
edge flange. The only difference right
now is the end and start. So now I will
make another example
that will show you the difference
between the edge flange and the miter
flange.
As you remember we make this box in
previous tutorial. We made it this
flange
edge flange and another edge flange.
Three steps.
So the first is flange a U shape as you
notice here. And then we made the edge
flanges over here and here. And then we
made the miter flanges over here by the
edge flange. And as you remember with
the third flange, we have an angle of
80°.
So let's see how to create a similar
box, but with the miter flange.
Start a new part.
We start by making a base plate on the
top plane by
the base flange.
Select a center rectangle.
Make the two edges equal.
Dimension 100 mm.
Base flange
41.
Okay.
Select a mit flange
and select the edge where you want to
create. So we open it a sketch normal
tool. And now
let's make a sketch.
And this time we will have a second
line. So this is the first difference.
You have to actually made two edges at
once. So let's give it some dimension
and angle we said
80 from outside.
So it is 100
and give this edge
20.
And when you are done,
exit the sketch and select the rest of
the edges.
And when you are done, click okay.
And as you know, we talked about the
option over here.
Just click okay.
And you will notice that we created
the same box in just two steps. So you
will see that this tool is a timesaving
and also you are able to create several
edges at once.
There are cases where the miter flange
might not work. For example, if you
would like to pick a miter flange in
series,
the edges should be on one singular
part. I mean when we created this
miter flange we make it in one single
plate. So we could select the edges on
series and also the starting sketch
should be on a perpendicular plane on
the selected edge. For example, let's
start to make a miter flange on this
edge. Click mlange. Select that edge.
And we started a sketch. When you go
normal to you will see the plane is not
perpendicular
on the edge on that surface over here.
So this might create a problem and the
might flange
won't work. So let's make
a line.
Select this plane
and make a line.
Exit.
You will see view. When you click okay,
there is an error
that it couldn't work.
exit that sketch
and you can make it
with an edge flange but we will see how
to make it again with the miter flange
and delete
this
then so go again to the same m flange
there is no need to create an edge
flange
we will save the steps go to the m
flange branch and edit sketch
normal two and add another two edges.
Give it equal position and dimension 10
mm
and exit. You will notice the shape is
updated.
So we created
this box with only two steps with the
help of miter flange. So you will see
how timesaving is this tool. And imagine
if you would like to create this shape
with only the edge flange. You need one,
two, three, four steps. And also it
allow you to create detailed sketches
that cannot be created by the edge
flange. For example, let's go back to
the starting sketch. Sketch six. Edit
sketch normal to. Let's add a bended
edge or a hem.
Pick arc
and define it
some relation
dimension.
For example, this pended pitch. Exit
from the sketch and you will see that
you created that 10.
You can flatten. See how it looks.
Welcome to solid work tutorial number
154. In this tutorial, we going to talk
about the next feature in the sheet
metal after the miter flange hem. We
will talk about the how to use the hem
feature. The reasons I started a new
part.
So let's first make a very basic plate
to explain
the
hem feature.
This is uh basic plate this dimension
click. Okay.
So we have a plate here.
Here we have our basic plate. Go to the
hem feature over here. And here you will
see the options. You have edge and where
is start bending either inside or
outside adding material to the base. And
you have the types and size. I'm going
to select first the closed one. And you
can notice the shape of the hem.
So
you're going to
pick this edge and
here you see
this bending
and you can give it a length
for example
20 or
5 mil. And this is a bending outside.
You will see the bended sheet is added.
And if you pick inside, bend will be
included in the base plate. And then you
can select the next one. The open
here is not shown
because the value here might be small.
Then change it to 10.
And you will see the type
of this pen. So this type of bin mostly
can be decorational or during some
function.
Here you can change the length
and the inside or the gap distance.
Make it 10 and make outside and you will
get this shape.
So let's move to the next type. Go to
the hem
and select the tear top. This one will
always touch the base. And here you can
change the degrees
and the inside radius. I can make it one
mm.
The types of hem explain the reason why
you are using them. The hem are used
mostly
for safety reason because the sheet
edges are sharp
and it can also for doing some function.
For example, you can pass some wires
inside
or for decorational read. And the last
type over here roll where you will get
the same type but you will have a chance
to make a gap. If you this one you will
always touch the base sheet and here you
will get with a gap. For example, you
can grad
and the
control the angle. Click okay.
Also with the hem feature you are able
to
pick many edges at the same time. Go
again and edit the edge
and select the rest of the edges.
So you can notice over here. So you can
imagine this kind of and you are able to
reverse the direction of the hem. If you
look to the left, you can pick the edge
and reverse the direction.
For example,
one by one or you can rever them all.
And one thing before closing this
example, if you go to the hem and pick
it the first type closed,
you will notice
the length of 10 here.
You will notice the box will trim the
corner.
This is kind of small steer
door.
Welcome to tutorial number 155. In this
tutorial, we will continue talking about
the hem and see how to edit and compare
it with the miter flange and see the
differences. At the end, we will make an
example using the hem.
We made this box in one of the previous
tutorials and we created that hem here
as you see manually with the miter
flange. As you remember if you go to the
starting sketch sketch six edit sketch
normal to and you will see here we
created that hem. But we also could do
it by the hem feature. But the
difference here that you are able to
create a custom shape hems that are not
available in the him options. For
example, we can add an extra extend here
2.5. And then make this distance
2.2.
exit. And you will notice we created a
custom shape
he done.
Click okay.
So this shape is not available with the
hem feature. So this is one thing also.
If you notice here, you could create
that hem without any intersection here
in between. So let's try with him. So
just one thing in the sketch here we
made this distance 2.2 so that the
sheets will not intersect otherwise you
will get an error here suppress or make
this
to construction
for now
and exit. Now we don't have any hem over
here. So let's try to use the hem
feature.
Go to the sheet meter
and on the edge select that edge.
So you can edit the
the values
and select this type for now. You can
reverse
edge. Select
second edge.
Click okay. So here you got an uh
building error because of the
intersection. Let's try to make it bend
outside and also let's
make
this type but you still have the
intersection over here. Click okay. So
you get an intersection here that we
could avoid by using the miter flange as
we see before. So let's again edit the
hem. You can try also the values over
here.
Also, you have another thing to do if
you would like to fix this thing. You go
here to the edit him width. So, you can
drag
this edge
and the other edge.
and then click finish.
So this is one way to edit the hem and
also you can try to edit that edge as we
learned
you can go to the him you have this
sketch over here if you would like to
edit the second hem. So you can edit it
manually,
can add dimension.
We didn't select all the edges because I
wanted to show you that we also can
mirror the feature. If we select the
right plane and then go to the feature
mirror
and select the hem
pick geometry.
Okay.
The second edge you can do the same
mirror
and select the front plane
and
select that edge. Click okay. Geometry.
So I made the hem
on the opposite side so it will be
easier to see the edges and how to deal
with this.
So one way to deal with this
intersection to increase the gap over
here. But sometimes the gap should not
be increased but let's just see how to
do it. Go to the miter flange and edit
feature. And here the gap distance we
can make it
1 mm.
In this case we can use
the manual him. So let's suppress this
him
and again return
normal to
it. And let's again
edit the gap of 01.
Click okay.
We have a hem that is not intersecting.
So these are some of the differences
between using both. So hem it can be
faster in simple shapes and the manual
hem integrated with the miter sketch can
be easier in more detailed shapes.
So now I'm going to start a new example,
start a new part
so we can see how to use the him with
two different functions.
I go to the top L and create
sketch.
So if you try to create a press flange
with this sketch, you will get an error
because of intersection. So go to the
sketch and trim the
edges over here.
This flange.
Click okay
with the thickness of 1 mm. Click okay.
So let's go to the hem. First of all, we
need to add a safety bending for the
sharp edges.
Go to the hem and select
the edges. We will pick this type.
Give it a distance of 10 mm
and select the rest of the edges.
As you notice, we are able to hem this
shape as well. Click okay.
So this bending is to avoid the sharp
edges
as many of the sheet plates. Now let's
make another hem to do a function to
hold the door. Go to the hem. And this
time I will pick the teardrop
and select this edge.
Make it 2.5.
And the angle
you can edit the angle according to
requirement
and you can also bend it inside.
Select the other
then click okay.
And we have this
door over here. So we used the hem for
two reason. First to avoid the sharp
edges in the first hem and for making a
function to hold it with a hinge.
You can edit the edge the sketch if
to make it if required make it a bit
shorter. Click okay.
Okay.
Welcome to tutorial number 156.
In this tutorial, we're going to talk
about the next feature after the hem the
job. And if you hover over the feature,
you will see a brief definition of this
feature. And there is a sketched line.
For that reason, I thought to start
talking about the bending lines and the
boundary box lines before starting the
feature and then use the job in two
cases, closing and offsetting.
So first what are the bending lines? We
have this box which we made in one of
the previous tutorials. And if you
flatten that box,
you will have
the sheet, the original sheet
metal.
And if you notice over there, you will
see dashed lines,
vertical dashed lines and presented
dashed line. And those are representing
the bending lines. So they are showing
at this edge or at this side you are
going to bend.
These bending lines are important
because without them you don't know
where to bend exactly. So you can
imagine this is the 2D drawing. And
let's hide the sketches.
And if you send this piece for
manufacturing, they can cut it by the
method they are using either milling,
punching, water jet or whatever. But
after that, for example, you don't
exactly know where are the bends. So
let's again show the bending lines.
And here you can know exactly that
there's a bending over here and then
here and so on. Also you can access the
bending lines if you go to the flatten.
Also you can see them all in one sketch
in the bend line sketch over here.
And the one after that is the boundary
box lines. So they are representing the
outside boundary of this shape. So you
can imagine if you would like to cut
this piece of sheet metal then you need
to send it is representing this boundary
over here
which we can see it by the boundary box.
So let's unflat this box and start a new
part to use the job feature.
I will make a box. I will go to the top
plane and select the
corner rectangle
and make
rectangle and give it some dimension.
And this rectangle if I would like to
extrude it with the base flange. Let's
try to extrude with the base flange. You
will get only the plate but this is not
the thing I want. Close it and
make an opening in this sketch
and take corner rectangle
and make it for construction and then
trim
the entities. You can give again some
dimension over here
and trim the
unnecessary edges.
And again go to
cheat meter base flange extruded to
mm.
Click okay.
So now we have cheat middle box with an
opening over there. And you will see how
to close this with the job feature. So
to close this logically you need to bend
this side over there and cover extend
that edge under it. So let's see how to
do it in the job feature. So we learned
that there's bending lines. So the job
will ask you about a plane where you
create a sketch or to have a sketch. So
let's first
try the first method by creating
a sketch. So select this plan. Solid
works will open to you directly a
sketch. So go to normal tool
and then create a bending line.
Here you are going to create your
bending and give it a dimension
of 10
mm.
that except
and here the job options
the fixed face
it is clear to be this face
and here you will see that you are
offsetting
the edge
and if you make it normal too you will
see the edge will remain the same but
with an offset
And the next command jog offset can be
blind.
There you can add
the distance
or up to vertex up to surface which we
mentioned before. And then you have the
dimension position.
So we pick it 10 mm. So the 10 mm will
be from the down edge
to the upper edge
or from the inside edges over here and
there or from
the
inside edge over here to the outside
edge over here. So in this case we know
that the thickness is 1 mm. So I will
make it 1.1
and give it some tolerance. Here to the
left you can reverse the direction. We
said that the edges are matching but
here can the bend included in the
length.
Check that. and the choke position.
You can decide where to
make this bend
after the line
or in the center of the line or on the
edge of that line. And here is the
angle.
If you would like to add an angle to the
bin,
I can make it 80
degrees
or
50.
So it will be
matching
the edge.
and give it some tolerance.
Then when you are done, click okay.
So let's make the determined minimum 1
28.
Click okay.
So now we bended
this edge. So, let's extend the other
edge to close
the box.
So, after creating this
job, so let's extend the other side to
close this box. We will do that by the
base flash. If you notice here over the
command this flange slash tab.
So let's see how to extend that edge or
make that tab. Click on that face
sketch normal to
and draw a rectangle. So you can see the
edges
where to start this rectangle.
from this side before the bending and
ended on the
down corner
and the
the rectangle is fully defined.
Go to the
sheet meter
base flange
and here merge results. Click okay.
So now it will be one single chip. And
if you notice over there in the tree,
solid works recognize it as
it has its own sketch.
Welcome to tutorial number 157. In the
previous tutorial, we made this box and
we made that joke close the box. So in
this tutorial, we will see the second
method of creating a jog by an existing
sketch. We will make a hanging tab on
this
box.
So let's start a sketch on that face.
normal to
and I will draw
a slope
and define it with dimensions.
and earth relation.
So we here we have
this slot and I will make it for
construction
because I need the down part.
put the line
and quickly
make this
same slope. So if you go to the extrude
to make the cut,
you'll notice that the thin feature is
not working. So let's
create the sketch manually. Go to the
sketch
offset
and offset for 1.5
mm.
Click okay
and close the gaps.
Go to the ext.
And here up the next
So now let's start a sketch for the
bending line. Click on the same face
sketch
normal tool. And now I will place the
blending line over here and see if it
will be accepted.
Go to the exit the sketch or
go to the jog.
You will see that the job is activated
over here
and the fix it face. Select this face.
But you'll notice that the jog feature
didn't work and you didn't get the right
view.
So close this and again let's edit
this line. So again let's talk about the
bending lines. The bending lines should
be in the center of the bending radius.
For example, exit that sketch and go
sheet metal and
flatten.
And here you will notice the bending
line. And let's again bend it again
just to make it clear here. Here you
have the bending line and a flatten
it's over the bending lines here over
here. And you'll notice
the bending line is in the center of the
bendings.
So let's again edit the sketch.
normal to
and let's add a distance.
So, delete this line
and make a new line.
So you see we made a distance
from the line and the bending. So let's
make it 1 mm and it should be not less
than bending radius which it is 7
something. So now let's go to the job.
Select the fixed face. And now here you
have the job is working.
So this is one issue we could solve. And
here you will see the option that we
talked about before. I would like to
make it five mm
from this face to inside face of the
tab.
Um the bending
is inside.
If we can also make it outside
or
so make it inside. And the the angle
angle I will make it 40°
and then click okay.
Here
we created this tab but there will be an
issue with this tab.
So let's flatten this tab. So you
flatten the tab and if you have a look
over there you will see that the tab is
intersecting with the
plane
and we can solve this either to make the
cut layer or as we learned before or to
make the bending radius of the job
included in the total length which is
more logical. So edit this feature and
go to
fix projected length.
So and this is the realistic or mostly
how it looks
and click okay.
Flatten
and you'll see
the cut will be similar to the sketch we
made to create this tab and flatten.
Now let's close this box.
Select
Edge fl
select this and
up to vertex
and select this point
and also select
the opposite edge.
Then click okay.
And here is the box initially closed.
And if you would like to improve it
further, you can try
to reverse the direction of this closing
jog and add more edge flanges on this
side.
Similar to this.
So I can close this one.
Welcome to tutorial number 158. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
command in sheet metal skit sheet bin.
And we will go straight to apply this
feature with an example and then we'll
see some cases how to deal with the
sketch bend and then talk about
advantages of sketch bend and compare it
with the base flange.
Start a new part.
Okay.
and we will draw a shelf hanger.
I will start from the front plane
and draw
a triangle.
And let's
give it some dimension.
and add relations.
Fill it. The down corner.
and make place for
holes. So it be easier
to save some time. I can make the holes
already Yeah.
So this is the basic sketch of the
hanger and we will mirror
this sketch. Make this for construction
and mirror
Click on this to uncheck it and the
mirror
this side. Go to the cheek metal base
flange and make it a thickness of 1 mm.
Click okay.
So now we have this flange
and now we will see how to bend it with
the sketch bend. So sketched bend is a
feature to bend some sheets.
Fill this edges feature.
Fill it.
Okay.
So now we can bend this hanger with the
sketch bend feature over here. So to use
the sketch it bend click on it and you
will again get two options as we talked
about in the previous tutorial. similar
to the jog. So you should be familiar
with this. So directly I'm going to pick
the face
and here solid works will start the
sketch to draw a bending line. Click
normal tool
and the line you will make it
in the center of this
base flange. When you are done, exit
and sol works will ask you about the
bend parameters. This is the fixed face
similar to the jug. And now you will see
you are able to bend it.
And here are the options which we
already talked about inside or outside.
And I will just keep it in the center of
the bending line. And here you can make
it with an angle.
So I'll make it
8 to 9.
And for the hangers, you notice that the
the radius is a bit bigger. So we can
override the value
to type 10.
Okay. Okay, we can click okay.
And the hole, we can make them a little
bit down.
Let's make this
sketch it bend. Sometimes when you can
get uh complicated faces or boxes and
you need to bend some edges and it can
be difficult to made it with the edge
flange. So this this feature is flexible
that you just can draw a line and bend
wherever you want. And also one
advantage with using this
sketch bend that you will get a smooth
edge over there. If we flatten
because we already draw that
sketch and we see it is smooth and when
you exit you will notice the edges as
well are smooth.
And let's compare it with the this
flange.
So if you would like to make the same
shape with the base flange,
it can be done because this shape is
kind of simple. But in some detailed
sketches when or in some detailed places
where you need some bends, you cannot
made by base flange. But let's try to
start a sketch for the this flange in
the right plane
and draw
a 90°.
The sheet meter is flanched
mid plane
and we set the
radius is 10 mm. Okay.
And here is the first step. And then
to create this triangle you need to cut
over here. And then again another step
over there.
And another thing the cut here is on an
angle. So if you would like to cut
this side and then this side, you will
not get a smooth edge
as in the case of the sketched bend
because the shape the original shape of
the sketch is made
and then bended.
And now let's see another case where the
this flange cannot make it. So we will
make a partial sketch shape bend.
Go to the original sketch edit. We will
create a tab
to support this hanger. So I will draw
corner rectangle.
I'll define it
some dimensions. is
and create a tab cut. Make this
construction offset entities
one
mm offset
verse.
Okay.
And close the gap.
and now exit.
You'll notice that this tab is already
bended with the sketch,
but I wanted to keep this straight. So,
let's see how to do this.
We can edit this feature again. Go to
normal to or we can start again
to show you how can be done. Suppress
this feature
to give it a chance to be bended. We can
extend that cut.
Make a similar
and define it.
Make this construction.
So we extended the cut
and now let's try to keep this straight
and see and start this kitchen bend
and line from this side to this side.
It said the fix it face
is this.
You can select one of these
options.
When you are done, click okay.
So here you can see that
we could
partially bend this hanger and this
cannot be done with the S flange.
Welcome to tutorial number 159. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
cheat sheet meter command, the cross
brake. In this tutorial, we will see
what is the cross brake and why and have
a look at some real examples and then
see how to apply the cross brake on a
single face and see the options of a
cross break and then we will have
another example to show you how to apply
the cross brake on multiple faces. Then
we will have a look how to know the
direction of cross brake.
The cross brake from its name it is a
brick with the shape of cross on a sheet
metal face or in another words cross
band. Here I have a real picture for a
real example. Here we have sheet of
metal where the cross break is applied
on that face.
So while they are using the cross brake
when the sheet metals
fists become long they became weaker. So
the cross break is to add some support
to the sheet metal and increase
stiffness and rigidity of the face when
it become longer or in simple words to
make the sheet metal stronger.
Here we see this on a single face. And
here I have another picture for a duct
where you can see clearly
how the cross break looks like. So this
is somehow a long sheet metal and this
cross brake will support and decrease
the vibration. And let's get back to the
first image. If you have a look, you
will see that the cross bend
has a radius and has a depth
and as well it has an angle. So when we
come to the command in solid works so it
will be clear what it means with the
angle and the radius.
So back to solid works and start a new
part and let's try to make a similar
thing
sketch on the top plane. I will pick a
corner rectangle
and make a rectangle
and give it some
dimensions. So I will make it 2 m. So it
is
2,00 mm and
the length make it 1,000.
Create a plate with a thickness 1.5.
Click okay.
So here is the
this steel plate and let's add some
edges. So pick
select the edge.
Give it
dimension of length of 30
mm and then select the rest of the
edges.
When you're done, click okay.
And here on the bend radius,
I'll make it
5 mm.
Now we have a single face plate. So
let's add a cross break to this face. Go
to the cross brake command
and here the cross break options will
open over there. And here you're going
to select the first where you're going
to apply the cross brake. So as you
remember in the picture over here. So we
will make something similar
and I pick this face
and if you look the arrow over there
that is the direction of the
cross break. So it is upward and if you
would like to reverse it you make it
downward but is upward. And here we said
the bending has a radius. So let's make
it
5 mm and the angle almost
100.
So you can guess the angle over there.
It is quite deep cross. So
you can guess the angle to be kind of
135.
And when you are done click okay.
Solid works will not show you a 3D view
of the cross break but this line they
will indicate there are cross over there
as well on the feature tree. You can see
the cross break.
So let's again talk about the cross
options. Go to the cross bra edit
feature and you have here edit cross
profile to have a successful cross break
the cross brake lines be coincident with
the edges. So go to edit the
cross brick profile and now you are able
to see the lines and modify them. So for
example if
delete this
coincident relation and make the line
shorter.
Here you will notice the finish is not
activated. So it will not actually work.
If you go back and then click okay, you
will get error. So edit the
the line again. And let's this time add
it on this edge.
So now it is coincident with this edge
but it is not on the corner.
So you can add some
dimension
there
and then finish. So you will notice that
the cross brick is working. You can do
the same on the other
edges as well.
finish the sketch. So you will have the
cross brake applied
as you see.
So now let's try to make on cross on a
multiple faces as you see here.
Start a new part.
Go to the top plane
and
create the the base of that box.
I'll select corner rectangle and give it
some dimensions.
equal and over here I will make
an opening.
So again select corner rectangle
and add some dimensions to it from this
edge
to this line five mm
and
this edge is
to
5 mm.
Untrim
unnecessary
part. So you can fully define
the dimensions are already assigned. So
we can just simply
fully define the sketch.
Okay.
Extrude
this sheet metal or the sheet metal box.
The bend rad is 5 mm.
The sheet thickness
um
mm. Click. Okay.
So, here is the initial D.
And now let's apply the cross brake on
the faces.
Select cross brag here. 5 mm. And if you
notice in the picture,
the duct here is is not as deep as in
the previous one. So in this case, the
angle can be around one 65. So 170 is
like the most of the cross breaks
around.
So we can make it around that value 165.
So pick here in the face, select the
faces
and you notice that you are able to
apply the
cross break only one time
and sol not allow you to
select multiple faces. So when you are
done click okay.
And over here we can
before applying the cross pick at the
rest of the faces we try to close this
gap.
We can do it
by adding edge flange over there.
Give it a distance
mm. Select offset
2 mm
and click okay.
So it is clear that this
face or this edge over there will be
spot wielded
with that. So now let's apply the
cross on the rest of the faces.
Cross select this face. Okay.
Crossway
in this face as we saw in the picture is
upward. Click. Okay.
And the last one it will be a little bit
special because of the adhering edge.
So let's see.
apply course break and then
this edge or this distance over there it
should be welded with the to the edge
over there.
So we need to edit the
the place of the cross brace lines and
make this point
and this point vertical and this point
with this edge make it consistent. So
now it's fully defined
and as well
and the same here.
Delete the previous relation and
this point
to this point
make it conant
and it will be directly defined.
Click okay.
So we can apply the same gap on the
other two edges to give it some
symmetry. And to do that you can measure
the distance over there
and it is
23.5.
Let's try to
and you can keep them
or you can keep them as they are.
You're done. Click finish.
In reality as we saw it looks something
like this.
And one last thing I want to say how to
know the direction of the cross brake.
As we said there's no 3D view for the
cross brake. There are two ways. First
way if you go to the cross break edit
and you will see the arrow over there
and there is also the method that they
look at it in industry is on the drawing
because there are some values can be
shown and this is we will talk about
when we came to the drawing with the
sheet metal.
Welcome to tutorial number 160. This
tutorial will be a theoretical tutorial
but it will be important tutorial to
understand the logics behind the sheet
metal bendings in order to get an
accurate sheet metals dimensions. In
this tutorial, we will talk about the
sheet metal trees
and where to locate the bend allowance
menu and then talk about different
materials
calculating the K factor
and NC general K factor values. And then
at the end of this tutorial we will see
some programs that calculate the key
factor.
So here we have a new part file.
Start with the top plane and draw
a V shape.
I'll define it here.
I'll give it some
dimension
here. Give it a symmetry relation. And
now make sheet metal beam from this
V shape by the
base flange.
And here give it a length of
150.
As you remember we talked in the early
tutorials that we will talk later about
the bend allowance over here.
So
we will discuss this menu now. So if you
open the bend allowance you will find
money
method to calculate the bend allowance.
You have bend table which will be the
topic of the next lecture and the K
factor and then the bend allowance which
is a longer equation that include the K
factor. We will look at the formula of
bend allowance and then the bend
deduction and bend calculation.
The last two they are mostly based on
experience and so we will discuss more
the first three options and then in the
tutorial after the next one we will talk
about the gauge table where you can
combine the bend table and K factor a
saving time method.
So now for now pick a key factor and as
you remember in the previous tutorial we
said this will be a stainless steel
sheet and we assign 04
K factor and we will see how we came to
this value and then when you are done
click okay.
We said in the tree you will get you
will get the cut list and the sheet
metal and this flange and if you want to
get back to the theoretical values you
should edit the sheet metal over here
and here you can find or adjust the bend
allowance
but you cannot find it in the this
flash. The reason for that we said it
considered the whole work on the same
type of sheet metal or one single sheet
metal part. And let's just specify a
material to make it clear that we are
dealing with stainless steel sheet.
Why there is a bend allowance? The
reason for that there are different
materials and as we said when you bend u
a sheet of aluminum will not give you
the same dimension as bending a sheet of
steel and so on would the cover
also
the type of press you are using. If you
have a press with a bigger bending
radius also that will affect for example
the K factor.
The K factor is the ratio between the
neutral line and the thickness of the
sheet metal. As we can see here, here we
have the neutral line
and here we have T and the thickness is
T over there. The place of the neutral
line can be changed depending on the
bend radius and the bend angle.
Now again go to the sheet metal and
let's talk about the next the bend
allowance. The bend allowance is kind of
more accurate way because it used the
complete formula which we can see it
over here. The bend allowance is pi
multiply with the radius the bend radius
plus kt over
180. So this is the formula of the bend
allowance.
In one of the next tutorial, we will
talk about the gauge tables, a popular
method in the industries which combine
both methods.
Here I return to the key factor. Click
okay.
Now you may think it is complicated
process but it is not because the values
are already calculated for the most used
sheets. There are bending tables we will
talk about in the next tutorial and also
there are even a faster way called gauge
tables will be also the topic of the
tutorial after the next. And here if you
go to the Wikipedia
you can read more to understand this
topic and you will notice it is so I
recommend you to read this article about
building. It will give you a wider
understanding
about the sheet metal bendings. And here
you will see the types also you have the
punch.
And at the end you will see
more detail about calculating the K
factor and bend allowance
as we said.
And then you have a general
table that you may use for the most
standard sheet metals of aluminiums and
steel. And here the value of the K
factor which you can pick according to
the radius bend radius. For example, we
have uh in this in our example this back
to the values over there. We have the
bend radius 7 and thickness is 1 mm
material is steel. You can find the
value will be 0.4 four. And also as you
notice here and as you notice here
when the bend radius is increasing
compared to the thickness the value of K
factor is increasing as well and the
hardness of the material
will also affect the K factor. As we
know the steel is harder than aluminum.
Here
is an example for a sheet meter industry
example for a bending press and they
have also their app for calculating the
bend uh K factors
and you can
start it here and
you go to the
bend deduction
You can see
very easily the values over there
and calculate the key factor.
As you remember, we used stainless steel
in our example and we made the thickness
1 mm and the aside and the angle 75.
the A side 126 and
then calculate
and here you will see the value of K
factor it is closed 04 if you remember
we said if you increase the bending
radius that will increase the
K factor here you have the bending
radius let's make it 2 mm meter and you
will notice the K factor became 0 five
and so on. If you make it 4 or more it
will be 6.
Now return to our
sheet meter B
and go to the sheet meter to modify
the values
here. You can change it
according to the website or you can keep
it 04. I'll make it 38. And you know
from where I bring the 38.
Click okay.
Welcome to tutorial number 161. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
method in bin allowance, the bin tables.
The bend tables include the values and
according to the material and thickness
they can calculate the bendings.
So in this tutorial we will see how to
create new bin tables and locate the
already existed
solid works tables and if needed to
modify
and how to apply it on cheap metal
parts.
So to insert sheet meter bin table. So
you go to
insert sheet meter and down there and
there you will find
table and there are two ways either to
use an existed file which we will see or
create a new table. A better way is to
create a new table based on the saved
tables
inside sword works directory.
So to find the cheat sheet met bin
tables in solid works go to the program
files the solid works directory swords
core sod works and
language
English
and sheet metal bin tables
and here you will see samples.
Here is a ptl file or text file that is
a sample can be edited. So you can
create a copy from that and it also
there are some
samples
that already
to be filled.
So it's recommended before filling this
making a copy. For example,
here you have a copy and then
fill the values if you have them. So you
can
fill the table over there.
And in solid works also there are some
bend tables which are really valid but
they are not allowed. That's why we will
just show you the bend tables and in the
next tutorial we will show you how to
use the gauge tables. So we'll through
this course we will be using
the those two method the key factor or
the gauge tables. And here you have
table one. It is in inches.
And
also there is the metric
with allowance. And if you see over
there it it is for the 90° bends.
We will go back to the file and try to
see how to implement the bend table. So
let's just edit the sketch over there
and make it 90°.
Okay.
and then go to the sheet meter
features
and
we saw in the previous tutorial that we
calculated the how we calculated the key
factor and now let's see the other
method B table. So once you pick the
bend table, it will ask you to browse
the place for your bend table which we
already saw before. So you can again go
to this to the same folder bend table
and if you click okay you remember in
that for in that folder there were just
empty tables that they are here sample
and here is the copy which we made. If
you click okay, you will get warning
because it is an empty
table. So it it couldn't calculate
anything. So let's again go to that
table
override
in table
and
browse
the fillet metric table
in allowance
and here is
the table which we already saw. Click in
there. Click okay.
And now you calculated the bend by the
bend table.
Welcome to tutorial number 162. In this
tutorial, we will talk about a popular
method for determining the the sheet
meter properties and we will see what is
gauge table and why and where to locate
them, use them and then show you some
samples
and also
show you how you can make your own gauge
table depending on your requirements.
First start a new part and I will make a
simple sheet metal beam on front plane
and give it
some dimensions.
Go to the sheet metal is this flange
and the length make it 200.
Click okay. I will assume this is steel
beam and the thickness was one mm as you
see. Now go to the sheet metal
properties
edit feature and as you remember here
are the values which we showed you how
to calculate and here is the K factor
but you may ask yourself that if you are
working with few types of sheet meters
then you are already know the bending
radius
and the thickness and the K factor and
already calculated the K factor
and ask yourself that these values
should have been saved somewhere and
used directly without the use to reenter
them. So this is the work of the gauge
table. If you look over there you will
notice there is use of G table.
So this is the method. For example, you
can edit your own gauge table and add
these values in there and every time you
start a sheet metal part, you just load
the gauge table and automatically will
be is a time-saving method and it is
very popular at industries.
Before checking the use of gable,
I would like to locate them on your
computer. So they are found on the solid
works folder. So if you go to computer
program files, solid works core and then
solid works language
and English.
Here you will find the gauge tables
already over the bend tables which we
talked about in the previous tutorial.
And if you open the gauge table folder,
you will see many examples.
So each gauge table depending on the
method you are following. So there are
gauge tables based on the bid allowance
which we showed you the formula.
You have bin deduction and then the K
factor and there are some sample tables
and we said that we concentrating on the
K factors
method. So here you have the K factor in
inches.
If you open that
and you will see
there are two thicknesses but these are
in inches and here you see in
millimeters
and here you can see the gauge table and
it looks
and this is how the gauge table looks
like. It is a bit different than the
bending table. And here is the
for which material it is steel. But it
is clear it is not the stainless steel
because of the value of the K factor and
the process is the air bending K factor
is on the K factor units and then the
material is steel. Table is divided by
gauges. Gauge number five is for
thickness one and the bin angles
as we notice over there and
for the angle 75 the K factor is 6 for
this type of steel and for thickness two
you have the bend radius over there
already and you have the bend angle.
So this is what make the gauge table
popular because here
it will pick automatically
depending on your printing radius
and thickness and the type of material
you are using it will directly calculate
the key factor for you.
So let's go back to solid works to the
part which we made and now let's check
use G table
select based on the key factor
and then
here is the steel air bending we saw it
on the table
and even you can you will see that
the thickness is one then it should be
the gauge number five. So here is gauge
number five is thickened and if you pick
gauge number four you will see the
thickness is 2 mm but in our case it is
1 mm
and the bend radius it calculated
to be one
mm.
You can change it or override the radius
for example
but I will keep it for 1 mm
for the gauge table. Here the bend
allowance is gauge table
and when you are done click okay.
So here is browing our table and
you get and if you edit the sheet meter
feature you will see all the values
are there.
So let's start let's make another
example. Start a new part. Okay.
Pick front plane
a shade middle
and we already know that we are working
with
steel.
And the thickness should be
2 mm
and the bend radius 2 mm.
So you just go directly to the
base flange
extrude to 100 and use G table. Select
the type of G table.
We said that gauge
four
contain the thickness of 2 mm and the
bend allowance and the bend allowance I
let it to the gau table to calculate it
and the bend radius here you just can
make it two and you don't need to
think about anything else because the
table will
dua for you.
We saw this is a small
gauge table and there is an example I
want to show you. So this is an example
for a gauge table for the Chad industry
and uh here is the reference link
and here you can see it's the units in
inches and it is for steel and aluminum
and here you can see the gauge number
and the thickness and so on. Modify it
to millimeter and I'll show you how
change it over there.
Click enter.
And here for the thickness
to change it it was
you just simply type equal
the value will show.
So this is the original value you just
click equal
and change this to mm multiply by
25.4
four
and you'll get the thickness in mm
as well. the angle, the radius, you can
change it in the same way
and so on the rest of the values here.
See the
So, let's see the nearest
gauge to our previous example. this one
here
with a thickness of
2 mm.
And here is the thickness
and the
bending radius
is almost 2 mm. So it is gauge 14.
So let's
save this and apply it to
example.
So edit the sheet met feature
here. Browse for the key factory
and select the table which is click
okay. And here is the copy of CH's
table. Click
yes.
And
it will
upload the values
of your material. And as you remember we
said the nearest gauge is
gauge 14. Find it over there.
14 gauge steel and the values already
loaded. As you remember, we have only
one bending radius. And click okay.
And here the values are calculated.
You can also make your own bin tables.
We can go back to the solid work
samples. Pick one. Make a copy.
And let's say that
is
stain
steel
and the values
we showed you that how you can calculate
it in tutorial 160
is
38.
Let's assume it is the same for
the rest of the bending angles.
You can
fill your gauges by yourself. So for
now, I'll just
deleting these
and also
these values and the rest you can
continue on. So you can look at which
material you are using and which are the
angles you are using and the pending
radiuses
and fill according to your requirements
the table.
Make a new part here.
The following dimensions
sheet met
100.
Use G table and this time browse for the
new sample that we made.
Select the gauge factor is a copy of
our table that we edited. And there is
gauge five
and available thickness is only 1 mm
because we deleted the rest. Whether
the bending radius is 1 mm and we
already calculated
the key factor of this
table or key factor.
Click.
Okay.
Welcome to tutorial number 163.
This tutorial will be a simple short
tutorial, but it will be important to
continue the sheet metal feature menu
and important for the next tutorial.
If you remember, if you go to the sheet
metal feature, edit feature
here at the end, you will see the auto
relief section.
We already talked about the gauge table
in the previous tutorial and the bend
parameters
and bend allowance. Now, let's talk
about the last section auto relief.
We will talk about the types of auto
relief. rectangular
tear or brown and understand the auto
relief ratio down there.
So start a new part and let's make a
very simple box.
Okay.
Go to the front plane
and make a
U shape.
Okay, let's
assume this is a steel sheet and go to
the sheet meter
and give it a length base flash length
100. And for the bending method, I will
use the gauge table the topic of the
previous tutorial. Also pick the same
table shown in the previous tutorial
charts and the
sheet metal parameters I will pick the
gauge number 20.
So here we have gauge number 20 and the
thickness
the bend radius all and the bend
allowance are calculated according to
the table and here you will see auto
relief. Just click okay for now because
auto relief in this case will not be
shown because
there is no tight
corners or
any need for them. For example, let's go
to the sheet metal
and
expand the auto relief. You will see the
three types. We said rectangular tier AB
if you pick
click okay you'll not notice anything
so you will see what is the use and
purpose for auto relief.
So in order to show the auto relief I
will make an edge flange
for this
box and
make it up
to vertex
up to vertex and
is vertex.
So now if you scroll down over there you
will see that
the bending over there might looks not
that perfect
and it can be even harder for the
machining and there's a risk for tearing
and it can be managed by the relief. So
the auto relief is from its name to give
a relief to the sheet meter wide
bending and processing. For example,
let's
decrease the offset of this edge plan.
Edit feature and here make it with an
offset.
Make it of 3 mm
and reverse it.
and click okay.
So in case of a steel this also this
type of bendic might be difficult for
such material. So the auto relief
purpose is to relieve the corner. So
let's now go to the so to make it clear
I will edit the edge flange
edit feature and edit flange sketch
and make it a bit shorter over there.
And on the other side,
give it some dimension.
Five
and
five there.
Click
finish.
And if you notice over there, you will
see this little cut near the bending. So
this is the auto relief. So in this
case, it will be easier
for bending. So the type chosen over
there. Go to the edit feature and it is
a brown. So it is from its name. It will
have a round
edge over there.
Make it normal too.
And here you see the round. If you pick
the
other type, the rectangular.
Click. Okay.
And here you will see the rectangular
type on both edges.
And the last one there
it is kind of tearing directly
through the sheet.
So I go back and pick the up round
and down there you will see
0 five. This is the ratio of the
auto relief related to the thickness of
the sheet meter. So 0.5 we will get
exactly if you remember the thickness is
almost one
is 91. So the
distance
over there will be almost half the
thickness.
measure. If you go to the measure tool,
select
this face and this face
you will see the normal distance is
49.
That will be the same distance if you
make it rectangular
and pick that edge and you'll get the
length 46
and for the tier it is a tier and it
will not have any gap. So I'll pick the
upper round.
Click okay.
And let's try to make different shape.
Let's make the offset.
Click. Okay.
You will see there is no any auto relief
because
there is already a gap over there and it
is process for bending
and let's now return it back to change
the offset direction.
Click okay.
Now let's try to make a full edge
edge flange
pick that edge
and
click
make an offset.
Click okay.
You'll notice that there is no any auto
relief because the bending is directly
near the edge.
You can
check over there that there's already
the overall is already checked.
So in this case there is another way to
deal with the corners which will be the
topic of the next tutorial when we talk
about the corners over there.
For now, let's again
repeat the process of the auto relief
ratio. This time, let's make it.
You notice the maximum is 1.9. This for
now make it one. Click okay.
Here you will get the same
the gap will have the same distance as
the thickness of this sheet.
If you select the the radius
and the radius is 049 that mean the
distance or diameter
is equal to the thickness.
Let's again change it to the maximum
0.15. it. You'll see it will be almost
the gap distance
is almost twice
the thickness of the material. Okay.
Welcome to tutorial number 164. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
section over the the corners
and how we can deal with the sheet metal
corners and add a corner relief,
break corner and close the corners and
at the end
we will see how we can w the closing.
Now I will make a very simple uh sheet
metal box to show you briefly what is
the corners.
Start from the
front plane
and make a a U shape and define with
dimensions.
We will make a box similar
to what we did in the previous tutorial.
Cheat me
base flange
100.
And I will add another edge flange on
the corner
on the edge over here
up to vertex.
Okay, this is the
edge flange. So we can treat this corner
over there. Let's just check the
what we chose here. We have material
outside
and
90°
and the bending radius.9
and the thickness
is
so let's make the thickness one
mm
and the following
option
So go to the corner and we will pick the
corner relief over there. Click on the
corner relief. Collect the corners and
you will see how to
you'll notice that solid works selected
two corners
on this edge and in that edge. We
remember in the previous tutorial that
we couldn't add a relief. For that we
needed to edit the sketch. But with the
corner relief we can add a relief
in this way. Here you can see the two
corners selected corners and you need to
set the type of the relief. Here you
have a rectangular circular
and tear
up round and constant width. So let's
pick the
up round
and
select the second one.
It will be
over there. And as well select upper
round.
And you'll notice over there there is no
error.
And here is the slot length.
and slope width. So, let's make it 0.25.
And
this one, make it two.
And let's notice over there.
Or you can change
the shape.
For example, if we select a tear,
it will be just
a small tear over there. And if you pick
a circular, you will see a circle
shape in there. And here are the
circle
widths or slot width. You can make it 2
mm. And you will see
the shape over there. And even you can
make it reach to the thickness which we
talked about previous tutorial or
tangent to there.
Click okay.
And here you'll notice that we could
treat it this corner
which we
couldn't do it with the auto relief. So
this is a corner. You can use the corner
relief instead. This is the corner
relief is
there. Let's flatten and see.
The differences this is the tear type
and this is the circular.
So it is up on the requirements and
which is easier to bend. You can pick
the type.
And we will talk about the next type of
corners with this example box which we
made in one of the previous tutorial. So
let's try to finish this box
with the corner tools.
So we would like to
close
the gaps over there. So this is
let's say a liquid container
and we would like to close
the
gaps over there
and try to add
a corner relief to make it a bit easier
for bending and see how we can with the
corner. So first of all let's try to
change the corner relief over there. Go
to corner corner relief and collect all
corners and we will see if solars could
select them and you will see they
collected
four corners over there. And I would
like to change this type
of off
to be there.
And now you can see all the corners type
are there. You can also select a corner
individually. For example, corner three.
If you click on corner three and make it
circular,
so you will get a circular relief as you
notice over there.
But let's make them all here and
and you'll notice it is a bit easier for
bending. Just I click X over there
because I would like to show another
way. For example, if you couldn't apply
the corner relief for some reason, a
complicated corner, for example, you can
do it on the flatten
mode. If you flatten this
box,
make it normal too. And then
if you expand the corners menu over
there, you will see corner trim. This is
the only option can work on the trim.
And then just make sure that
you are not selecting any face because
it will
break all the
the corners of the products. Just clear
or delete face and select
that edge.
And you'll notice
it is a fillet, but we would like or you
can make it a chamer, but we would like
to make it a circular relief.
And here is the edge.
And if you notice you get circular curve
make it to mm.
You can
pick the
other edge. Click okay.
And here you make a manual
corner trim. And if you exit, you will
not see that trim because it will be
just shown when on the flat end. So I'm
going to delete this corner
which we make and apply
the corner relief.
Collect all the corners
and
I will pick the tear for all of them.
Here
you notice
as well over there. Click okay. As you
notice we made kind of a small gap and
this will make it easier for bending and
minimize the risk of tearing the sheet.
And then we can
deal with it at the end by welding
this corner.
So now the next step we would like to
close the
edges over there. We can do that on the
closed corner.
And here are the faces to extend and
faces to match. For example, let's
extend this face.
And
you will see it select all the faces.
Make sure that we can uncheck delete the
unnecessary
faces.
and faces to match. It automatically
knows it is the face over there. And you
can change the type of closing.
In this case, it's not shown. You may
minimize, decrease the or
reverse the buildings.
So, as you notice now, we closed that
edge.
So, as you notice now, we have a better
shape for this box.
And we can repeat the same process on
the
next
corners.
And here for the closed corner if you
edit you can control the
the gap between the edges. For example
the gap is 09.
If you try to make it 01,
it is a bit wider. And if you make it 01
and it is
almost closed. So this is how it looks
like when we change the gap distance. It
closed more.
And
the first case it was
like this. There's a small gap. So it
depends how you would want it. So
I will make the rest of the edges
similar
to this one. Almost closed.
And now let's see how to use the next
type of corners the welded corner. As we
said this box will be box for liquids.
This edge is not convenience
for a liquid box
and we used to close this edge partially
but is not closed completely because it
is in case of sheet metal it is a bended
edges is the job of the next type of
corner welded corner. So now you can
weld that edge and then you will close
the the corn the edge corner here
completely.
So it will be valid for liquid. So to w
that edge first select the edge where
you want to
weld it and you will notice very easily
you created a w over there from the
bottom corner to the
upper edge. And here you can if you
check this you can add a fillet to make
it
looks a bit better. So you can add a
fillet and we can make it for example
one mm
didn't work. So you can make it. So here
you will see
this corded material over there.
Start from here the whole way to the
edge. Close this here. And
and here you can see the welding
material. And this
edge corner over there is completely
closed. And it is valid for adding this
side. You can see this is the
with the material.
You can try to make cross-section and
see it from inside.
So you can see there is no gap
and compare it to the other side.
Over there
you will see there's an
opening. There's a gap, a small gap over
there.
So, we can repeat the same process
to the rest of the corners. And if you
notice over there and expand, you will
see only the welded corner option. And
if you suppress
the welded corner, then you will see
that the rest of options
are working. So the wed corner is one of
the last steps in finishing your
products beside the trimmed corners. So
let's add let's unsuppress
this one
and continue to work the rest of the
edges.
So the remaining option now is the brick
corner.
So let's see how to use it. We flatten
the
the sheet metal which is going to go to
industry. We can modify it further and
try to modify these
sharp edges. Go to the corner. You will
see corner trim and it will
automatically trim offate the corners.
So we can make it uh
you can select one by one because we
selected the face you'll see that all
the corner flip
and just select
edges where you want to add a trim or
a fillet. So this is make it two or one
2 mm.
Even you have another way to do it with
the break corner option. Click the brick
corner and select
this edge. You notice that you broke
that corner.
You can make it fillet
or a break is fillet. You can make it a
break of
of file.
Here
is the box which we started in this
course
and we want it to be for for holding
liquids is almost complete.
We did from all edges and closed and it
can hold liquid
without any problem.
And at the end of this tutorial, I would
show you another example about using the
corners. Here we have this product made
in another channel.
And if you remember this blade made with
sheet metal.
This is a sheet metal part
and made simply by a base flange. And
here
if we hide this,
you will see this sheet metal part has a
broken corners over there to make it
easier to slide
over the plastic barriers over there.
So we can open
this part and
here is the
broken corner
edit one edge
and we can even change it to f 1 And
there.
So it depends which one
you need and which one can be easier.
Welcome to tutorial number 165. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
section or the next approach in forming
the sheet metals. The forming tool. As
we remember, we have the first approach
for making sheet metals. the direct
which create
simple sheets and then it might be not
enough to create more complicated
shapes. So there is the forming tool
next. So it take the benefits of other
features for the sheet metal. So you can
use for example the extrude revolve and
to to make usual shapes and then
make them to sheet metal. In this
tutorial, we will talk about some ready
forming tools in solid works, how to
locate and use them.
And then we'll show you how to make your
custom forming tool and make an example
a ventilation fan vent. And then we will
look quickly to another real example
where the forming tools were used.
So first let's start a new part on the
top plane. Let's make a very simple
Let's make a very simple plate. Go to
define it with dimensions.
Go to sheet meter
and we have the values over there. Click
okay.
So here is a very simple plate and to
find the formal tools they are in the
design library. If you go to the design
library
and
expand it, notice there forming tools.
So these are forming tools which are
ready to be used.
You can
click on them and find the types over
there. We have no bars,
lenses, flange and so on. For example,
we can take the circular
grip
and here you can just directly place it
on that plate and you will form your
plate according to that forming tool or
you can flip the tool.
And here the configuration we don't have
any other choice than default. We will
see how to make another configurations
in the example. Next and in the link you
can link into the form tool and we will
see how to use them. Then we are done
click okay.
So here is the shape of the forming
tool. So this shape is not easy to be
done by the basic
sheet metal commands over there.
Try another case. Click on that face.
Make a sketch normal to just make some
random points. Let's make one point
here.
So on
it said
go to the again to the former tool
and let's pick run flange in this case
let's place it here. So the face is
already is pick it directly
and you can place it where you want. But
to be sure about the place you want to
put it, you can add dimension. You can
open the next menu.
Make it normal to smart dimensions and
can easily add some dimensions to the
place of that
round.
[Music]
Okay. And can make a dimension right
there.
Let's make this 70.
Also, you can place directly on the
point which we made. Click. Okay.
Now, let's see how to use the sketch
which we made here with points
to help positioning the forming tools.
Go to the design library. Run flange.
Take and
place it over there position
and you can simply
pick the point as you notice and place
it directly.
And here we can add
relation
to that point.
So we have the round flange on the
places where we want.
Also you can use the linear and circular
pattern to
to pattern the forming tool. For
example, for the
feature to
as you notice you could
also you can
linear pattern
direction
and for the feature let's pick
for sake pick this single one
You can change the number for
320.
Okay.
So now let's start making our example.
the ventilation grill and use some
forming tools.
Start a new part.
Go to the top plane
and make
simple plane.
Make the edges
equal and the dimension
250.
Go to the base flange with a thickness
of 1 mm 38K factor. Click okay.
Let's make the edges with the miter
flange. Go to miter flange as we learned
how to use it. Pick that edge normal to
and draw
edge
10.
[Music]
Exit the sketch
and select the rest of the edges.
When you are done, click okay.
So now let's see what we can find in the
forming tool library to create the
vents. Go to the forming tools and let's
find
movers.
Let's pick this type
and
flip the direction.
And you can change the angle to 90°
and click okay. And then we can
linear pattern
the SL.
Go to linear pattern
direction one
features
reverse. First.
This is the initial shape
of the fan bend. But
actually this is not how I would like to
see. This is just a quick sample how to
use the bloovers. So this is a popular
type of grills. And in the description
below I have a a link for animation to
show you how this lub is made. This is
first and second. And I would like to
change the style of this grill by using
the forming tools.
I would like to have the louvers longer
and create just one press die to create
the whole louvers at once. So make it
longer. That will increase the passing
air volume. And making all in one press
will also save production time.
So, delete the louvers and the
see how to create a custom forming tool.
Start a new part.
Go to the top plane and make the press
die.
Give it a dimension. You can make it 150
or a bit smaller.
So it is matching our
grill.
Extrude it.
Okay.
And let's make the lower man. Click on
this.
Go to the
right plan
normal to
and draw
and draw a quarter of a circle.
Give it radius of 10.
Make this
here. Make it horizontal. And dimension
from here to here 20.
Close.
and extruded mid plane
100.
Click okay. And here you will make a
circular revolve
sketch.
Invert entity and
feature revolve.
Make it 90°.
Mirror this
white plane.
Okay.
Add a fillet of
2.5 mm to the
edge over there. Now
linear pattern
this loop direction it's over there
reverse
number is
seven
feature def
[Music]
click okay
can make
19 instead.
So this is the shape of the D which is
going to press the plate, the sheet
plate and produce all these at once.
After making the dye, you need to
convert it into
a forming tool. Go to the sheet metal
forming tool and the stopping face. It
is clear to be this face
and faces to remove. We want this
ventilations
vents.
When you are done, click okay. So you'll
notice the the colors has changed.
You need to save it in the forming tool
folder. Pick a form tool
and find a place to
you have forming tool
movers and you can call it
custom
mover.
Save.
And let's go back to the grill,
the main grill,
and press it for other ones. Go to the
forming tool. You will find the custom
blue bar where we save.
So it will be the face of pressing will
be this face.
Pick it and drop it on that face. normal
to adjust position the
like this and this line coincident or
midpoint
and here you have lower center. We are
done. Click okay.
And here you have
the grill ready.
All done
in just one press.
So now let's talk about other options in
the forming tool. If you edit the
forming tool over there, you'll see we
said about the configuration. We don't
have any configurations. Also the link
over there is not checked.
So now let's see first how the link can
be. So let's undo this
process. Click delete.
Show the
main sketch.
Click this first. Go to the forming tool
and drop it over there. Normal to
and pick the
good position normal to
this point.
This point
this point this point. Make it
coincident.
Okay. And on the type over there,
click on link link to form tool.
Click okay.
So that mean
this these lover are linked to the main
die. So any change you make here, it
will be changed as well on the
grill. So let's edit the length of
make it 75.
Click okay.
And here you don't see any changes. to
see the changes. Go to edit feature
and
return back.
You will see the sketch is updated.
So let's add a configuration. Go to
configuration. add configuration
and call it second
for example and
return to the model edit sketch
and here we can make it for example 75
return to the part
edit feature
You'll notice that you have
second and first.
So you can make many configuration
dependings on the size
of the plate and simply change the
length by configuration.
And one last thing I would like to show
you about using deforming tools. This
kitchen sink example. It is a real
example in industry.
So this is how the kitchen sink is made
by pressing a piece of sheet metal with
a die press.
Here for example we have made four
dies to create all these pendings. The
first form to create the the first
pending over there in this face
and the second one to create another. If
we
move over.
So this is a row
sheet of metal. Then the first dye is
pressing to create this.
And the second press will create
this shape.
The third form
will make this
we'll make
this shape and the last one
to make this lower. So it was applied on
this face.
Welcome to new tutorial in the series of
teaching solid works from the beginning.
This is tutorial number 166 and we will
continue talking about the sheet metal
tools. In this tutorial, we will talk
about the gaset the next option after
the forming tools and we will talk about
the gaset options, how to use it,
position it and look at the shape
profile
dimensions and at the end we will look
at some examples.
So start a new part over there and let's
make a simple
beam by sheet metal.
Let's give it some dimensions
and go to sheet metal base flange
extrude it to 30.
Let's make it a bit a little bit wider
than 50 mm.
So and
the
bend radius 1 mm the thickness 1 mm and
K factor 38. So these are the values we
are using almost in all our tutorials.
So now let's have a look at the gaset
tool. If you look over there, you will
see the gaset icon and also you will
notice that it is a part in the forming
tool section.
So actually the gaset is a forming tool
but it has the gaset shape. So because
it is a standard shape and it used to
give to make the sheet metal stronger
and increase the stiffness of the sheet
metals
and you can for example when you use it
you'll notice it is a forming tool which
you can make by yourself.
So to start the gaset, click on it and
here you will see the options. You'll
have the position
and offset and profile. So let's talk
about the position. From the icon over
there, you need to select two faces. So
let's select this face and this face.
You will see the gasset.
Just in two clicks you get your gaset
made. And if you notice over there they
are the reference edge point. And we
will make another case where we can make
our edge and point. But if you click on
the edge, you will see the reference
edge is over there and the point is on
the other side
with pink color.
And the next option is the offset. If
you look over there, you have distance
of 20 mm. This is the distance from this
point to the cassette. And if you
uncheck the offset, you will have no
offset. And the
distance over there, the offset distance
gray out. So here you have the
the gas without any
offset. If you click okay, so you see an
error because the edges they are not
complete. So let's click on offset. And
if you remember
the width of this is 50. So you can make
it 25.
You will get the gaset exactly in the
middle. So click okay. Or before
clicking okay there's the profile. You
can decide the shape of this cassette
from the profile over there. Let's check
the first option the depth. So if you
look on the picture over there, you will
notice where is D which is here. So it
is the thickness that is written. Let's
make it 30.
Click okay.
As you notice the there is a drop. Let's
make it without any drop because I used
it before
and without any
option over there.
So this is the shape of the gaset which
you will see without any without adding
any fillet or any draft.
So if you click on the gaset feature
over there you will notice
the dimensions which we added 25 it is
from this edge to the middle of that
casset.
The 30 is the the depth and 0.5
is the thickness and
we'll show you later.
We'll talk about it as well later. You
can make it smaller and can make it
click. Okay.
And if you change
so that is the thickness order.
So let's continue talking about the next
options.
The profile dimensions you have D1 D2
you can imagine it like a chamfer. For
example, you can decide by the length of
edges over there. One here and one
there. Because you see D1 and D2 can
make this 20 and the second
or
make this one 30
and this one 10. And also you can
control with the with the angle with the
angle over there. You can make it 45
and the length 30 or you can make it 30.
So you understand
the meanings of this. And if you click
over there flat cassette you will have
just
without any fillet. If you click okay
you will get this
casset. So let's back again and click
on the
related cid. And now here are the other
options. If you would like to make it
wider for example you can make it 10.
And the ending thickness should be
less than the ended width. For example,
we have 10.
So here it should be
four less than the half. Click okay.
And it
said work it. Let's edit again. If you
make it
five
it will fail. So we make it 4.9
and it will get
a very
thick cusset.
So let's make it again
1 mm similar to the thickness the sheet
meter thickness. So here you can add
fillet from inside and outside. So if
you make one m let's make it 2 mm.
Click okay.
You will get this inner fillet. And we
can also add a fillet on the outside.
Let's
add a flip
here for two or three
mm and click okay
and you will get the
fillet over there inside and outside.
So this is one case
of using the gaset. So now this LBM gets
supported by this cassid.
So let's suppress this gaset and show
you how to use the line. Make a line on
that edge.
So if you would like to have a gaset
with an angle,
let's make a line example
and give it some dimension
and make it
for construction.
this point.
This point.
So, we have a line over there. And let's
make also a point somewhere
over here. Let's make
exit. So, go to the cassette.
Select this face and this face. The edge
we will start to pick this line.
You will notice the gaset is
perpendicular to that line.
You can edit
the values.
You can make it 45
and here can make 40.
Not done. Click okay. and you will get
the fillet inside and outside from the
previous
gaset. So now let's again edit
and pick
the point.
If you pick this point,
it will be as well a reference
to that point.
So the distance will be 25
from this point to the middle of that
and when you are done click okay.
So this is another case for using the
gaset.
So now let's start using the cassette in
our previous example which we did in
tutorial number
158. As you remember, we made this
shelf holder
and we added this step to fix it on the
wall.
But you can notice as well
that is not enough.
Go to the main sketch. Edit normal to
select all these and delete
rebuild
and
suppress
the building.
So now let's add a gaset instead of that
tab.
Click on
gaset.
Pick this face and this face.
And let's now add a draft. And the
thickness will be 1 mm. uh to mix the
middle.
And here we can add a draft
and the depth
of make it 50.
You can increase the thickness
a little bit. So, and here for the
distance, we know
the distance is 38.38
divided by 2. So, this will be the
middle of
this holder.
And we have a 2 mm and 2 mm over there.
And click okay. You will get that
cassette on this bending
and the share folder is stronger. and
can hold heavier loads.
In the end of this tutorial, I would
like to say if you want to make you a
custom cassette for example like this
shelf holder cassette with a special
shape
and it is as we said in the beginning
the gaset is a forming tool. So you can
format. So here we have an example for
that custom cassette and it will be an
example in another channel
and the link will be below.
Welcome to tutorial number 167. In this
tutorial, we are going to continue
talking about the sheet metal features.
And now we will talk about the next
section after the gaset the cuts section
which include extruded cut, simple old
and vin. And we'll see the differences
in the extruded cut for the sheet metal
and the simple hole. And then we will
have a look at some design library
events kind of ready cuts. And then the
most important part in this tutorial,
the vent options. We will have a look at
the fin feature options which include
the geometry properties, flow area,
ribs, sparse, fill in boundary and we
will
cover these options in one example.
So start a new part
and make a custom theme. Pick the front
plane
line
and we will make this shape. This is
defined with some dimensions.
And here we'll have an angle
120.
near
midpoint.
So we have this side perpendicular to
the biz edge and here we have an angle
extruded with a sheet meter base.
Make a thickness of one mainly.
The bend radius key factor 38.
Click okay.
Let's make it
a little bit wider.
So now let's
try to make a cut in that edge.
So select this face, start the sketch
normal tool, and let's make
a rectangle
over here
and define it.
So we have a rectangle and
we are going to make an extrude cut
through this sheet metal. Go to sheet
met extrude cut and
for now nothing is new. We already know
about the extrude cut and you have the
arrow over here
and you have a second direction
and so on.
Click okay.
Return back to the
cut extrude edit feature. And now we
would like to
see the difference between the normal
extrude cut and see what is additional
when we are cutting through a sheet
metal here. If you notice you will have
length to thickness. So if you click on
that the cut will be only
through that. So if we just uncheck
direction two, the depth of the cut will
be the same as the thickness of the
sheet metal.
So this is one thing
and
another option. Let's now click through
all
and cut through the second side and
click through all and normal cut is
unchecked. Click okay.
You will notice that the cut over here
is not
perpendicular to the surface over here.
And it is not as the most of the cut
because if you flatten
the part, you will see the cut here with
an angle.
And in reality mostly the punch gives
you
straight cut similar to the cut in the
first edge. So we can fix this if you
edit
here and check normal cut.
So it will give you
a straight cut
through the edge. Open perpendicular to
the sheet. If you flatten
and look again.
So this cut here is more logical.
Unflatten. So we saw the
two differences
and extrude cut.
So now let's move to the next is simple
hole. So simple hole because as we know
in sheet metal you'll have only a hole.
There will be no special holes for
screws or so on. So you can create
simple hole
directly
on the sheet metal. And here you can
make the diameter change the diameter
and the depth of the cut. And here
you can check the face if you would like
to have it perpendicular to that face.
So just clear selection. And you have
the draft option as well.
Now I will talk about the design library
or cuts. So to locate them
go to the
design library
features
and here you will see sheet meter and
over there you will see many cut shapes.
For example, we can pick this one and
drag it drop it directly
on
on the surface.
And once you drop that on surface, you
will get the cut directly. And to the
left here, you have the ability to edit
sketch.
If you go to the sketch over there,
let's make it normal too.
So smart dimension, we can add dimension
over there. We can make it 10.
And from this side, this side
10.
And also you can change
on the dimensions of this shape.
You can make it one
five
and this will make it four.
When you're done, click finish and
you'll get
this shape
again. Let's pick another
sheet meter feature.
This time we can try this shape and
place it over there.
And if you want to change the size,
override the main dimensions,
make it normal too.
This one we can make it two.
And this one make it one
and be
can make 10.
So you have the chance to override the
dimensional values
and you can edit the sketch as well.
Add dimensions
40.
We are done. Click finish.
Now I will talk about the next feature
and the most important feature in this
tutorial the event
feature over there and it is an
interesting feature very nice to use and
time saving and I will show you how to
use it with an example. We will make a
ventilation grill. Start a new part.
This time we will make a circular
ventilation grill. Go to the top plane.
Draw a circle
and give it dimension of
150 mm sheet meter.
We have the values from the previous
part. Click okay. And here you have this
sheet metal disc. So we will draw a
sketch. If you pick the print feature,
you will read a message over there that
you need a 2D sketch.
So let's make the sketch.
Select that face. Start the sketch
normal too.
We will make the boundary
circle of that drill.
And let's give it
125.
And we will make
lines the lines of the g or the ribs.
On this line you can
linear
pattern.
Select
pattern it on
direction.
Here we have
six pattern.
Look. Okay. and
repeat the same process
in the other side.
Click okay.
And to
support the ribs, we can make one rib in
the center or it called spar.
Let's make a line
here
and another line
for testing
over here.
And we can add extra support ribs in the
center over there. We can make
another
inside circle.
Make a third
sketch. Trim.
Okay.
And now go to the sheet meter vent
and you will see the vent will already
select your sketch. So the boundary as
we said the outside boundary of the grid
is the circle
and the feature will directly create
this hole and the face
is the two face over there and
we will look later on the flip on the
draft
the area is cuted 100%. So the flow is
100%. Now we can decrease
that when we are making
when we will make the ribs. The rips you
can make them directly by selecting the
line.
So you'll notice how easy
to work
with the bend feature.
And here you have only one
option is activated
is the width of the rib. The reason on
the sheet metal
because it is a plate of sheet metal and
you don't have a solid feature. We will
see later in another example how to use
the rest of the option. But for now you
have 5 mm and you can change it to
three.
And you'll notice now we have 71%
flu area.
And
if you think drips need some support,
you can add sparse
the line in the middle.
And as well, we can increase the width
five mm 50 or five.
I make it
10.
And then we can
the fill in boundary
adding some extra
support. Now this select as far delete
um
fill in boundary
be this
circle.
And for the spars, we added this line as
a test. If you want to add more support
the to the ribs,
you can select
this line,
but for now I will remove it.
So here you have the basic shape of the
grill. And now to make it looks better,
we can add fillets
to the edges. Go to the fillet and
can add 2 mm fillet. And you notice
the fillet
is applied
to the grill.
Now it looks okay.
When you are done,
click okay.
Two more holes to fix this
Here
is another grill made by the vent
feature. So this is a plastic grill and
I will go over the steps how I made
this. Since it is a plastic
grill, it is outside the scope of this
series. But if you would like to see how
it's made in details, I will put the
link in the description below.
If you go again to the vent feature
here,
the vent can be used for cheat meter and
for plastic ventilation units. So, this
one is made by plastic and
we'll show you how it's made. First,
we extruded this plastic
plate. And here is the main sketch.
And then we use the ventilation
feature
to make the grid. And here I wanted to
show you what we said before
when we are working with plastic parts.
The rest of the options will be
activated.
So we have the depth here is activated.
And it was not the same in the sheet
metal. We saw that the depth is great
out. And here is the plastic part.
We added as well a draft so it be easier
for injection molding. Apply the draft
with one degree angle and a filate.5
mm.
The advantage of this plastic that we
have a high open area because we made
the ribs stronger by increasing the
depth of the rib and which we can see
over there. We have 20. And if you click
10,
you can notice
and you can change the way you would
like. And let's make back again 20.
And instead of making
the rip wider and decrease the flow
area, we can make it
we can increase the depth and that will
increase the strength
of the grid. So we have almost 77%
[Music]
area. And the same thing with sparse you
have the depth
value is activated which you can
increase it or decrease it.
So this is the main
point of this grill and then we made a
cut
to remove the extra materials.
So here is the grill looks
nice
and all is done in just few steps with
the bend feature.
Welcome to tutorial number 108. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
section in the sheet meter commands. The
unfold, fold, flatten
commands. We will see how to use the
unfold unfold commands and compare them
with the flatten and how to link these
two options with the flatten. Also,
we'll see the differences between the
unfold and flatten commands.
I have this box from one of the previous
tutorials. It already has all the bins.
Let's see how to first use the unfold
command.
Click on unfold. Here you will get a
fixed face and bends to unfolds. Let's
first
select the base face
and then here you have collect all pins.
Let's click on that it will collect all
the pins. If you hover over each one,
you'll see
which pen is selected.
And here is selected all the pins. And
when you are done,
click okay.
Then you will get
all the bins flatten or unfold.
Now it looks like similar to flatten.
And if you let's make it normal too,
you'll see the unfold mode. Let's undo
this and click flatten instead.
Click on flatten.
Make it normal too.
On the flatten mode you will get the
bendings line which are not shown in the
unfold mode. This is one difference.
Let's unflatten this.
And now let's unfold by selecting the
bins. Click unfold.
Let's select this face. So let's see
that we don't want to unfold all the
box. We just need to check one edge. So
I selected this fixed face and the pins
to unfold.
I will select this bend. Click okay.
Now you will get
that bend unfold.
So you can check if you have any cuts or
any things then
you can check it by the unfold. Let's
undo this
and see how to use the fold
command.
Let's first
unfold the whole box. Unfold.
Let's select this fix it face and
collect all the pins
and click okay.
So you'll get the box
flatten.
So we can try now to unfold edges.
So click fold
for example
we can select this face
and for the bend we can select
this bend so and check if it will work.
Click okay.
Now you got
this side fold.
Also you have the option. Let's undo
this.
Also you have the option to select all
the bends. So let's select this face and
collect all the bends. Click okay.
and you will fold all the bins.
So now you may ask yourself that you can
use the flatten instead of unfold. So
let's now talk about the main advantage
of the unfold
because if we work on the flatten mode
and make cuts, it will not appear when
we
unflatten the box. For example, let's
make a cut over there. Select
the slot and let's define it.
Okay. Now when we unflatten
you will not see the cut we made and you
will see that the cut is after the
flatten moon. So let's instead try to do
it with the unfold.
Select this fix it first and
let's just bend
this
bend this side. Click okay.
Now let's make a cut over there.
Make a sketch normal to
select the slope and let's make it
beside
And when you are done, you can fold
the box. Click. Okay.
As you notice the
cut appeared on the box. Also, you can
try to treat the corners as well. Also,
we can use the unfold command for
unfolding other shapes, not only boxes.
Let's start a new part
and we will make a pile. Pick the top
plane.
Make a circle.
Let's define it.
100 mm and
let's make a welding gap.
Pick center line.
Make this construction.
Go to
sheet meter. Um,
and extrude the pipe. Let's say 300.
The sheet meter thickness is.15.
Click okay.
So now we have this pipe
and let's see how we can unfold
this pipe. Go to unfold fixed face. If
you try to select this face, it will not
allow you. But if you pick that edge,
you are able to
pick that edge. The bend bends to
unfold. So the whole pipe is
a bend. Just click on it
and click okay.
You will get the file
flatten.
And you can undo or you can make
modification to that pipe and then fold
it again.
But let's try to fold it on the other
side. Go to fold.
Select this edge
and bend to fold the pipe. Click okay.
And you'll notice that we
fold it on the opposite side.
Also, there are other ways to fold
unfold. We will talk about them in the
next tutorials when we talk about insert
bends.
Welcome to tutorial number 169. In this
tutorial, we will talk about another
approach in creating sheet metal parts.
At this moment, we are familiar with
most of the sheet metal commands. And
now we will talk about the convert to
sheet metal. That will make it clear
which way will be for example easier.
For example, if we would like to make
such chip.
So we can do it with the base flange
approach and the rest of the commands
or there is another way shorter way
convert to sheet metal. So one of the
advantages of the convert to sheet metal
that you can implement the solid
features
for creating sheet metal parts. So we
will make this shape and see how we will
do it and then
have a look at the convert to sheet
metal options fixed
bend and rip edges and we will see
another example how to use rib sketches.
Also one another advantage of using
convert to sheet metal feature that you
can convert more complicated chips to
sheet metal
which can be easier to be done by the
sol feature.
So let's start a new part
and
pick top plane. Select
hexagonal
and define it
65 and extrude it
to 50 with 25
Draft angle. Click okay.
Now mirror
this part.
Mirror.
Select this face. Bodies.
Click. Okay.
So we made this shape
in two steps. And let's see how to
convert it into a sheet metal part. So
go to the convert to sheet meter and
here you will get the convert to sheet
meter option. Use gauge table. We
already talked about it. We'll keep it
to the default. And let's assume that we
will have a base flange. We will pick
the base face over there. The thickness
of the sheet metal we will keep it 5 mm.
and reverse the thickness. We will see
now when we will start selecting the bin
edges.
So let's assume that is the base flange
over there and the edges around are the
bin edges. So you can select the bit
edges directly over there and you will
notice the color
is the pink color.
and the purple color represent the rib
edges.
There are other options. Let's just
click okay for now
because we selected only these edges. So
the works converted only the down part
into
a sheet metal part. And you can flatten
this part.
So if you would like to do the same
process in D approach the base flange
you will need to create hexia diagonal
and then you will make an edge flange
then edit the sketch and it will be like
more steps to do this.
And if you would like to make the whole
body it will take longer time. So let's
go back to convert to
sheet metal option.
And here we have the rib sketches. We
will talk about it in the
second example.
And here are the corner defaults.
If you can
look over there.
So depending on the requirements you can
decide. I will keep it open. And the gap
you can make it one mm.
And also the overlapping gap.
And other leaf you can make it
rectangular. We talked about it before.
And here if you
click
reverse thickness you will get the
thickness inside. So I will check the
reverse thickness.
And if you look over there you have the
default
radius one mill.
You can
override the value for example you can
make it three
five so I will keep it five so we talk
it about
the bending radius before so
when you are done
or before that you are able also to
change the radius directly on
the shape. If you notice over there, you
have the radius for example.
We can make this radius to be 3 mm
or.5
mm.
And the gap as well,
you can change it.
Change the type of the gap and the gap
width.
can make it 2 mm.
I will keep it to the default.
Now let's continue selecting the rest of
the bendings.
If you go to the bin edges
and select
the bend over there
and this edge
And let's close upper edge.
So now when you are done click
okay.
So you notice that solid walls converted
this shape directly into a sheet metal
in few
clicks.
Now let's see how to use the rip
sketches. For that we'll make first a
simple part.
Start a new part
and pick the plane.
We'll make a simple cube.
not extruded
100 mm.
This time I will add a shell.
Let this add shell of 1 mm.
Okay.
Go to sheet meter.
And let's first make a sketch for the
rip. Select
this face
and make a center line
for there. So this sketch will be used
for the rib. Now go to sheet meta.
Convert to sheet meta. And as you
notice, we don't have the base. Select.
Let's say
let's select this face
and
the thickness five and the radius bend
radius
is 0.5.
And let's pick the pin edges.
You can see in the preview the shape of
the chime meter part.
Select this edge
and also select this edge.
So you'll see that we have
the opening there edges over there. But
we would like to modify it to have it
have the rib in the middle. So go to rib
sketches and pick this sketch.
You'll notice that we got the rib
on that side. So let's also
add another bin edge over there. So
we'll have the whole face closed. And
when you are done, click okay.
So you'll notice that we got the red in
the middle of that face.
You can flatten and have a look
at the part.
So let's back
to the main example and try to make
a rib over there. So, let's roll back
and start the sketch over here
normal
and make a line in the center.
Except
and
D forward and edit the convert
sheet metal hair. Drip sketches at
this sketch.
You will see the opening drip there.
Let's just clear your selection. And to
make it easier,
let's uncheck
this part. So we have now the top face
is open.
Select
drip sketch.
And now
the bending edges select
this blend
and this bend edge. So this is how I
would like to see this box. So when you
are done
click okay.
So and here you have the ribbit sketch
to make the opening in the middle of the
tip face. Let's
flatten.
And here is the flatten part.
And if you would like to make this sheet
metal part with the base flange and
basic commands, you can imagine how
longer time it will take.
Welcome to tutorial number 170. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
sheet metal feature, ribb. You can find
the ribb here before the last feature
insert bends. So in this tutorial we
will see how to use the RIP feature and
have a look at the RIP parameters
and see how the RIP works and the cases
you need to have in order for the RIP to
work.
And then we'll have a look at the RIP
options, drip directions, gap distance,
and then we'll see how to make sketched
rip.
So first let's start making a new part
almost similar to the one we made in the
previous tutorial
and see how we can rip the edges by the
rip feature instead of converting to
sheet meter. So let's define it and
give it a distance
extruded
50 with
outward draft angle. Click okay.
So now let's
try to trim the edges in order to
produce a similar
chip by sheet metals. So let's go to
sheet metal rib and here it will ask you
to select the edges.
Simply you can pick edges and you will
see the arrows in two directions.
So now we selected the edges to be
ripped but in this case it will not work
because you need to have a clear shape.
You should imagine the solid feature as
a box or a sheet metal part before
ripping it. So let's now click okay.
You'll see the
error. So close this and let's shell the
shape. Go to feature.
Go to shield and let's say that you want
to make this
shape by sheet metal plates of thickness
one mm. So let's make it 1 mm shell.
Click okay. And this is the initial
shape of the solid feature. Now
let's go to sheet metal rib. There will
be also another
case that
it may not work to select all the edges
at once. So you need select one by one.
Let's just first try to select all the
edges.
Click okay.
You will get again a geometry error. So
clear section.
And now let's just apply
to only two edges.
see the shape of the rib. Now we will
get two errors. So the rib will be equal
in both sides and the gap distance 0.1.
Click okay. And here you get the rib
over there. So this a solid the solid
feature how it would looks like if you
would like to produce it by a sheet
metal part.
So let's compare it with the previous
tutorial shape. Here is the sheet metal
part from the previous tutorial. And
it's made by the convert to sheet metal
feature. And here we have ribs
as you notice in that side.
And in this case all by the rib method
you have the ribs
in that chip. Let's continue adding more
ribs.
Let's this time add to this edge
this edge. And let's make it just in one
direction. Click on the arrow or you can
change the direction here.
So you will have a rip on that direction
and on that direction. Click okay. So
you'll notice how
the rip looks like.
You can now continue to the rest of the
edges
or let's
suppress these two edges and add to the
edges
and the gap distance let's make it.1
click okay. So this is the solid part.
If we would like to make it
B sheet metal plates.
Let's now
try to make a similar ribs to this one.
Here you have ribs
all the edges
and you have one
rib
over there. So let's try to make it.
Go to rib
and select this edge. Click okay.
Now it looks almost similar to the ribs
made by the to convert to sheet meter.
So let's go back to the previous
example.
If you go down there, you have sketch
trip over there. So let's see how we can
do it
by the feature.
Go to the part
start sketch over there.
Let's
draw back.
Make a sketch over there. And let's draw
a line
over there.
Exit the sketch.
Roll forward. You can edit the
sketch over there to add another edge.
This one.
Click okay. You will also get that rib
over there. So, let's edit and delete
that edge. Make it in a new word.
Select that line and make the gap 25.
Click okay.
So this is also one way to manipulate
with solid parts in order to get to
exact shape. As you know there can be a
lot of shapes tricky shapes and for now
we saw many approaches how to work with
them.
We from the beginning of this course we
had a look at the base flange feature
and then we looked at the forming tools.
Then we look at at the convert to sheet
metal. Now we see direct.
In the next tutorials we will see also
another approaches
how to sweep
uh sheet metal part. Also there is
another way to make more complicated
chips with sheet metals by lofted bends.
So at the end of this course you will
have an idea about these options and you
will be able to decide which approach is
easier and better to reach to the
requirements and also this course will
be a good reference to repeat it again
and again to have a look to the
features.
Welcome to tutorial number 171. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
command in the sheet metal menu, insert
bends and opposite to this command, the
no bends,
and see how to use them. Also, we will
compare it to the rip in the previous
example. Then we'll go and have a look
at the insert bins parameters. use the
no bends after that and see one of the
advantages of using insert bends by
making an example and unfolding it and
compared to the unfold command.
First let's talk about the example from
the previous tutorial
170 where we used the rib command. So,
as you notice, we made drips over there.
Maybe that is not the most perfect chip.
Then that will be the work of the next
command. Insert pens. Because the insert
pens will take the ribs one step
forward.
So let's start a new part and make a
similar example so it will be easier to
compare.
Pick top plan.
Select hexagonal
and
give it dimension.
extruded
50 with 25
draft outward angle. Click okay
and chill it with a thickness of one m.
Click okay. So now we have
a similar shape.
Go to sheet metal
insert bends.
And here we will ask you about a base
face. So you can imagine this is a base
flange or base.
Select it and you will get similar
options to the base flash options. You
will get a bend parameter. Let's make it
2 mm.
And here you have a thickness. We
already made a thickness.
And bend allowance.
We already talked about them. Auto
relief. We can make it rectangular.
we also talked about it and here is the
rib parameters.
So here you will make again ribs similar
to what we did
in the previous tutorial
and you will see and we will see the
difference
between drip and insert pins.
Select edges here. You can change the
direction. Make it two
directions
instead of one.
Here
we selected the edges to be ripped and
the gap distance let's make it this time
0.5.
Click okay.
Click okay again. And here you'll notice
you made
a modified rib than in the previous
tutorial. So we get the outer leaf. We
have the bend
radius also we have the gap.
So actually the insert bends in the
beginning is a red feature. If you look
at the tree over there, we have a ribb
and are there are two more steps after
the rib flatten bends and process bends.
So these processes made it the part to
be sheet metal part. Here you can also
change the relief type. You can find it
in the sheet metal
properties.
You can change it to
a brown
or we can make it
there.
So it depends on which type you need.
And if you notice on the sheet metal
menu, you have the no bend
commands is activated
and the insert bins is not activated for
now because we already have bins.
So before using the no bins, I would
like to talk more about the two options
over there
on the insert bins.
three. First, we have the rib. If you
edit the rib, we already talked about
this feature in the previous tutorial.
It is already included in the insert
bins. You have the edges
and you have the gap distance and the
directions.
And also you can add
a sketch more sketch to that. And now
let's roll forward to the next option.
This option will flatten the
part.
Then process bend. It will bend it
again.
So as you saw that we have the flattened
and bend again.
on the tree. But you can do the same
process
by clicking on no bends. If you click on
no bends, it will show you the part
without any bends or any
bend allowance. It will be just similar
to the rib the previous strip. And if
you uncheck the no bins,
you have the bins again over there.
And when you check the no bends, you
will see the insert bins is activated
again. It will allow you to insert more
bends if needed.
And also you can use the flatten option
for that part.
And you will get the part
flattened as you see. So this part maybe
is not that complicated
geometry but the rib and insert bins can
come handy for more complicated chips
which can be difficult to be done by the
base flange and tab.
We will make an example to see how we
can use the insert pins and see one
advantage of using the insert pins.
Start a new part
and let's make a pipe. Pick the front
plane.
Draw a center line and draw another
line.
over there.
Let's define it 200
50.
Go to feature revolve. Click yes.
Okay. So, use a thin feature. Make a
thickness of one and revolve it one
degree less to make a welding gap. Click
okay. So we have this simple pipe.
Now we can flatten this pipe with insert
bend. Put sheet metal. Insert bend.
Just select that edge. Click okay.
Flatten
you will see you are now flatten this
pipe. So the part here the part which we
made is made by a solid feature
by the revolve post and we could
use this solid feature
to convert it into a sheet metal with
insert pen.
If we roll over there, you will see the
unfold command is not activated. We used
the unfold feature in one of the
previous tutorial. You can go back to
that tutorial and try to compare it to
the insert pen. So you will notice here
that the unfold is not activated.
Start a new part on the top plane.
Normal tool. Let's make
another pipe
quickly.
We have a circle with an opening.
You see,
go to sheet meter
and here you have the base flash and the
sheet meter is not activated. Roll it
forward the cursor
pick
flash and select that edge.
Click okay.
So here we have a pipe made by P flange
sheet metal.
If you go to the unfold
and pick that edge and select the body.
Okay.
Now you have the pipe flatten.
to unflatten
or to fold the pipe. You can suppress
the fold
or the unfold command or you can add
another fold to it. Then just unsuppress
add a fold. The edge is selected already
over there and then to fold select this
part. Click okay.
So this is the fold unfold method
and the first pipe is made by the insert
bands. If you would like to flatten the
first pipe you can as we said there you
can as we say suppress over there
and you will get the first pipe flatten.
Click on suppress.
So there are two approaches but we said
the insert bend
took the advantage of using solid
feature. So for example the first file
can be a more complicated shape that is
not easy to make it by a base flange
command. And then you can add the insert
bend to it and bend it.
Welcome to tutorial number 172. In
tutorial, we will talk about another
command for creating sheet metal parts.
In this tutorial, we will talk about the
lifted bin command which we see over
there. We will have a look at the cases
where the lifted bend can work and when
it can't work. And then we'll have a
look at the main two types of the lifted
bend.
Bend. Lofted bend and form lofted bend
and see the types under the bend lofted
bend which are ch tolerance number of
bends segment length segment angle and
see the difference between them
and see which type
will fit your requirement.
The sheet metal lofted band is almost
similar to the solid features lofted
post and lofted cut with some major
differences.
And if you hover over the lofted bend,
you will see that the lifted bin and
sheet metal works between only two
sketches.
So let's start making two sketches.
Let's make on the top plane a circuit
and give it a dimension of
and make another sketch on another
plane. Let's make a plane
parallel to
top plane with a distance of 200.
Click okay
and draw
a center rectangle.
Give it dimension
175.
connect this tangent to the circuit.
So here we have two profiles
or two sketches. Let's hide
this plane.
So in the original lofted ben
or lofted boss these two profiles will
work also in the surfaces loft as well
the loft between two circle two sketches
will work but in the sheet meter as we
knew before that we should have uh a gap
mostly for bending gap or welding gap.
So let's first try to see we have click
on the look bend you have bent and
format but first let's try to select
this sketch you will notice that you are
not able to select any of the sketches.
So exit from the lifted band and let's
make opening gaps in both sketches. Edit
that sketch normal to
and let's make
center line
and opening gap.
Make this rectangle for construction
and give it
2.5
and then trim
the circle over there.
fixed point over there. Now it's fully
defined except
and the same thing
on the second sketch.
Make you can convert entity or
again create a similar
rectangle
and trim
the entity.
Click okay.
So now the sheet metal lifted bin
supposed to work but you will notice
later that it will not work probably for
one reason. We will talk about it.
Select lifted ben.
Now select that sketch. You notice that
you are able to select that sketch and
select the second sketch.
You see it working it. But if you hover
or zoom in, you will see there's a gap
over there and the bend is not fully
covering that gap. If you click okay
to see it clearly,
you'll see there's a gap over there.
So the reason for that that you need to
have bending radius
instead of a sharp angle 90° angle. So
delete that lifted bend.
Go to sketch tool edit
normal to add bending radius in form of
fillets. So let's make it 10 mm.
Click okay
and exit from the sketch.
And let's try now to
use the lofted bend.
Select first sketch and the second
sketch. And you notice there that you
got
the loed bin fully working.
Here in the first options you have bend
and form. Let's first click on the form.
You'll get just a very simple loft
without any short lines or angles. And
we will have another example about it
later in this tutorial.
And let's discuss the first option belt.
And if you roll down the profiles which
we already selected sketch one and
sketch two. And here are the facing
options.
So depending on the manufacturing method
which is going to be used to produce
this
cone or dot
here are the options or dependings on
the shape wanted.
So the easiest way to know the
difference between these four types is
at looking at the figure of it over
there. So the code tolerance is the
distance between the max distance
between the linear segment and the arc
to show this
segment and the arc. Let's exit from
this command and flatten.
And if you notice over there, there is
straight lines or segments instead of
arcs.
It is clear over there. And let's
unflatten and go back to lifted bend
edit. Go to the code tolerance
and we can
decrease or increase the value to five.
So it will be clear to see the segment
and the cord arc over there. So the
maximum distance it is five mm between
the arc over there and the sigma
and the second one is according to the
number of bins.
So it is
almost clear. So depending on the number
of pins you have here four
corners
and you can decide the number of bin in
each corner. For example, now we have
two bins which represent this one over
there and one over there. If you
increase,
you can notice
that increase. Also, you can change
the type of bends in each corner by
selecting the dot over there. So, if you
click on the dot and let's select number
of bends and let's type
it,
you will see that the number of bends
are h over there and it's applied on
that corner. And let's go to the next
corner and try to apply a different
type.
And this time let's select the segment
length which we showed you before.
Click on segment length
and it is here five mm.
Let's click okay. And
the segment
you can
see if we flatten
the part. Let's click. Okay. And
flatten.
And here
you'll notice the maximum distance is
five. And here it's shown four.
7 and adding the bending radiuses. So it
will be almost five. So the five
representing the maximum value
uh except
and let's go to the angle between
the bending lines.
Edit the lifted bend again
and move to the next corner.
And let's this time select the segment
angle. So this is
the angle between the sigas. Here it is
30. Then let's make it 40.
And you see the angle is 40. And
let's make it less 10.
And this clear the angle between
the bending lines increasing and
decreasing
without changing the angle value.
So now this is prefabs
and with practice it will be easy to
differentiate between them
and the rest of the options. We already
talked about the thickness
of the sheet meter and the bend radius.
All done. Click.
Okay.
Now we will have another example
where we can use the lifted band with
the form type.
We have the famous example by
by Alex and it is found on the internet.
And here he has the instructions how to
form this part.
And as you notice on the second part,
use the lifted bend. And if you notice
this shape there is no angle or bending
segments.
So the you the type used to create this
shape is deformed
bend
but also it will be a repetition for the
unfold the cup unfold back.
Here the dimensions are in inches.
So we will assume that they are in
millimeters multiplying by 10. So for
inches over there we will assume it
40 mm and.1
in we'll assume it to be 1 mm
and so on for the rest of the
dimensions. Here the circle is 2 20 mm
let's say and 30 by 15 ellipse.
So start a new part
and make a second reference plane 40 mm
far from the front plane as you see over
there.
So features
reference plane
and reverse
offset and make it 40 mm. Click okay.
On the front plan, we'll have a circle
with a gap.
Let's make a center line to
make easier
to deal with it. So, let's check the
dimension of first
sketch.
you will have 20 mm diameter and the gap
is 1 mm.
So
the radius should be 10
mm and the overall diameter is 20 mm and
the gap over there 1
mm. And let's make them
symmetric
about the center line.
So here we have the first sketch is
fully defined. Exit and
go to the
second plane and insert
sketch
normal tool.
And here
we will need an ellipse 30 mm by 15 mm.
Here you can see partial ellipse with
the cab.
So the distance From
this point to this point
is 30
and
from this point to this point
is 15.
Let's make this
presenter
and the gap
1 mm. And let's make them
cons symmetric around
center line.
convert into the um
for construction
symmetry.
So now we have the ellipse fully
defined.
And the second option
or instruction is to use the lifted
bend. Go to lifted bend cheap meter
lifted bend and this time we will pick
the format type
this sketch
and this sketch and the thickness let's
make it
and as you notice it is similar to the
shape
we saw.
If you convert it into pen for this
shape, you'll see it didn't work. So
let's make it
form and the number of bent line.
So we keep it to the minimum one.
So make it small and click.
Okay.
So here we have the initial shape
of
the exercise inside that plane
as we can see it here
in the picture. So here we have a
similar shape. So and it said that use
the unfold.
So as we learned so you said unfold.
Let's go to the unfold. Pick
that edge and bodies or bend to unfold
is that body. Click okay.
So now here is the unfold
shape
of that part.
So now let's create the holes. We have
we have almost 3 mm
hole.
Did the holes. So pick that first start
a sketch normal to and let's draw
circuit
3.12.
Let's make a dimension
of 2.5
or better make it five
and five over there
and go to feature
extraord.
So now we will have we have the hole.
Let's
you can make the holes all at once, but
I would like to make the holes
tangent to the curve.
Go to
feature
curved driven and select the curve and
features
is this
pole and we need 10
holes and let's make the distance
7.5. five
and that will be okay. Click. Okay. And
now we need
uh as you notice from the shape we need
eight on the other side.
Now we will make a line a direction line
for the second pattern. So we have the
face with an angle. We can make a center
line
between this angle. Make a sketch in the
face. Nor to select
center line
and make it an angle of
7°.
Except from the sketch
linear pattern
the direction we pick this
this 7.5
pattern
the features.
Let's make the distance
make it four
five.
Click okay. And now let's unfold
or fold back
the part.
Go sheet meter. Fold
select the edge is selecting the body.
And here we have
the required shape
on the side that sketch.
So if you compare it with the
part over there,
you'll notice that we got
a similar shape.
Welcome to tutorial number 173. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the last
command in the sheet meter menu, sweep
flange. And we will see how to locate
the sweep flange command and show it in
the menu.
And we'll have a look at some cases
where the SW flange
will work compared to the previous types
of sweep in the solid feature and
surfaces.
Also, we will have a look at the type of
path and profile to use to create the
swift lounge.
And then we will have a two examples
using swift flash and then compare it
with the miter flange.
So first of all if you go to the sheet
meter menu you will not see the sweep
flange. To locate the sweet flange
command, go to customize,
right click on the menu, customize,
and then go to commands,
sheet meter.
And here
you will see the sweep flash command. So
you can drag it and put it on the menu.
So we have the last command over there.
If you hover over the swift flange you
will see the profiles
or the path. They can be closed path or
an open path and we will make an example
for each case. But the main difference
with the sheet metal swip flange that it
require some certain type of path and
profiles
in order for the swift flange to work.
To make it clear, let's start to make
the first sweep flange.
Let's make a path. Go to the top plane
and let's make just a very simple path
straight line
exit
and go to the front plane to create a
profile.
If you go to
let's say let's make
uh an ellipse partial ellipse
and let's make this point this point con
and go to cheatme swift flash you See
the profile is selected the partial
ellipse and the path let's say this
line. Click okay. You'll notice
you will notice an error that only arcs
and lines are allowed to create sheet
metal sweep flange. Exit
the command. And if you go for example
to the sweep surface
the profile
and the path you notice it will work in
the surfaces.
So it is special case in
the sheet metal strip flash you need to
follow some certain type of profiles. So
let's edit the profile the ellipse and
delete that ellipse.
and make instead just one line
exit. Go to sheet metal swift flange.
The profile is this line and the path is
this sketch. And here you'll notice
you'll get a similar options which we
talked about before
and then click. Okay, this is a very
simple not nothing special in this
example.
So let's start a new part
and make this flange.
Select top plane center point rectangle
sheet metal is flange and the thickness
let's make it 1 mm. Click okay.
Now let's pick the right plan. Make a
sketch for the profile. In this case, we
will show you that
second case when the
strip flange won't work. So let's just
make a simple
profile on the
right plane.
And let's define it.
Give it a dimension of one 35.
And here
and here
and exit. Or we can directly go to the
sweep flange.
the the profile is selected and here
we can select the edges.
As you notice we can select edges but
this case will not work because the
sketch or the profile should be
perpendicular
to the beginning of the path. So let's
click okay and you will get another
error that the plane should be normal to
the edge.
So let's exit
that sketch and instead
make the sketch in that
layer.
Click sketch
normal to and select this line this line
and convert entities.
Now go to the sheet meter shift flange.
Select this edge that edge.
And you'll notice that you are able to
sweep around that edge.
And you will you may ask yourself that
it might be similar to the miter flange.
It is not. There are some differences.
So that depends on which type of shape
you need. And here the bending radius is
2 mm. You can change it for example to
five. It will change order um
in the angles
and as well you can select the type the
flange parameters
inside or outside
and so on. Let's make it outside
and click okay.
So here once you made the SW flash
around that plate and you create a
continuous
box and this also able
to be flattened as you notice over there
and here you see the bending lines
around.
Let's exit.
Now we will start another part
to create a swift flange where the minor
flange is not able to make it. So start
a new part.
Click okay
and select the top plane
and select line. Let's make
a path.
For example, let's make
a fridge base.
Let's make this horizontal and define it
with some dimensions. Let's make this
and this
350.
This is the path which we need.
except select the
front plane. If you make a
sketch on the right plane, it might not
work because the plane is not
perpendicular to the edge. Select the
front plane normal tool. Let's make
this shape
or this profile
and let's define it
50 and let's add some relation these are
already perpendicular and here as well
make this equal
and those lines
equal as well and make
25.
So we made this special profile without
adding any radiuses. it will be
automatically added when we
use the swift flange. So now the profile
is ready. Go to sheet metal swift
flange. As you notice only the swift
flange command is available for this
profile and the base flange. If you
click on the base flange, you'll create
only a straight
profile.
Let's just click on swift lash. The
profile is selected and select the path.
And let's make the
bending radius
file
and click okay. So we have this the
fridge pairs for example and it is able
to be flattened
as you notice over there. And here are
the bending lines.
Now let's see
the difference between this web flange
and the miter flange. We made this part
in one of the previous tutorials. a
tutorial about a miter flange and later
on we will the edges.
So we could do also the same type of box
if it is possible to be manufactured by
a sweep flange
and make it suitable for holding liquids
instead
of making it by miter flange and then
welded. So that depends actually in the
type of material and manufacturing
process. So if it is not possible to be
made by sweep flange then it can be done
by the miter flange. Let's have a look
at the cross-section of this profile. So
we have a profile looks like this. So
let's
start a new part
and make a similar
profile.
Select the top plane and make
a base plate.
Make it equal and define it dimension
of
50.
Then go to face flange
and have it with 1 mm thickness. Click
okay.
Now go to that face over there. Start a
sketch normal too.
And let's
make our profile.
can be something like this. This is
final
45.
Let's make this
tangent with this and
let's make this 50.
So here we have the profile
fully defined.
Go to sweep flange
and select the edges.
And let's make the
bending radius
to be 1 mm
and the
flange position outside.
Click okay.
So we have now a continuous
edges without any gaps as seen in the in
the miter flange case
over there. So we have a continuous wall
and it is suitable for holding liquids.
This kind of profile may be a little bit
detailed and can be difficult to be
flattened. As you notice over there, we
can
go and edit the sketch.
We can
move this part
except
and let's try to flatten.
And here you get your
middle tank.
Exit.
And we can try add him manually instead.
Welcome to tutorial number 174. This
tutorial will be a real example for
using the sheet metal commands. The
commands which we learned in the
previous tutorial in this series. We
will make this real power supply which
can be ready for manufacturing
and also this tutorial will be a good
review for the previous commands. We'll
make this power supply which consists of
two parts top part and the bottom part
and both of them can be flattened.
Start a new part for the first
chassis.
Go to the front plane
and
let's make
the base
for the button
part. Make mid point
and uh
dimensions
9.25.
This side is equal to this side.
Now go to sheet meter
is flanged
and extruded
to 150
and the thickness 75
bending radius.25
K factor 38
and
the relief rectangle. So these are the
basic information and it will be used
automatically for the next features.
When we are done click okay. So this is
a steam
and here in the appearance we can make
it
brushed ste on the press flange. Just
make sure that the
the P flange is outside
as you see over there.
Now we need an edge flash on this side.
Go to edge flash.
Select this edge
and make it a length
38.75.
And make sure the
the flange position is inside as you see
over there.
And here
the
relief is rectangular. And here over
there, edit the flange profile
and give it a distance
from this line
to this line.
Good.
The same
over here
and this
side is 38.8.
And before finishing the sketch, we can
do one more thing. Instead of making it
in a separated
command,
we would like make a cut over there for
another edge flange. So click on that
time
make it for construction and this line
make it for construction
normal too and
draw
this these two lines and give it
dimension of
11.75
and here.8
and
connect the rest of the lines.
So you notice there the sketch is valid.
Click finish.
So now we have the edge flange with
a relief over there
and
the cut here.
And here we would like to make another
edge flange.
Pick edge flange and select this edge.
Edit flange profile
normal too.
Here the dimension is
8 mm.
And here make a gap
of
2 mm.
And
we would like make a cut over there.
6.75
and this distance
is nine. And trim
the rest. And when you are done, click
finish. Just make sure that
the edge
is material outside.
Click okay.
And here we need another edge flash.
Select edge flash. Select this edge.
and edit flange sketch
normal too. The place of this line
is correct. And let's make this
for construction. and
draw another rectangle over there.
Make a gap of
and
This line
1.25
and this distance
15.5
and this
make 10.
And when you're done, click finish and
make the sure the edge is
material outside.
Click okay.
Add a miter flange on this side. Click
sketch
normal to
pick a line
and
Draw this shape
and give it the dimension of
four and
here 10.
Go to
sheet meter miter flange and you will
notice it is extruded automatically to
the edge. Click okay.
And here on the main edge flange we need
more cuts. We can make them
on the face or we can edit the main
sketch over there. So depending which
one is easier you can choose. I can
again pick the main edge flash edit
normal to add
some cuts.
And here
construction construction and
add another cut over there.
Now the sketch is valid
here. Make one mm
here. Three.
And this one
2.5
and this
3.5
distance
from here this one
and from this stands to
here
four.
And here four as well. And then can add
relation.
Reform the sketch.
So now the sketch is fully defined and
we have the cuts. Click finish. We could
also do the same by adding simple hole
but it might be easier to make it on the
same sketch.
And here add another edge flange.
Edit the sketch
normal too. And then
make a gap. Define it with
2 mm and the length
30 mm.
Click finish.
Let's make sure that is
outside again. Edit and make it material
outside.
And here we will add a flate for this
sharp edge.
Go to fillet
and make
2 mm blade over there.
And now we will make some holes for
fixing the second chassis, the top
chassis.
Click on this plane sketch
normal to
and draw a circle
over here
2.5.
This point.
Let's select
midpoint. All is already selected.
Select this edge. Select midpoint.
Select this. Make them vertical.
Go to sheet metal. It's shortcut
through all.
Click okay.
And here we can add one more hole by
drawing a circle or simply linear
pattern.
This hole direction is
Is this edge over there and
quantities to
feature
this hole and make it 20 mm over there?
Click. Okay.
and now we need a similar edge flange on
the other sides. So first let's make
sure that the first S flange is mid
plane extruded edit feature
and here make it mid plan. So this
process will save us from creating a new
plane.
Go to front plane
mirror
and let's pick the edges that we want.
First we need this edge and this edge.
And that's it. Click okay.
So the edge flanges are able to be
mirrored.
Unlike others feature in sheet met they
cannot be mirrored and should be created
individually.
We discussed
this in the previous tutorials
in this course.
And on the top there we will add a 3.5
mm edge flange. Go to edge flange.
Select this edge
and make sure the material outside
the length
is
3.5.
Click okay.
and add fillet of 1 mm around the sharp
edges feature. Fill it
1 mm.
Okay.
And here we would like to make a
cables
hole.
So let's
draw
slot
center point slot and make it to the
in the center of
and here make a dimension of
10 mm
and 10 mm over there
and
here make it 16
mm.
And one more cut to add.
Select center rectangle and
make a rectangle over there
tangent with this edge or colinear.
And
this one is
27.5.
So extrude cut
meter extrude cut. Select this
area and this area and this area.
Extrude. Cut 10 mm.
And here we can make the distance
from the center of the slope and the
edge
27.5.
So that we have chance to make another
cuts over there to fix the
second chassis or the top chassis.
And here we would like to make some
ventilation slots.
Click on vent.
Select.
Click on that face. Make a sketch normal
to select center slot
and draw
slot and define it with some dimensions.
Radius 1.25
and this is 6.5.
And from this edge to this edge
7.5.
And from this point
to this edge also 7.5.
Go to the And here go to linear sketch
pattern.
And we need
to fill that surface with slots. So
let's make the
7.5 the distance between
and let's make it 10
instance or entities to pattern
this slot.
So we can And here the distance we can
make it seven. And on direction two we
can make three
lines of pattern. And the distance make
it
12.
And we can skip
the unwanted
pattern. This one. This one.
And this one here we can try to make it
7.1.
That looks better.
So we can skip more instances
over there. Can skip
this slot and this slot
and make
distance
7.5.
And we can skip
this one over there.
When you are satisfied with the shape,
click okay.
Now add a little dimension over there
and over there.
that would defy
the pattern. Click okay. Now the pattern
is fully defined. Go to sheet meter
extrude cut length to thickness. Click
okay.
On the other side, we will make the
ventilation hole. Click on that face.
Start a sketch normal two and draw
three circles.
First make a distance from this the
center of the circle to the edge 20 mm.
Select midpoint
and the center make them horizontal
here. The outside diameter should be 35
and this
distance between the center to the edge
is 20. So, we need to fix the place of
the hole over there.
Go to
normal to
here. Make it 35 instead.
So, let's check.
So, now it is correct. So again edit the
ventilation sketch
normal two and here
should be
and the last circle
15. Now let's make lines for the spar.
Select line. Select center point
to the outside circle
and circular pattern the lines.
So the direction or the center of
circular pattern is point over there and
entities to pattern this line and make
them
eight. Click okay.
Now go to sheet metal. Then as we
learned how to use it, the boundary is
the outside circle.
As you notice now, it is already
got a cut and the ribs.
Let's make the
and reps. Let's
select
the lines.
And for the
sparse, we can select
this circle and this circle.
And we have 2 mm
spar and 2 mm reps and define affiliate
of one mm
4.5
and click. Okay.
and hide the sketch.
So this is the ventilation.
Now we will make some mounting holes on
this chassis to mount the second
chassis. So go to this surface, start a
sketch normal two
and draw three center point rectangles
in the middle of each
edge
and a third one
over here.
So make the
The edges of rectangles equal
and give it a
of 5 mm.
And the second side of the rectangle is
tangent
or colinear with the edge the chassis
as well in the rest of
rectangles. So now they are fully
defined.
So extrude them.
Go to sheet me tab. Extrude cut
to this
surface. Extrude to surface
and select that surface
or better
this surface over there.
Click okay.
So now we have the mounting holes over
there.
And here we may need some fillet for the
sharp edge here. Go to fillet
1 mm.
Click here. Um
in this side
also we can add
over there.
Click. Okay.
So now we'll see the final touches. Now
we need more edges. Here we need another
edge flange. Go to sheet metal
edge flange
and select
this
side
and it is already material outside.
Edit.
Make it normal too.
and we can mirror the holes as well.
Select front length
feature mirror.
Click okay.
And one last thing, we need a socket
hole over there.
No more to center point rectangle.
Give a dimension of
by 19
and a fillet of 3.5.
Okay.
I'm dimensioning
make it 17.5
and this point to this edge
as well 17.5.
Click okay. Go to shape meter
extrude cut length thickness.
Okay.
So now we have the power supply is
almost ready. We can also add an impulse
to the bottom.
Go to forming tool counter sync impulse
to
and position.
Make sure it is in the
select midpoint and this point. Make
them horizontal.
And as well over here,
select this point
and this point. Make it vertical.
Okay.
for the tube chassis. Start a new part.
New part. Click.
Go to the front plane. Start a sketch
and draw
this shape.
Make this point with the line
midpoint. Give the dimension of
mm and here
the angle
in this gap
and
this edge
5.4 before
we can mirror the same
lines on the other side.
Go to mirror
and select
these three lines. Mirror about the
center line here. Click okay.
So here we have the base
of the top chassis. Go to sheet meter
this flange and extrude it to
on the other side. And here you'll have
the same sheet metal configurations from
the previous part
75 and the rest of the values.
Click okay.
And for the appearance we can add
brushed steel. And also we can add the
material over there.
Stainless steel
sheet apply.
Close.
So here is the base shape. And let's
just make sure that
the side of
sheet meter is outside the sketch as we
notice over there. Click okay.
We can make one thing to make it easier
to
follow or that top chassis is matching
the bottom chassis. We can start an
assembly and work in the assembly mode.
Click okay.
And here show the center point and drag
part one in the center.
So now we have the chassis is centered.
Hide again the center point. Let's mount
the top part. Select the part and
here
can make this side consent to this side
or we can make this line
consider to that face.
Click okay.
Now let's make this one coincident.
So now we have the basic shape is
matching
the top chassis. And here we can make
some modification.
We can change this the color of
just to make it easier to see.
So here in the assembly mode, it can be
easier to check for matchings.
So we can go now try close the gap. If
we go here normal to you, you'll see
there is a little gap over there. We can
measure it.
and close it and measure the gap between
this face
and this face.
You will see the normal distance
is 1 25 26.
So go to the
edit part and edit sketch.
Here we can make it 30
- 1.26
table.
Now it is matching. And here we need
to make the material inside.
Is it pl
Okay.
So now we have the two sides perfectly
matching with the top chassis.
and pink
to
add another dimension.
Click okay.
and exit the sketch.
Now we don't have any warning. Then
let's continue modifying the top chassis
here. We need
if we change the transparency
here. We can notice that we need some
cuts.
So let's try to
create that cut.
Select that
or edit bar.
Normal to start a sketch in that face.
Normal to
draw
a cutting rectangle.
the same on that side.
The two sketches are fully defined. Now
go to feature extrude cut through all.
So it will cut only
on the top part.
And here we need an extra cut for that
edge. Stop sketch normal to select again
a rectangle from this point
to this point
and this line to this line.
feature shortcut
up to next.
And here on the top, we need more cuts
for inserting
a mounting teeth.
So go to top plane
start a sketch normal too.
And here we can show
rectangles that we need.
Select center point or select rectangle
and draw rectangle for that cut
and one over there.
And a third one in the bottom.
Go to feature
sl cut
up to next.
Click okay
and change the style of the
material. Now we can see that we created
a cut for the mounting teeth. Now we
need to insert an edge flange over
there. Go to sheet meter
edge flange and select this.
And we can make it
the distance three up to
mm.
And the material we can make it bend
outside.
and select the rest of the edges.
So that is the mounting teeth to mount
the top. Just click okay.
And now more things to add. We need
holes
to fix on the edges. Start a sketch in
there. Normal to change the style of the
material
and draw
circles
the
we can fully define
They're already matching the
holes on the button chassis. Go to
feature extrude cut through all. Click
okay.
Change the style of the material. And
you'll notice that we made
perfect holes that they are matching the
base chassis.
So now the top chassis is almost fixed
on the top on the bottom chassis. We
have the screws over there and we have
the mounting teeth
or tabs
over there.
And one last thing to add is ventilation
holes on the top similar to the one on
this side over there. Click on the top
plane normal to
and draw center line
and draw
cutting slots.
and from here to here
five
and the radius over there is 2.5 by two.
So it is 1.25
and the distance from here
to this size is 21.5.
So now we need three lines of these
slots and seven pattern
to the left. Go to linear sketch
pattern.
On the x-axis
make it seven
and on y axis three.
The distance
should be five
on the x- axis and
16 on the
yaxis. Entities to panel is this slot.
So here we can change the directions.
Click okay.
And here we can try to fully define
calculate.
So remove the relation should be a bit
easier. Click okay. And now mirror
the
slots
in that center line. Click okay.
Now go to sheet meter
extrude cut length to thickness. Click
okay.
So now we have the ventilation slots
are ready and the
chip of the power supply
looks better. Now we set that part.
So change the
transparency
and again return
back to the main color of this.
So here we have the final look of the
power supply.
Save.
Save all. And now we can go to the this
part open part two and try to
to flatten the part to see.
Now we have
the part which we need to cut to create
that
power supply.
In the next tutorial, we will see how to
create a drawing to send that part for
manufacturing and what is required in
sending sheet metal drawings in order to
understand the bending process and where
to bend. So the next tutorial will be
the last tutorial in this series and it
is about how to create drawing for
manufacturing the parts. So we'll make
this example
in order to show you how to manufacture
or produce it by sheet metal processes.
Welcome to tutorial number 175. The last
tutorial in this series sheet metal in
solid works is about making the drawing
for your sheet metal products to be sent
for manufacturing.
So before starting with this tutorial, I
assume that you already attended the SL
works drawing section. If not, I will
put the link for that series in the
description below. In this tutorial, we
will make a drawings for our previous
product. We made we made it in the
previous tutorial. We made this fully
manufactured power supply and we will
make drawing for it to send it for
manufacturing. So we will see the
difference between the the standard
drawing which we saw before and the
sheet metal drawings.
We will make as well the standard
drawings
then make the flatten drawing
and we'll talk about the bend table and
punch table.
So here we have our power supply from
the previous tutorial which contain of
two parts.
So first let's make a drawing for the
top part and for this part we will make
it from the part mode open part and for
the next drawing we will make it from
the assembly mode. So we have our
top part over here and as we learned
before to make a drawing go there make
drawing from part or assembly.
And here we will choose A3 the most
popular one. Click okay.
And here we get the
sheet paper. And if you notice to the
right, you will have a flatten pattern.
So this is new for a sheet metal. We
didn't see that in the solid products.
So let's first make the
the standard views.
Find the front plane
and
make the right plane and the top plane
and then asometric.
Click okay. We are already familiar with
this views. We make we can make some
arrangement to make a place for the
flatten view. So now we have the basic
drawings over there and they are half
the size of the original size because as
you see they're half one to two. Now
let's go again to the drawings and pick
the flatten pattern.
So this is the most important
view of the sheet metal drawings. You
can also make it make for it a front and
top view. But for in this case it is not
necessary because
all we see is
a flat sheet of metal.
So now here if you zoom in to the
flatten pattern you will see the
direction of bending. Here are the
bending lines which are very important.
And here we have as well
the other
bending lines and the information on
them.
So it may a little bit confusing and not
clear to see. We can manage it for
example
changing the size limit to double the
size or the actual size and it is
actually depends on which is better to
be sent. For example, there is a way to
send all the views the standard views
and the flapping views. For example,
the reference will be the flatten view
and to make it easier also sending the
standard views.
But it might be
small and difficult to see. We can try
to change the size to one
by one. But as well in this case it will
be the sheet of paper will be small
to handle the views.
So one way to solve it for example we
can delete the flatten
view and make it in a spreadsheet.
And here we can have only the standard
view the front
the right and the asometric
and we can define them by adding
dimensions. We can add dimension
automatically. If you go to annotation
model item and select the view
here pick the first one and second one.
You can add more and click okay.
Yes. And here you will get the
dimensions
which we made. Here you have all
dimensions. It is an easy way to add
dimensions.
And again we can
add it for the next view.
Click okay. And here we have
the required dimension for the right
view and the last view. Click okay.
So to deal more about drawings and so on
as I said you can attend the drawing
section again
we already discuss it about the basic
drawings. So here is the first standard
drawing which can be additionally
attached to the flatten pattern and sent
to manufacturing. So start a new
drawing.
Okay.
And pick A3.
And for the part we will need the part
two.
And check the A flatten.
And here you get
the part over there.
So as we said before, we have the
bending lines
in there and the information required in
order to manufacture this part.
Also you can make it
bigger for example because we have
enough space
can make it two or we can make it
one.
So now it is easier to see and more. So
you can save this drawing
and attach the second one with it which
we made in the beginning. So this is one
way you have the flatten pattern
and you have the standard drawings. So
it can be helpful in that case.
For the next part we can see another
way. We can make only the flatten view
and attach instead the punch and bend
tables. So that might be
more accurate and easier to see.
And let's go back. And here have the
standard views. So now let's go back to
the assembly
and
we will make a drawing from the assembly
mode. First go to
new
make drawing from partse simply
select A3.
Okay. And here you'll see that we have
only the assembly.
But we are interested to make
drones for the base chassis.
To locate it, go to view layout
model view. Double click on part one.
And here you will see what you can
attach to that drawing. We need the flat
pattern
of course beside the standard views. And
here you can change the view
that you want. So click over there. Here
we can add top view and here a side view
in order to make easier that there is a
forming tool in the middle. And here we
can see the shape of it.
And as we said, we have only the flatten
pattern. So we can increase the side to
be one by one.
If you if it didn't change, go to sheet
meter scale
and
select one.
Click okay.
So there is
the bending lines are shown over there.
If you click on the bending line, you
get the information and you can also add
more information. You see the direction
of bending, the angle of bending and the
bending radius. You can add also more
information to this bending line. If you
click on the view,
go to the left here, you will see
the parameters you may need. So for
example, the bend direction is
already
selected, supplementary angle and the
bend radius. Here you can add bend
order. You see the bin? This is the
first bin, the second bin and so on.
That can be handy. Click okay. And if
for some reason it is not clear to see
from the
paper. So it can be easier to make it in
separated table. If you click
on the right mouse there in the bottom
you will see tables
or you can access that
or in annotation tab tables and we are
interested in the bend table and here
are the format you can choose from.
Click okay.
And here
you will see the information
on a table which might be
easier to see. And here you have the
tag, direction, angle and inside radius.
For example, a you'll see the annotation
is over here. So you can let's select
all the annotations
and
make an arrow. Click okay.
And here you can see
where is A and B and C and so on.
So this way may be easier. So it
dependings in which way you can see it
better. So here we have G and E
and so on. And here is the fixed face
which is the base plate.
And one more thing in this flattened
drawing we have a forming tool which
used in the middle. We used an impulse
to create the punch in the middle of
that sheet.
So we can show the information related
to this format tool by showing the punch
table. Go again to table,
select punch table. And here you will
specify the X and Y axis to locate the
place of the
forming tool. So for the X-axis I will
select the bottom edge and Yaxis
I will select the first edge over here.
So we have the origin point should be
over there.
And the face will be this face.
So this is the easiest way. And click
okay. And here you get the
punch table related that forming too.
So the tag is A1.
So the works automatically recognize the
punch or forming tool and the location
related to the origin point which we
made zero and zero over there
y location
angle
and quantity one. So you can add
dimension for that. go to smart
dimension and
to make it easier
to know and you can add dimension for
the rest of the parameters you can go to
model item
select
first two option click okay click yes
and here you will see all the dimension
shown
the drawing.
or you can add them in a separated
sheet with the standard views. So there
are many options in order to reach to
the final manufacturing
shape.
So for now I will go to annotation
and
hide the dimensions for now and we can
add them
or show them when we need.
Hello and welcome to the very first
tutorial in a new series in solid works
mold tools. This is tutorial number 176
in general and we will talk about the
mold tools. Where to locate the commands
and which manufacturing processing are
using the mold tools and then we will
have a quick review for the surfacing
section in the mold tools
and how they are related to the mold
tools. And then at the end we will have
a look at some important definitions in
molding draft parking line and
shrinkage.
So go to solid works and start a new
part.
Okay. So to find the mold tools commands
go to insert
and here you will see molds or an easier
way here in the tabs
right click and check mold tools and
here you will get the mold tools
sections
or the mold tool commands. So if you
have a look at the mold tool commands
you will see there are four sections.
The first section is related to
surfacing. Most of these commands we
talked about in the surfacing
section. And here are the analysis
section.
The third section is drafting and
parting line and scaling. And the last
section,
this is also an advantage of the Solid
Works software. It has more tools
commands. So it makes working with molds
easier. As we know making molds is a
complicated process.
And the mold are used mostly in
injection molding processing
manufacturing process mostly for plastic
and also in casting also. There are some
molds or dyes for forgings.
So before going some molding clearance
definitions, we will have a quick
revision review for the surfacing
sections and I will put a link below for
the surfacing tutorials which we talked
about before. So go to the top plane and
we will make a very simple
block.
So let's make it of a cube and here make
a dimension of 200
and extrude it into directions.
Go to features extrude
mid plane
and extrude it 200
steel. So let's add a steel.
Also there are some molds made of
aluminum.
So we have a very basic block without
any separation or any parts. Go to the
mold tools and we will see how to use
planner surface. Go to the sketch one.
Show select planner
and select the sketch.
Click okay. So you just created a
separating surface. Hide
that. You will see there is a surface.
So this is one way to use planner
surface.
And also if you would like to let's show
again the block. And if you would like
to have the planner surface not in the
middle
like shifted 1 cm
or few mm above the center you can go to
the offset
select bler surface and make it
20 for simple. Click okay. Hide the
block again. You will find a second
surface which is offset.
Show the block again. Roll it surface.
For example, if you don't need all the
time to hide the block and need to show
the the surface, let's hide the sketch
because there are two surface but they
are not shown. You can go to rounded
surface and here are the options. For
example, you can select the edge of that
surface and the rest of the surfaces
the rest of the edges.
So here you have a 10 mm. You can
increase it. You can make it normal to
the surface
or table to vertx or sweep. So we stick
on the first option. We can make it just
straight
and we are done. Click okay. So now you
have the surface is clear and it is
clear there is a surface separating the
block
and fill it surface. For example, if you
would like to have a different chip than
the cubic shape or the
the square
shape, you can make a custom
surface. You can just for example create
the surface on the top of that chair
and draw a circle.
Give it a dimension of
350.
Go to surface.
Go to more tools.
Exit from fill surface. Select.
So you fill it that surface
which is circular surface.
So I'm going to suppress that
circular surface.
So it a surface for example we have
created that separating surface
but when we generated that with surface
we made
one for the rid and a second for the
male. And here is the offset
which we can suppress
to make it clear.
So that offset
and here we have only two surfaces
which can be better if we make it made
them in one single surface. You go to
meet surface.
You can select the rolet and
the planner surface. Click okay.
You'll notice that now we have only one
single
square surface. So this is a quick
review for the surfacing
commands in the mold tools and later on
we will see how we can divide the block
and make it two parts and adding parting
line.
So now let's talk about some molding
theorems. So the first term we will talk
about is the draft and why we need the
draft. So the draft definition according
to the Wikipedia website is the amount
of taper for molded or cast part
perpendicular to the parting line and it
is measured by degrees. And we will show
this what is exactly mean with drop. And
you may already know what is the drop
because there is many commands in solid
works we use in the solid features. We
have the draft. So there we are creating
an angle. And why we need the draft? It
make it easier to extract the parts the
injected part or cast part from the
mold. And that will also
increase the mold life. As you know the
molds are quite expensive. And the next
term is the parting line. So this is the
parting line where the draft is
calculated. So we made the part as you
remember in the beginning here. So the
parting line should be
this line over here which is spreading
the mold. Also draw the parting line
here. So we can draw
that separating line between the two
sides of the mold. And here we can draw.
So here I made a very simple shape. If
you see the line, the straight line over
there that can be the parchment line.
And the top side over here is the upper
side of the mold. And here is
the lower part with the mold. And here
is the gasted or the injected product.
Let's say it is a cup over there.
So the draft is if you see the angle
also the graph can be positive and
negative. Here for example this side
and we say this is this line is the
parting line and here can be a positive
draft and this side is a negative side.
So if you imagine the product over there
with a draft it will be easier to
to be extract extracted from the mold.
So this is a positive draft and here
this side is a negative draft.
So here again we can see this is a
parting line
and here is if we make a straight line
and here is
the draft angle.
So one last term is shrinkage. Once we
extracted this cup from the mold.
So this is the actual size of the mold
but after cooling it will get smaller.
For example this is a plastic or a
metallic. So that is a very basic. So as
we know the material are shrink when it
gets colder if the plastic which is used
is will be shrinking with 40%. So the
mold should be designed 4% larger than
the actual I'm dead.
Welcome to tutorial number 177, the
second tutorial in solid works mode
tools. In this tutorial, we will talk
about the first command in the analysis
section of more tools draft analysis.
For that reason, we will make this
plastic mobile cover. So, we will apply
the draft analysis on that plastic part.
And we will show you how we made this in
this tutorial. And also during the
design process we will have some faces
with a draft and other faces without a
draft or we can notice that in the draft
analysis process. And then when we are
done with the part we will apply some
draft analysis to that part and see if
it requires some drafts or not.
And that is the first step for preparing
the plastic part for injection molding
and creating a mold.
And we will see the colors and explain
them and read the drop from the part and
see if there is a need to add any draft
to the part.
Now we will start making a front cover
of a simple
mobile phone. Start a new part.
Go to the top plane. Start a sketch and
pick a center point rectangle
and give it dimension of 43.5
and
second side
[Music]
18.5.
Add affiliate of 18.5
to the upper corners
and 12.5
to the lower corners.
Now we'll make another
sketch or another profile for the top.
Select threepoint arc
and here
and give it a dimension of
50.
radius and the point
from here to here
26.
Make this point and this point
horizontal.
So now we will extrude the first
profile.
Go to feature extrude and select the
outside profile. Extrude it to 5
mm.
and add a draft of five degree.
So that is an important. Click okay. And
now show the sketch.
So select the sketch. Go to extrude.
Selected contour. Select that contour.
And it have to be five + 3.5.
And the draft as well. 5° merge results.
Hide the sketch.
And now select the right plane. Start a
sketch to make a cut on the upper side.
Select three
point arc
and make an arc from the first edge to
the second edge
with a radius of 25.
And the distance between this point and
the upper face 5 mm.
and
and make the distance between
this point to the corner 15 mm. Go to
extrude cut.
You see the
the arrow of the cut is upward. Make it
through all both. Click okay.
We will add some fillets.
Go to fillet. First place is over there.
And make it 20.
Click okay. And make another fillet
with radius of 7.5.
And select this edge.
Okay. And the last fillet
for the upper face
is three
on five.
Select that edge.
Click okay.
Now let's shell
the cover with
a thickness of 1 mm. Click. Okay.
And now we will make a cut for the
screen, the mic,
the the speaker and the buttons.
Go to this face. Start a sketch normal
to
here make an offset
of one mm
reverse.
Click okay.
So this is the first cut for the screen
and here we will make a cut for the
speaker.
Let's make a reference circle
for construction
and give it a dimension of
7.5
and dimension from this point
to the upper edge
also 7.5. five
9 mm
and the center of the circle to this
point
vertical.
So this is the reference circle for the
for the speaker
holder. And now we'll make another
circle
for construction
for the cuts.
Make it a dimension of 7.5
divided by two.
And let's make
the cut circle
1 mm.
This circle is equal to this
circular pattern.
direction is this point. Click. Okay.
Here we can make the whole bit tighter.
We can make 3.25
and make a relation
over there. and
add a dimension to fully define
the circles.
And here in the bottom, we will make a
slot for
the mic.
Draw a slot with the dimension of
3.5.
the radius of 0.5
and the distance between this point
and the down edge
9 mm.
Give a relation from this point
and the origin
of
vertical here. We can make it a little
bit smaller.
mm.
So now we can make a cut and make the
bottoms in another cut.
Now we will make holes for the buttons.
Start a sketch in this face
normal to and draw an ellipse.
Give it a dimension of
mm
for the vertical distance 5.25
and the horizontal
distance 7.25.
and make a distance from this point and
the origin
to be
11 mm.
Now let's add some relation to fully
define the sketch. Select these three
points.
Make horizontal and this point this
point vertical and add two more
dimension from this
point to this point.
the lowest edge
of
18.25
mm. Here we'll draw a center line for
reference reasons.
And now make a linear pattern
with that ellipse entities to pattern
this ellipse
in the x-axis. Let's make it 11 and
three reverse the directions. So you
have the second ellipse is center in the
middle and we need four in the y axis
and make a distance of 8 or 9 mm. Click
okay.
And here we'll draw the main
buttons
and here make this
line
this point
coincident
and give dimension of
10.5 five
this and here give it 5.5.
Let's fix this ellipse.
And here the distance 5.5
and
this line
8.25.
and add a flat for the corner of 2.5.
Go to mirror.
Select
these entities this line. Click okay.
can add a fixed relation for each
ellipse or fully defined sketch and make
a cut
through all.
Click okay.
Now we will make housing for the mic and
speaker holes.
So if you show the sketch of the
speaker holes. And here for the
And let's add another circle for the
mic.
Edit sketch
normal to let's make this is a little
bit bigger. 7.5
and add circle.
Make this circle with this line tangent
and
make that circle for construction
sketch on that face. normal to select
this line convert entities
as well. Select that line
convert entities. Go to features
extrude.
Select here thin feature
with a thickness 75
inside the circle.
and extrude it up to body. Select that
body and here make an offset
of 2.5
in the other direction.
Click okay.
Start a sketch on that face.
Normal two and draw a circle
over there.
the dimension of
3.75
and distance between this point and the
origin
mm
and the vertical distance
50 mm.
Make a center line to mirror this circle
on the other side.
Select mirror.
Select this circle. Mirror about
center line
as well. We can mirror them on the left
side. Make again another center line.
Mirror.
Select both
circles.
mirror about
this center line. Click okay. Now
extrude of the body.
And we will add to these screw cylinders
extra fits so it fit better on the
second side. This process could be saved
if we make the circles in the previous
process when creating the screw
cylinders. Select this first. Click
offset.3 reverse direction inside. Click
okay.
And for the rest as well.
Good feature. Extrude 1 mm. Click. Okay.
Now we will make the holes for the
screws. Go to hole.
select hole
and the diameter is
2 mm
and the distance here make it 5.25 25
position. Select
each
each cylinder of them.
Let's check the whole not.
Okay, here we need to decrease the whole
make it four.
that looks. Okay.
Then click okay.
And here we have the holes.
And one
final touch to add a fillet for the
edges. Make a fillet to five. Select
this face.
This face.
Here
is our mobile cover ready. First thing I
would like to mention is the top plane.
If we notice over there, the top plane
is our reference in creating this part.
So I will show that plane.
And now go to mold tools select draft
analysis. So the first option over there
is the analysis parameters
which means that we need the reference
for this injected molded part which
represent the direction of pulling and
injecting. For example in this case we
can consider the top plane is the
reference because the pulling will be
upward.
So we select the top two plane
and here the angle represent the draft
angle. So this angle is probably high.
For this I will make it one. But for
now, if you notice the part, we have
green on the top side as we discussed in
the previous tutorial that represent
positive tr and the yellow
faces. These are bars require drafts and
the negative so far it is in the bottom
side that represent a negative draft. It
is okay. So far it is in the bottom side
because this side will be dragged
outside.
So as you remember in the design process
we added a draft for that face in the
upper side and we didn't apply any draft
when we created the screw
cylinders. So that you can see that in
the draft analysis process. So this the
draft analysis purpose is to check for
draft and which part you draft.
So that we that is the reason we didn't
add a draft to show you that it can be
shown over there. So, and if you hover
over the face, you will see the drag or
the draft angle is
0 degrees. And if you hover over this,
the draft angle 5° as you remember when
we started to make this part, we extrude
it with a draft of 5°.
So I close this for now and go to the
part.
And here we added a draft of 5°.
So let's just remove the draft. Click
okay
and check the draft analysis.
Check the top plane and here the side
also side without any draft. You will
notice it is in a yellow part.
So this is one thing to think about is
while designing the plastic part to add
a draft during the process that may save
some time. So exit the draft analysis
and fix the part again at the draft of
five degrees.
Now go back to draft analysis. Select
the
analysis parameter. We set the top
plane. And here is the draft angle. This
draft angle is for comparing greaser.
For example, we wish to have
five
degree draft angle. for example for the
outside. And if you click okay, that
will show everything is in green. And
click again. Let's say that we need it
10° for our product. So
select the parameter and here you will
see that this side will require a draft.
But for our case, we already apply the
draft for the outside face and we don't
need to compare it and just need to
compare the draft of the inside
cylinders. And we wish to have
between 0.5 to one degree
draft angle. So let's make it one
degree.
So you'll see that the top face is okay.
And we need only to fix the outside face
of these cylinders.
And if you go to adjust triad, if this
is if you would like to change the angle
of the reference plane, for example, we
said the plane representing the
direction of pole. So if we adjust
and let's say that
part will be injected in with an angle
and you will notice
there are some
troubles with some faces but that case
is not logical
and just exit return to normal and or
control Z and start again
and here we it one degree
and let's say for the direction of pole
we take it the right plane you will see
there is something wrong and everything
need to be changed
and it is clear that the direction is
wrong otherwise that is the correct
direction of pole and then this part
will require a lot of work for example
you need draft in each of these faces So
return to top plane one degree and face
classification.
So the positive draft we have 32. The
faces required draft in yellow
59 and the negative are 49. The negative
ones they are okay. So far they are in
the dotten side.
Straddle face. This face is kind of
in between in some meeting points and
here the positive steep
over there. So these faces
are in green. It is somehow okay. They
are laying in between the positive
draft and the required draft face. So
the area in between it can be a steep
face and for the bottom steep it will be
in dark blue.
And let's say that we need to apply
a draft angle for these
outside cylinders
and then start the draft analysis once
again. So for this for example the
bottom holes we can apply a draft but it
is a thin layer. It might not be that
big problem for injecting molding but
the cylinders over there we need to try
to fix or add some draft
and inside cylinder since it is designed
for a screw
logically it doesn't need any draft
so exit and see how we can apply a draft
for these
faces. So you have one choice is go to
draft over there in another way by going
to the solid feature over there
and when we extruded this part you could
add an angle of 0.5
and make it outward.
Now go to draft analysis again and the
reference plane is this plane and here
we see five.
So we get the red over there. So as we
said the red in the side is okay
and we can add one more draft for that.
address.
Select
address five.
Click okay
and check the draft analysis once again.
And here we get red color. So we need
only two faces over there. This face
and this face. Click okay. Select this
edit feature and add drop of
five.
So we got a green that mean in the
bottom side that mean this is a wrong
direction of pawn. So edit again
make it outward click. Okay.
So now we have
the button side is
ready and we have the poles
we have the draft applied for the
required faces
and on the top side
and if you wish to add a draft as well
for that part. So that can be done
during the cut by adding a draft and
running the drop analysis once again.
So one last conclusion this tutorial
that the draft analysis is a very good
way to check for the draft. If someone
misses to add a draft al it is a good
practice to add a draft during the
design process that would save some
Hello and welcome to this tutorial
number 178. In this tutorial, we will
talk about the next command in the mood
tools under cut analysis. In the
previous tutorial, we talked about the
draft analysis and we see how to apply
the draft and read the colors and solve
any draft issue in order to make the
injection molding process easier without
any filter. In this tutorial, we will
talk about another issue, the undercut
analysis and understand the meaning of
the undercut and applying and solving
the issue.
So now here we have this
mobile cover from the previous tutorial
and as you remember we applied the draft
analysis and here we selected the
direction of all which is the top plane
and the minimum draft analysis we wanted
was five and here you have
all the part as we
But there are also other issues we have
to look forward. For example, the
undercut surfaces. So let's go to the
undercut analysis and discuss more about
it. Here we will also
pick the direction of pole again the top
plane and here we will see the undercut
faces. The first two cuts, direction
one, direction two, they are the faces
which you can see from direction one.
Then we look on that arrow which
represent direction one. And here we see
the
light blue faces
and direction two are the faces which we
can see from the top side.
So basically these are faces. No worry
about them because they are just
representing the faces which we can see
from top and bottom of this cover. These
two faces we need to think more about
the
undercut and straddle undercut. distraed
undercut are something in between might
not be that big problem but the uploaded
undercut we need to try to think how to
fix them and they are shown in red for
example we cannot see them clearly they
are mostly because of the flate over
there so the undercut the oploed
undercut actually the faces can be
difficult for the to be injected or to
be seen by the mold and to make it clear
we can try to make another example. So
the oluded undercut in this case are
because of the fillet over there and
they might not be that big issue it can
be easily extracted from the mold. So as
we said the undercut faces are so tiny
and they are not that
by imagining the injection direction it
will not represent any issue. So we'll
have to do another case where the
undercut might represent a problem while
extracting the cover from the mold. So
here start a sketch normal to and let's
make for sample a cut
for the charger or the speaker
five
and
8 mm
and from this point
this point
five
and select this point presenter with
this point and make a cut
of 0 five.
So for example we have this Extruded
cut in this cover and go again to more
tools
under cut analysis
and the direction of P is the top plane
and as you notice over there we have
a large surface with unseen
undercut face. So this face might
represent a problem. It is
a other tiny face over there.
So there are two ways to fix this
cut either by removing it or making a
path
for the surface. So let's make
exit from the undercut analysis.
Select this face. Start a sketch.
Convert entities and make it
make a cut
through all.
Click. Okay. So now we make a part for
that surface and let's again go to more
tools under cap analysis
and select the two plane and here we
have only one
face after we solve it the after we
solve it the inside face and we can try
to
to fix this issue again by adding
another draft.
As you notice, we solved the face over
there and we have one remaining undercut
face need to be solved. We can easily
fix it by make the cut through both
directions.
So, as you notice right now, we
managed to
fix that cut over there. And here can be
a snap fit or so this area can be a
place for a snap fit or also you can add
another hole over there for the charger.
Welcome to Solid Works tutorial number
179. In this tutorial, we will continue
talking the next analysis tool in the
mold tool section.
So the next analysis tool is the parting
line analysis. So after performing the
previous analysis, draft analysis and
undercut analysis, now it's time to
prepare for creating the mold. So for
creating a mold, we need a parting line.
So the parting line analysis aims to
help in placing the parting line of the
mold. So let's think about this part.
And we need a mold for that. And here is
simple view of a mold of two parts. And
let's imagine that the inside cavity is
for the mobile cover. We closing the the
mold. There should be a parting line.
Let's close this mold and
change it to and change the
transparency.
So you can imagine the inside
product is the mobile cover and here is
the parting line in the middle.
So the parting line analysis
feature helps to place the parting line
for creating the mold. Now let's go back
to our mobile cover and let's see where
we can place our parting line.
In this case for this upper half
normally it should be inside the top of
the mold. So let's click on the parting
line analysis and the direction of the
pole is the top plane and you will
notice the parting line will be on the
edge over there. So it is logically as
we said that would be the upper side of
the mold. So in this case the parting
line will be on the edge or in other
words this part will be inside the mold
and the top face of this part will be
the top face of the mold. If we go back
to the the mold over there
and hide
this
part. So this is the or the upper face
of the bottom mold and here is the edge
which can be the parting line for our
mobile cover. So to make it clear we
will make another product. So let's see
another example. Start a new part and
pick the top plane.
And we can draw
a simple cone.
Click okay. And
let's say we would like to
create a pattern line for this part. Go
to the mold tools. Click on the parting
line and the direction of pull.
Depending on how you would like to pull
it, let's say we would like to have a
mode that
will with a direction of pull on the
right plane. And you will see
there is the parting line in order to
inject each half of this cone. And if
you would like to make the direction of
pull the top plane. So you will notice
that the whole cone will be injected in
one in the first half of the mold and
there is no parting or preview for a
parting line. So depending on the size
and the mold, you can pick as a helping
tool for placing or where to place the
parting line. And we are done. Click
okay. So you'll notice this is the
recommended parting line for your mold.
And here we can notice if you imagine
this product. So this is the first half
of the cone and
the second side will be the
other side of the cone.
Welcome to tutorial number 180. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the feature
section
as we see in the picture below here or
the section comes straight after the
analysis
section.
As you might notice, this feature can be
found in other sections. But there's a
reason why they are in this mold tools
sections because they have some specific
importance.
We will talk about the split line
feature and then talk about the draft
move face and then the scale and see how
they are related to the mold tools
section. In the previous tutorial we
performed a parting line analysis for
this cup and we took the right plane as
the direction of pole and we got the
parking line shown as we see. Maybe in
this case for this cup maybe the the
best pole direction is the top plane and
that's why we will try to make another
example to see to run the parting line
and then talk about the split line.
Also we performed the split line or
parting line analysis on the mobile
cover. And if we
took
the direction of pole to be the
right plane.
As you notice, click okay. You didn't
get any line.
So that is clear that is not the right
direction of pull or you cannot for
example mold this part in two separated
each half in one separated part of the
mold.
So that why again we
run the parting line analysis and pick
the top plane. And once you have the
parting line analysis on, you'll notice
there is no any appearance
or colors on the part. So let's start
making a new part. This time we'll make
a simple this and try to make parting
line and then
how to use a split line as a helping
tool. Here I will insert four planes
parallel to the
two plane and in each plane I will draw
a circle
and on the second plane another circle.
Make it 40
and on plane
number three. Another
circle and give it a dimension of
100.
There again another
circle. Give it dimension of 60. And
then the last circle.
Give it dimension of 75
and go to
feature
boundary post and select
So this is a simple vase plastic vase
and for this kind of part because it is
curve it might not be possible to make
the direction of pole to be on the top
plane.
Let's just hide the planes.
It will be difficult to extract this
from one side. So let's go to more tools
parting line. And if we pick the top
plane,
this shows that this part with this
complicity can be molded on three parts
because this
side to the left if you separate it and
that side by itself can be easily to be
injected
and extracted and the second side and so
on.
But this might be not logical. And let's
try now to find a better solution. Go to
parting line. And this time select the
right plane. And here we got a more
logical solution with one parting line.
And we said that parting line represent
the the line between the sides of the
mold.
Here we can add
appearance to this.
So again go to the parting line and
select the right plane. And here we got
the parting line.
But you might need to not to work on the
parting line mode. So you can
deactivate it and instead as we know
that there is the parting line
is
over there we can make a sketch
on the front plane
and draw a line
match. ing the parting line
and exit. And then
we can go to the split line
and select the face
which will be this
face and select projection.
Click okay.
So here you can deactivate the parting
line and you get the appearance again
and by split line
as a helping tool.
So here the split line you will get the
a preview for. So by performing the
parting line analysis, we knew that the
line over there in the middle
representing the parting line and we
made a sketch that is matching that
parting line and to keep it as a
reference while working or to see it
without the need of activating all the
time the parting line analysis mode. We
created a split line
And now let's talk about the next
feature. It is also an important feature
in injection molding tools. Every part
as we said to make it easier to extract
should have an a draft. Perform a draft
analysis for this phase and we'll see
what will happen. For example, we will
need a 3° draft angle.
And here is the side of the ball. And
you'll notice
that we have kind of not logical
combination. Here you have the positive
draft and then get the negative draft
and again you'll get a positive drop.
This side might be very difficult as we
said to be injected with the direction
of pole is the top plane
and we know we said that we made the
parting line on the right plane. Let's
go back to one of our part or the mobile
cover. As you remember, we added a draft
when we performed a draft analysis and
we added a draft
and fixed all the faces over there.
So, it is important to get a draft to
make the part easier to extract.
For example, we can run draft analysis.
This make a part new part.
Let's extract
a cylinder
and perform a draft analysis.
Here you'll notice that there are a side
that need a draft
in order to be easier to be extracted.
So here are required drop that why the
draft feature is important in injection
molding tools. So we can make a draft
pick draft and here the neutral plane
would like to be this plane and face to
draft
this face. Click okay. And now let's
perform the draft analysis and pick this
face
and the reference
five.
Click okay. Now here our part is green.
So in order to make it a bigger draft
angle for example 3° we can
edit the draft
to make it 3° draft angle.
Click okay and the draft you can make
inside or outside.
And let's run the draft analysis. Pick
this space. And here the reference to be
2°. And we have our cup is
green.
And now let's talk about the next
feature, the move face. We said when we
are performing the parting line
analysis, we get the
The parting line, for example, in this
case is the edge. And if we would like
to expand this to make the parting line
join or to make an offset for that face,
we can use the move face feature. But in
this case, because this simple
cylinder or simple cup, the
parting line will not be shown. But we
can try to
use the move face. If we have the
direction of pull is the top plane and
we would like that
10 mm
on the other side to be
molded in the other side of the mold.
For example,
in the case of our V
So let's first
use the parting line or the move face on
this simple part. If we select the move
face, the option which will be used is
the offset but the used in our mold tool
case is offset. Select this offset and
we set 10 mm and here we move that face.
For example, for some reason that we
would like the parting line to be on the
top plane and the part over the top
plane will be injected on the other side
of the mold.
This is only an example. For example, if
we run the parting line analysis and we
pick the top plane here, we not see any
parting line because it will take the
edge. But with the help of split line,
we can
draw a sketch.
normal to and make
a 10 mm which
is on the origin.
[Music]
Split line and select the face
and here have our split line.
And as we said, this is only an example.
We can try to use it also on the face.
Go to move face, select, and we said
let's make it 30 mm.
Try to use it on the mobile.
For example, we would like to
extend
the edge of this face.
over here
to be matching the
the screw cylinders.
We can pick move face and
make it 1 mm.
Click okay.
But I will delete this feature for now.
And we can solve it by adding another
edge or a snap fit edge.
So now let's move to the next feature
which is also a very important feature
scale. As we know that materials are
expanding with heat and shrink when they
become colder and also it is the case
with plastic injected molded plastic or
uninjected molded parts. When they are
hot they are bigger in volume and when
they are getting colder they shrink.
That why for example this mobile if we
would like to have to inject this mobile
with the size shown here we should add
in consideration that this plastic part
will shrink for example 5%.
For that reason to solve this you need
to add a scale. You have
many option but the most used is the
centroid. It will scale
and here you pick uniform scaling and we
will make it 5% bigger. It means 1.05.
So this is the part
which you need to design a mold for it.
This is tutorial number 181. In this
tutorial, we will start talking about
the last section in the mold tools menu,
which it is the actual tools for
creating the mold.
In the previous tutorial, we had a look
at the surface features section and then
the analysis section and the solid
feature sections. And this section will
start with the insert mold feature. So
it is the very first thing which is a
good practice to do is to insert a mold
folder which will include the mold parts
such as cavity core and so on. So in
this tutorial we will talk about the
insert mold folder which it is the first
command and see where to locate the mold
folder and then we will talk about some
terms
which are included in the insert mode
folders like cork cavity and parting
line and then we will see some reference
pages to read more about molding before
continue
making the mold.
Here is our mobile cover which we made
in one previous tutorial and we see how
to perform draft analysis and added
draft which is required and also we
perform undercut analysis and parting
line analysis on the same part. And
after fixing what is required, now it's
time to create a mold for this mobile
cover. As we said before, we need to
insert a mold folder. This kind of
arrangement which will include the mold
part. So click on the insert mold and
you will notice nothing changed or
nothing is shown here. But it is
actually a mold folder is inserted
and it is under the surface folder
and also you notice that insert mode
command is deactivated.
So let's now show the
inserted mode folder.
We need to show the surface folder which
we can find it under the
feature
manager. Go to option feature manager
and here you have the surface bodies
folder. So here you can click automatic
or show. In this case we'll make it
show. Click okay. And if you notice here
is the surface bodies folder and if you
expand it you will get the mold folder
which include the cavity surface bodies
core and parting bodies.
So that's why it is important if you
don't have any background in molding or
new it's good practice to read a little
bit about the cavity core parting
surfaces and I have some reference pages
on Wikipedia. I will attach it in the
description below to read about it. So
it will be when we continue creating the
mold. For example, here is a page which
contain many good information and here I
have picture which is found on the same
page.
If you notice here you will see the
cavity which is located over there and
the parting line which we talked about
it earlier over there. And there are
more terms as well.
And for the core surface body, the core
actually is the secondary mold side
which will be used to cover the side
cuts which we talked about it in the
previous tutorial about the undercut
analysis.
And about the parting surfaces. And
about the parting surface, we use the
parting line analysis to locate or to
view where to locate the parting lines
or and later on it will be a parting
surface when we move on with the
features or the commands in the next
tutorials.
Here if we go back to the face which we
talked about in the previous tutorial
and we said if we made a parting line
analysis
and we took the direction of pole we got
two parting lines
over there. So you may wonder how be
molded. So in this case there's a mold
called a threeplated mold.
We can see
a preview over there. But we still
instead we can do it when we pick
the front line as the direction of pull.
This is only an example. This can be
produced by other cheaper ways.
This is tutorial number 182. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the next
section or the next command, the parting
lines
and it is different than the parting
line analysis and we will talk about
them and we will see how to insert a
parting lines in two cases. The first
case is the mobile cover where the
product in one block
and the second example be the face where
the product is laying between two blocks
mold blocks and then we will have a look
at some parting line issues and how to
solve them and how to select the edges
and have a look again at the mold folder
and how it changed.
So here we have the mobile cover which
we made in one of the previous tutorials
and we perform a parting line analysis.
The parting line analysis will give you
a preview where the parting line will be
located. We run the parting line
analysis for this mobile cover and we
selected the top plane as the direction
of pole but we didn't see any parting
line. So this is not an issue because
solder considered this product or this
part will be included in the first block
of the mold. So the parting line will be
on the edge over there. So now we can
select the parting line which insert the
actual or the real parting line for our
mole. So click on the parting line and
here you get the options.
So the direction of pull
is the top plane. But before we
inserting the parting line, we need to
insert the
mold folder which we said about in the
previous tutorial. Click on the insert
mold folder.
And here we have the insert or the mold
folder.
So now after selecting the insert more
folder pick the parting line the
direction of pole is the top plane
and then the draft angle which we did
about it in the draft analysis tutorial.
As as you remember, we already performed
a draft analysis and it is ready for
this process. So, we said we pick it
half degree and then here you can
perform draft analysis one more time. As
you notice, we don't have any issues
with this
product because we already performed the
draft analysis
before.
And if notice the parting line which are
the edges
selected automatically over here and you
can see them in purple
over there. If you have a look to the
edge, you can see the parting line which
we couldn't see in the parting line
analysis. So this is the place of the
parting line. And when you are done and
about the colors, we already talked
about them in the draft analysis
tutorial.
And there is no need for splitting the
faces because
the parting line on the edge. And we
will have a case in the next example
where we need to use the split faces.
And when you are done, click okay. So
now we have the parting line and we know
that the top part of this product will
be laying on the upper half of the mold
or the
in one block of the mold.
And here what I mean as we said in the
tutorial before when we showed you this
picture
the mobile cover will be laying
on let's say the left side of the block
and the parting line will be
you can imagine over there.
And if you look to the feature trees,
you will see the parting line option
is over there and you can edit it
any time.
So now let's have a look at the next
example. The place where the product
will be laying between two blocks.
So we have the
to insert the mold further and then go
to the parting line
and select the direction of ball.
Direction of ball is the front plane
and let's say one degree
draft or let's make it zero
in this case.
This is only an example just to avoid
seeing the faces that they need trapped.
And let's run a drop analysis. You'll
see
that there is no any parting line is
selected.
So in this case you need to use plate
faces
and then you are able to select the
parking line.
Select over there and over there. Click
okay.
We already knew that the parting line
should be laying over there because we
run the parting line analysis before.
But as you notice, we have a parting
line warning that not all the parting
line are selected. If we edit again here
you are not able to select any parting
line on the top side or on the
but on the bottom you can select
this edge
click okay but still we are not able to
select on the top over there so I'm
going to delete this parting line and
see how we can solve it.
So delete. And here we have affiliate.
I would suppress this feature and
suppress the dome in there or down
there. But we can make it a bit easier.
But still you can have them and split
them as well. And here we will try to
insert
parking line again
front plane
drop analysis
and split faces.
And this time you don't see any line or
any edge lit in the bottom.
So exit from here and we will start a
sketch on this face
and draw a line parallel to the front
plane.
Make sure that it is covering or
exceeding the
product.
and go to the mold tools and split line
feature which we talked about and here
it comes handy. So here is the current
sketch and faces to split this face and
this face. Click okay. So now we have to
split it faces. Hide this line or this
sketch
and run the
parting line analysis one more time. and
pick the front plane.
Run the draft analysis
split faces. And now we are able to
select
this edge and this edge. And here we
have the top edge
and in the bottom
edge.
And when you are done, click okay.
And here we have the parting line is
working or showing without any
warnings.
And here if we go back to the
mold folders and have a look you will
see that the cavity surface body we have
one body and the core surface body is
again another body. So you can see that
the cavity body is the green one and the
core body is the red over there.
So you can imagine that one side is one
block and the other side on the second
block.
Welcome to tutorial number 183. In this
tutorial, we will talk about the shut
off surfaces. The next feature in the
more tool section.
In this tutorial, we will talk about
what the shut off surfaces and why we
need them. And we will see how to insert
them and have a look at the selection
manager options and surfaces types and
look at the cases when we need to insert
the shut off surfaces manually
and then have a look at the mode
folders. So simply the shut off surfaces
are shutting the holes in the products.
For example, we have holes representing
the buttons and the speaker holes.
So closing these holes are the shut off
surfaces. But why we need to add the
shut off surfaces? As you remember from
the previous tutorial, we inserted the
parting line for this mobile cover which
represent the lines between the core and
cavity the mold parts.
But if you again edit the parting line
feature, you would notice a message over
there. The parting line is complete but
the mold cannot be separated. So the
reason why we need to add a shut of
surface is to add more parting or
parting surfaces for to separate between
the border of the mold parts the core
and cavity. So you will know where is
which part will do the cavity and which
part will do the core.
So let's see how it works. Here is the
shut off surfaces. If you click on shut
off surfaces, it will automatically
shuts the holes over there because they
are simple holes. And if you notice the
shut off surfaces, they are not shown.
If you go down in the selection manager,
click show preview. So you'll see a
preview for the shot. Or now we are
shutting these holes. So you can imagine
the part to the right of the surface is
in the part of the core and the holes
or to the left are are in the cavity
part. So the cavity will be responsible
for creating these holes or otherwise
and that we will see when we creating
this mold.
And here you have the edges edges which
are selected. You can change which part
will do which. For example, we can clear
selection and select
the
edges over here.
So you'll notice the sides to the left
of the surface are in the part of the
core.
In other word, we can call them parting
surfaces,
but we still have the rest of the hole
need to be selected in order to the mold
to recognize the part of the core and
the cavity.
And here you have the need option in
case if there are many surfaces. So you
will decrease the number of surfaces.
So I will close the shut off surfaces
and I will suppress the fillet option in
the
mobile cover
fillet five. And to make it easier
for selection and you can still have
fillet and select them manually here.
We'll click on the parting line again.
You'll notice
the part the shut of surfaces
selected all the holes.
And now if you go down over there we can
show preview and create surfaces.
And here are the types of the surfaces.
So in this side if you notice
this face is straight. So it can be
enough to have the contact option. But
in case there are some
curves and you need the surface to match
this curve, you can change the type into
tangent. You can click on the
window over there and change it to
tangent
and here we have also type over there
you have no fill and you have all
contact
and all tangent. If you click on the all
tangent will convert all the types to be
tangent and if you click on the all
contact will convert all the type into
contact and here we can show call outs
or hide them to make it easier to see.
So now I will keep the default selection
and when I'm done I click okay.
So now we have the ch of surfaces are
there. So you can see a better you can
imagine the shape of the mold or the
core and the shape of the cavity.
But in some cases maybe this mobile
cover might be simple. have straight
faces. But in some cases the shot of
surface can be difficult to to make or
to be select by default and we need in
that case to make them manually. And we
will have an example about that later on
in the case when we create the
shut of surfaces manually. And how we
can use the surface commands over there
to create our shut off surfaces.
And now let's check if we succeed to
create the shut off surface and the
parting line. If we go back edit the
shape of surface
here, you'll notice we get a green
message. The mold can be separated and
solid work can differentiate between the
mold parts, the core and the cavity.
So a few steps remaining to create the
actual mold.
One last thing for the surface which we
created. They are only surfaces and they
are not affecting the solid body and
they are just borders. And if we have if
you need to have a look at these
surfaces, you can find them under the
mold folders. expand it over there.
And here you have the cavity surfaces
and the surface bodies and the parting
bodies. So
here you can see
the core
surfaces
which are in red.
You can see them. And these are the core
side of the surfaces. And here are the
cavity side of the surfaces.
So the cavity represent the green color
and the core surface the red color and
they are equal in the number.
Tutorial number 184. In this tutorial,
we will talk about the next command in
the mold tools menu, the parting
surface. And we will see what are the
parting surface and why we need them and
see how to insert parting surfaces and
have a look at the selection manager
options and the surfaces types. And then
we will see how to edit the parting
surface manually when and why. And then
have a look at the end at the mold
folders. Here we have the mobile cover
from the previous tutorial where when we
perform the shut off surfaces which are
now ready. And you may wonder this shut
of surfaces are
the parting surface between the mold
parts cavity and core but on the border
of the mobile but the mold exceeding the
border of the mold. So that is the work
of the parting surface is to extend the
shut off surfaces. So in other word the
parting surfaces parting surfaces are
extend to the shut off surfaces. We
called also the shut off surfaces as
well parting surfaces but on the mobile
area.
And for the parting surface, it takes
the
parting lines as a reference from where
it will extend.
So as you notice here, we have the red
shut off surface on the mobile and here
it ends on the parting lines. And now we
will extend that surface to cover the
mold blocks. To insert a parting
surface, click on the parting surface
over there. And here you will get the
options.
In this case, we will pick the
perpendicular to P surface because we
know the P surface for the mobile cover
which was the top plane which is already
selected over there. But in some
products
you need to choose normal to surface
or tangent to surface.
So in case of we picking the tangent
surf to surface it you will not notice
any difference because it will be
already tangent to the pole surface. But
if we pick the normal to surface you
will see the
difference over there. But in this case
we don't have any complicated product
and this might be easy to extract and it
is enough to perpendicular to the pole.
And here the parting line as we said it
is the edges or from where you extend
the surface
and the parting surface. Here you can
reverse the direction of the parting
surface. But this is not the right case.
We need to reverse the direction. And
here we can make it more for example 10
size
here make it 50.
And here you have the angle. In case if
we use normal to surface here you are
able to change as well
the
angle of the surface related to the
parking line. Here for example
if we increase it but as we said we will
pick the perpendicular
to the pole.
And here you select the type of
smoothing.
If you pick the two player, you might
not see any difference because we don't
have any sharp edges or
open edges. So you not notice any
difference. We will try to have an
example with another case where the
parting surface is separated.
And in the last options we have need all
surfaces. In this case we have only one
surface
and there is no more than any surface.
So that will not make any difference.
Here is the preview and the manual mode.
Here you can
modify
or edit
the parting surface
if you have a more complicated chip. But
in this case, we don't need to use the
manual mode because this is the default
chip. And as we said, we will have
another case where we need to edit the
parting surface manually. So this look
fine. And when you are done, click okay.
So here we have the parting surface
which is going to separate between the
core and cavity outside the parting
line. And now let's have a look at the
mold folders from the previous tutori.
You remember we have 22 cavity surface
bodies which represent the inside over
there and 22 for the core. And we have
one more surface. So the total number of
surfaces are 45
and all of them will have a purpose to
separate between the core and cavity.
And here is the parting surface which we
added
in this tutorial.
Tutorial 185. In this tutorial, we talk
about the next command, the tooling
split or in other word, creating the
mold blocks, the core and cavity. And we
will see how to select the face and see
some cases about it. And then after
creating the blocks, see how to move
them and see the effect of shut off
surfaces on the blocks. And then see how
we can spread
them and save them in separate parts for
further editing. Here we have our mobile
cover from the previous tutorial where
we made the parting surface and we
selected this surface to be
perpendicular to the direction of pole.
So we already know that this surface is
perpendicular to the parting line.
So now let's try to add a tooling split
which in other word are the the mold
cubes. Click on the tooling split and
here you have two options to select the
plane and or if there is an existed
plane or sketch. So here we need to
select a face. There are many way to
select the face. The first option we
know that this surface is perpendicular
to the direction of pole. So you can you
are able to sketch on it. But this is
not the case because sometimes this
surface as we said can be with an angle
if we go to editing the
parting surface. Our option was
perpendicular to the pole. But in some
cases it can has an angle as we see as
we talked about in the previous
tutorial. So there's another way to
select the
this surface to create the tooling split
because we already know that is this
face is perpendicular to the parting
line. And third option which I will
choose because when we started to design
this mobile cover we added in mind that
this face will be matching the top plane
and will be the splitting surface or the
plane which will separate the mold
blocks. So I'm going to select the top
plane so that so here I will select the
top plane
and
start a sketch
normal too. And here again when we
design we made it that the origin to be
in the center of the mobile. So here I'm
going to select directly a center point
rectangle from the center of the mobile
and draw a rectangle which represent the
mold blocks.
And here I can add a dimension according
to the design. So this is an example we
can make
150 and
100.
Click okay. And now I can exit from the
sketch. So we have our existing sketch
and go to tooling split and the sketch
is selected. And here you can specify
the block size. I will make it 50 in
each
direction. And here if you would like to
add an extra face to interlock surface
to be between the blocks but I will
uncheck this
for now. And here we have the shut off
surfaces
the 22 which we made in the previous
tutorial when we talked about the shut
off surfaces. So all of these surfaces
are included in the mold blocks and as
you remember we have 22 surfaces
the core surfaces. If we expand the
surface body
here, we have 22 for the core which are
selected over there
and the same for the cavity
surfaces
and for the parting surface which we
made in the previous tutorial is also
selected. So all the
so all the surfaces under the surface
body are selected.
And when you are done click okay.
And here we have the mold blocks the
core and the cavity.
I'll just assign some appearance.
Here
if you click on the tuning split you
will see the mold blocks are selected at
once but the whole file is including
three bodies the core the cavity and the
mobile cover. And if we go to the solid
bodies you'll see the bodies over there.
And here is the mobile cover. And here
we have the
core. And the top is the cavity.
For now, I will suppress this feature
and we'll get back to it again.
Suppress. But in this case, we will try
to make a tooling split on a different
face and select the sketch directly.
Click on tooling split. Select this
face.
You'll notice and sketch has been open.
Click normal tool and quickly make
the rectangle. And as you notice, click
okay.
Here we created a block but on the wrong
face.
So according to the face which you are
going to select solid walls going to
create the mold. If you try to hide the
upper block hide you will still see that
the block is laying between the parting
surface. But this is not the correct
positioning of the sketch because if we
again show
the block you will see there are not
equal in size. Here we have 55 and here
the length is 45 and if we go to the
feature we have here 50 and 50. So if
you select the wrong plane, solar work
still will pick the parting surface as
the splitting between the moles, but you
will get a wrong positioning of the
block.
So I will suppress or delete this
process and show our first
block over there. And here hide this
sketch.
Now let's try to move the blocks.
Move.
Select on the block. And you can simply
drag.
Click. Okay. And again
we move the core
and we'll have a look
at the mold from inside.
So as we remember we picked the shut off
surfaces and now you can see
that
you can see that on the cavity of the
mold. So as you remember we picked the
shut off surfaces to be in the button
side of the cover and here you see
here on the cavity
over there.
So we can also hide the parting surface
So here we have our
mold blocks.
So, one last thing in this tutorial, if
you would like to save the blocks in a
separated files for further editing, for
example, making runners and or fixing
holes, click on the solid bodies folder
and save bodies. In order to save each
body in a separated file, you can select
the body you need and then save it in in
aspirated part file.
This is tutorial 186. In this tutorial,
we'll talk about the next feature in the
mold tools, the core feature.
And we will see what is the core and
why. And then we will perform an
undercut analysis. And then again we'll
make a new mole for a new case. That
will be also a good review for the
previous steps. And then see how to make
a core.
The core simply is another side of the
mold. As we said before, there are two
part parts of the mold. The core and
cavity. And there is also a side core.
And the purpose for it is to reach the
areas that can be difficult to be made
by the core and the cavity. For example,
for this bucket and if you see the
handle over there and you can imagine
how we can extract from the mold. So
that will be kind of impossible. And you
need either to solve this issue or add a
core
to the mold or a side core. So first
let's go to our previous example the
mobile cover and roll back to the
previous steps
before performing any parting line. And
as you remember we performed an undercut
analysis for this mobile and we picked
the top plane as the direction of pole.
And if you notice, we didn't have any
issues or red areas
which represent any problem with the
undercut faces.
So for that reason we will create
another part and show you where we have
an undercut issues that they need to be
fixed or to create a core for it. So let
me show you quickly with this pocket I
have here and we will create it later on
on this tutorial. But here I will show
you an undercut analysis for this part.
Pick the undercut analysis and here is
the direction of port. You'll notice the
red areas over there which represent the
undercut
faces which we need to fix
in order to make this bucket
producible with the injection molding.
So click okay. One way to fix this issue
is to eliminate these
handles. For example, if we go to this
undercut and suppress and run the
undercut analysis, pick the direction of
pole.
Here we don't have any red areas, but we
still need the handles. Click
exit and unsuppress
the handle. Also one way is to create
another cut or to expand the cut
edit sketch
and for example
make it something like this but we will
still have undercut under there. If you
go to undercut analysis, click the
direction of pole, you'll see use have
under there except
normal to and here you can make this
point to be over there and give a
dimension.
And if we perform undercut analysis
here we solve this issue. So you have an
a view.
So you have a view right now. What we
mean with undercut analysis they are the
faces which are difficult to be
extracted and which can be represented
with red color with the undercut
analysis. So now let's create this
pocket to make a mold for it and then
create a core to solve the handle
issues. I'll start
new part.
Go to the top plane and draw center
point rectangle. Give the dimension 200
by
400 mm
and fill it the corners
with
40 mm.
Extrude it to
mm and give it a draft of 10°
angle.
And here
make a fillet of 20 mm
and chill it
or 20 mm. It might be thick but
I made it thick in purpose to make it
clear in previewing the undercut areas.
So now let's create the handle cuts.
Pick the right plane. Start the sketch
center point slot
and give it a dimension of
by
100 or
80.
this point the origin vertical and here
35 mm
and extrude it cut
from the both sides.
So here we have our bucket and now let's
perform a draft or start again start
again making a mold and review the
previous options. Go to the mold tools
menu start with the draft analysis.
The direction of pole is this face. And
we have the minimum draft we need is
three degrees. And here is fully green.
So this face will have no problem to be
extracted. But here we have still some
issues under the hand.
But the draft analysis for this part is
okay. Now we need to perform undercut
analysis. Is this face here? You will
notice the red areas.
So with the undercut analysis, we know
that the handles now need to be fixed
later on when we start creating a mold.
So let's perform under a parting line
analysis and click this face. We don't
see any preview but we will see that
later when we start creating a model. So
now let's make a parting line or insert
a parting line. Click on the parting
line.
Click on that face
and the minimum we say 3° for the angle.
Perform a draft. Here we have the green
over there.
Click.
Okay. And there is no faces need to be
split.
We have our parting line.
Then now the next step the shut off
surfaces. Click on shut off surfaces.
The edges to be closed.
Let's select them manually here.
And here we can make show preview
and make it all contact.
And again select
the edges
of this handle.
And here we have the green message over
there. Click okay. Now the shut off
surfaces
are done. The next command the parting
surfaces.
And here we'll keep the option probic.
And here we and here we can
giving the parting surface distance of
300.
Click okay.
Now creating the core and cavity by
touring split.
Select
this surface.
The sketch has been open and
create the center point rectangle
and give it a dimension 500 by 70.
And here we can and here we give it
350 for the core and 200 for the cavity.
Click okay. And here we have the mold.
So until this step, you should be
familiar with all the previous processes
because we discussed them in the
previous tutorials.
Here we can expand the solid bodies
folder and hide the core
or the cavity
of the mold.
which it is the upper side of the mold.
So now we have the bucket is showing
over there. And now time to create a
core for the handle. Click on the core.
And here you will ask it will ask you to
select a plane where you need to create
the core. So it is clear that we need to
create a core for this handle. So we
going to select this face and a sketch
have been open. Make it normal too. Now
we will draw that have an angles so that
the side core can be fixed
in a place in the upper side of the
block or on the core. Here I will select
the line
and draw this shape
center point.
And here give the dimension
of 100.
And here you can give it dimension of
100 75.
And this distance to this distance
can make it
120.
There we can make a symmetric
relation.
As you can see the upper line is on the
edge of of the bokeh.
And here we have the sketch is fully
defined. Here we can add affiliate
and here as well click okay
and when you click okay
exit you'll notice solid works will
automatically generate the side core
and
You will see the sketch which we made is
selected and the direction
it selected a face inside. But
to be sure with the direction we select
this edge because you can imagine the
side core will be dragged in that
direction. And here for the core of the
cavity you need to specify from where
the core will be extracted. So in this
case will be the upper side of the mole
or the cavity which we hided over there.
We can here select
and the tooling or the uppart side of
the mold is selected and here we can
specify a draft and the direction we
need to reverse the direction over
there. So that is the direction
and here we need to
give a dimensions for the extrusion
for the first for the first direction we
need to make sure that the extrusion is
exceeding the mold block. And for the
other direction we need to make sure
that it is meeting the part we can make
it. There is no need for incap because
the side will be matching the block.
Click okay. And here we have the core is
gen. So now we can show the upper side
of the mold.
And if you notice on the
solid bodies, we have a core bodies
folder.
So the same core process can be repeated
on the other handle.
And for now, let's try to move the mold
blocks.
the core and the cavity
and then
the side core.
So here is the shape of the side core
which will be
add it to the mold in order to create
this handle.
Hello and welcome to a new tutorial in
solid works learning series. This is
tutorial number 187 in mold tools. In
this tutorial, we will talk about the
cavity feature. In the previous
tutorial, we talked about the core
feature. So, it will come to your mind
that there should be a cavity feature as
well, but it is not shown or activated
in the mold tools menu.
The
cavity feature is not a main method for
making molds. It aims to make fast
blocks molds for presentations
and there is no need to follow the
previous mold
commands or instruction which we talked
about in the previous tutorials. So
let's start a new assembly or let's
first start making
product.
I will make a fast hotel.
So here is the bottle. We need to make a
mold for it. So we have to be in the
assembly mode. If we go to the mold and
here we can search for the cavity
and it's still not activated. So we need
to be in the
assembly mode. We can start an assembly
from the part.
So here we can insert the
part in the origin.
And to make the
two blocks of the mold, we need to first
insert the first block.
Insert
component new part. So here we can call
it
upper block.
Go to
open or edit part.
Here we can select the
the plane dry plane and start the
sketch.
So we need not to include the cap
section of this
here. We can draw
with the rough dimensions.
[Music]
So, here's the first
block of the mold. Now if we go to the
cavity
save the part then
here we can delete the internal Right.
Go to insert feature and then delete or
keep buries. Here we can select the
inside cavity. Okay.
So here you can try to hide the
bottle. Then we have created the cavity.
Since this is a symmetrical bottle, so
we can duplicate the block. Hold control
and here we have the
lower part of cit or the second part. So
we can try to make
So, here's a a fast method to create the
two blocks of the mold without the need
of following the previous
commands.
And this is only for fast molds.